mean, what is it that you want to protect? Things on the inside. To be strictly strict
about it, I mean, this is sort of an old-fashioned intranet, but really it's like the private
network. And it has all this trust, the posts and other stuff and other networks and equipment
and printers and, I don't know, IoT devices and whatever you have. I think there's a big
bad world outside. If the world wasn't bad, we wouldn't need firewall. So the world is
big and the world is bad. And the typical thing here is that you have a router that connects
you to the, like ISP, right? Or if you are, if the organization itself is already its own
ISP, connects you to the long haul. Remember autonomous systems? Yeah, I'm talking about
autonomous domain, autonomous systems that provide like long distance services. So anyway,
this connects you to the rest of the world. And then here you have this firewall. And the
firewall is your sort of first line of defense, right? Router is not a firewall. Sometimes
they can live in the same platform, but logically a router and a firewall are two very different
things. Router's job, main job, is to route packets and to maintain a routing table and
to exchange information with other routers about reachability and congestion and all things
like that. It does not generally perform security tasks. Its main job is not security. Firewall's
main job, the only job is security. There's no other job that a firewall has, just security.
Now here, this is again a bit old fashioned terminology, but often referred to as DMZ or demilitarized
zones. Okay? So this is where you put your publicly accessible servers, like your web server,
right? Or your VPN server, or some other server, or customer support, whatever. So things that
you want to be accessible from the outside with less scrutiny, anybody should be able to access
at least the company web server, right? Every company that, you know, unless they're super secretive,
right? 99% and more probably of the entities, right? Commercial entities have web presence. What
that means is they have a web server. Now some of them do it like this. Some of them host a
web server out on a third party provider. Okay? But many do this. They just put it in a DMZ. And
the firewall will make sure that traffic can go to the DMZ with no scrutiny. But the DMZ itself
is separate, physically disconnected from the rest. So there's no line. If there is a line
here, that's a recipe for a disaster. Okay? So if there's anything you remember, or one of
the few things you should remember about this lecture, that if you have a DMZ, its only connection
should be to the firewall. Okay? And there should be zero connection here. Okay? So I already
mentioned the moat. But, important thing, before you start thinking and have your mindset
that O is a big bad world and we ought to protect our precious resources from the big bad world.
It is true, but it's not the entire truth. In addition to that, you want to protect yourself from
things coming out. Why do you care about things coming out? Not just going in. Anybody?
We are a military or some company with some security technology. Okay? Let's develop this. Let's go
further. What is the general thing we are looking for here? To prevent?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. But what kind of attacks?
Perfect shovel. Okay? Perfect shovel.
Okay? But there's a term for this. We used that term before. Insider attacks. Insider attack.
Rogue employees, right? They happen, right? Rogue employees. Somebody knows they are going
to be axed on a day tomorrow. They can cause damage. They can put a bomb, a logic bomb somewhere.
They can exfiltrate the information. What about malware? Joe Schmo comes to work.
Total doofus. Not a malicious person. Sticks a USB that he brought from home to watch some movies
during lunch break into his work computer. And damn! Malware jumps from USB over to the laptop
or desktop and starts exfiltrating sensitive information. You have an unwitting insider.
But essentially what you have is malware. Okay? That sits on the inside and exfiltrates information.
That is why it is very important to control who goes in and who goes out. Just like in a castle
with a moat. It's not there just to control who comes in. It's also to see what comes out.
So make sure you remember that. The firewall is two-way. So location of course as you saw
in the picture is typically between the external and internal network, right? It could also be
inside your private network separating various parts, various departments. That makes sense.
It makes sense. It makes sense in certain government agencies like three-letter agencies. It makes sense
in military settings, right? Where you have strict compartmentalization of information. That there
would be a firewall even within the internal network, right? But that means that the internal network
is sort of naturally subdivided into smaller networks. Okay? You could also have it on your own machine.
On your own machine. So if you are running Windows, you might be running a personal firewall, right?
Microsoft personal firewall. I think on Linux, there is also like at least several packages
that will install a local firewall for you. Anybody configured their own firewall?
You and I? Nobody else? Nobody uses Windows? Nobody uses Linux? Okay. It's so fine. Most people
don't come across this. Okay, so important thing. That firewall is a nice concept, but it essentially
leaves a lot of room for deciding where to put it. Which layer? Remember the session, sorry, remember the
sort of rough seven layer hierarchy, right? Network particles, right? Network particles stack. Why?
You don't put it in the physical layer. Okay? That's like silly. You don't put it in the MAC layer because
the MAC or data layer because that's one hump, right? And it's like, what's the point of a firewall?
It's at the MAC layer. So the lowest layer where you can place the firewall is the network layer.
Because remember the network layer is hopping around the internet. It's the common layer of the entire internet.
So you cannot put it lower than the network layer. How high can you put it? Well, you can put it all the way
up to the application layer. And that leaves a lot of choice. Okay? So the simplest one is the packet
possession filtering router that is placed at roughly the network layer. Roughly, I say kind of, let's say
you're doing the network energy. Another approach is called proxy gateway. But proxy gateway means
that actually traffic terminates. So instead of just examining packets one by one, this proxy gateway
will actually like terminate the connection. And we start a new one. So it will be like stitching out
two connections. Does that make sense? Right? And this can be done at circuit level, which is application
independent, using sockets, right? Socket layer. And then it can also be done at application level layer. And that
requires designing kind of a custom application gateway. Right? And maybe, I suspect some of you have
already seen this in the real world. If you weren't like in the real world, you may have seen this. Okay?
These types of things. And then of course the personal firewall, you set up your own rules and this could
work at almost any layer, but generally it's a network layer. So we're not going to talk much about this. We're going to
focus on the first two, the packet and proxy gateway. Questions so far? Okay. So just a pictorial representation of
what I just mentioned. Internet and then you have this security perimeter, right? Which is a network security perimeter
where your private network is located. And this packet filtering router, which is the firewall, located there. And
all it does, it does it fast. Because it looks at a packet at a time, and it doesn't keep state about anything.
It just looks at one packet and says, source, destination, protocol, maybe what's the next protocol, maybe
port number, and like length and things like that. It says, what is this? What is this? Do I let it go or do I not?
So it just makes a decision. Let it go or drop. Very quickly. Okay? It does not consult much except maybe some
kind of a table. Okay? You'll see an example. Then you have a circuit level gateway, which basically splices connections.
So here you have an outside connection, let's say, that terminates here. And if you took a networking course, you've seen
the concept of virtual circuits, right? So essentially, this is a virtual circuit. Right? So there's one that goes
in here, in, and then it's translated into this. So this allows, you know, circuit level filtering. Right? Because it's all
socket based. Okay? But port based, if you will. And here you have application level gateway, where what happens
is you want to, let's say, telnet, right? Remote telnet, like a remote login, right? You want a remote login
from the outside to the inside. But what you first do is you actually log in to this application level gateway.
That's like a first line. And then from there you go to the actual place inside you want to go. So it's
really like translating to telnet session, to telnet session. One to here and one to here. And the same
would go for file transfer, SMTP, HTTP, etc. It's a real like proxy. Okay? And so this has the most information
about traffic, right? Because this looks at the actual application. So if an application
is not allowed, there's no proxy, the traffic is discarded by this gateway. So for example,
if you try to use, I don't know, some strange protocol that is not supported, right? Some kind
of a, some kind of a new app or something that's not supported. It says, oh, I only support telnet
TPS and TPS to be by. Okay? Whereas a certain level admin might not, might not notice that,
right? Because it doesn't see the application context. Yeah. So starting with, let's start
with packet filtering. So as I said, the decision is done per packet, without any other context
of whether this packet is part of a connection or not. Just look at individual packets. Okay?
What does it look for? Mainly IP source destination address and port numbers.
Protocol identifier, remember the IP header has protocol identifier. And when I say port
numbers, of course port numbers are not inside the IP header. That's inside TCP header or UDP header.
So look at both network layer and transport layer. There are some super simple firewalls,
also packet level filters that only look at the IP header. It's faster that way. Okay?
And I'll tell you why it's faster. Because remember IP has fragmentation. Remember I talked about
how IPv4 has fragmentation. So when the TCP segment is given to IP on the sending side, it could be large. Yeah?
And so the IP then will, if it's too large to be fit in one IP packet, it will chop it in fragments.
Well, only the first fragment will have the TCP header. Right? The other fragments could be like in the middle, right?
Or somewhere. So they won't have a TCP header. So you can't check the port numbers. Not good. Right?
If you want to filter by port numbers, you can't. Although the IP header won't tell you is the next
protocol is TCP. But it won't tell you what the port numbers are because the header isn't present in the
fragment. So that presents a problem. Also, you will, so one way to do so is to disallow fragments.
So some of these packet filters, right? These packet filtering gateway, they will discard
fragmented packets. They simply like return an ICMP. What's called an ICMP? They say no
fragmentation. Don't fragment. But I want to ask, like, when fragmentation is
usually because the router cannot send a large package. So...
Well, a router can only send a packet as large as what's called MTU of the next link. MTU is
the maximum transmission unit. So that's hard-coded in a given link. So for a given
router, you know, it has this interface. It's more than, at least two, right? That's why
it's a router. So for each interface, it has an MTU. So when it receives a packet, obviously
it's big enough to fit, right? But when it sends a packet, it has to look, is that packet
it's going to fit in the MTU on the next link. Okay? That's how IP works. Does that make sense?
But all I mean is that, like, between the routers in a network, you cannot, like, control the
router MTU between the routers. You cannot. You cannot. But there's something called MTU discovery.
I mean, generally today, so there's, like, the protocol, the way to describe the spec IP, the
way it's described, and the way it's implemented. So the way it's implemented today is more routers
do not fragment packets. And I tell you what. So theoretically, it should, it can be supported,
it should be supported, but it's not done because internet routers, and this has nothing to do with
security. Internet routers are supposed to process packets fast. Fast. Okay? And there's something
called a fast path. Fast path is take a packet, look at the destination, points to the next
hop, send it. If anything deviates from that, today's most routers will drop the packet. Okay?
Because technically they are supposed to, oh, well, the next MTU is too small, I have to split
this packet into two parts. That's a lot of work for a router. It deviates very much from this fast path.
So that's why many of them don't do it. Okay? But, so that's assumed for the, for the rest of this
discussion, right? You understood what I, I hope that what I mentioned before, the problem with
fragmentation. But assume there's no fragmentation. Assume that the source of the IP packet sends in a small
enough packet that it will not be fragmented. Okay? Which means that every IP packet has a
TCP header. Let's just assume. It may not always be the case. Then what you can do is, of course,
you can look in a TCP header and say, oh, there's a port number, and look at TCP flags. Remember,
TCP flags indicate what kind of packet this is, right? Is it the beginning of the handshake cover
connection? Is it the end of the connection? Etc. And if it's not TCP, for example, above IP,
there could also be UDP, which presents a bit of a problem, or ICMP, which is control,
internet control message protocol, which I mentioned earlier. It's like a maintenance protocol.
Anyway, so filtering rules are based on pattern matching, and you'll see some examples.
Different gateways or different firewalls that are different vendors for different languages.
It's not like a unified language for describing rules. So if you work for a company that implements
a certain, or buys a certain product, a firewall product, you need to learn the language,
their policy language, if you're going to configure a firewall. You better learn it well,
because misconfigurations can cost nera. Now, at this point, remember SSL TLS. Right? Remember?
SSL TLS, you might think, presents a problem. Doesn't it? Well, not for this kind of firewall.
Because if you recall, SSL TLS starts encrypting things above TCP. Right? And not even that.
Some things are not even encrypted, right? Depending on which version it is, but it leaves some
of the things. But TCP here is available, because it's below SSL TLS. So that's not a problem here.
Okay? What about IPsec? Ooh, IPsec is a problem. IPsec could be a problem for firewalls that want
to look at the TCP header, because they can't. Right? They can't. But what a firewall could do
is say, you know what? You want to come for me? Build the first IPsec tunnel to me. Are you
following what I'm saying? So, there's my favorite marker. What's going on today? Well, okay.
I think you all remember IPsec, right? So the firewall would say, hey, you want to come from
the outside, and you want to use IPsec. No, no. First build an IPsec through me.
Right? And then it means the firewall will actually be the endpoint of IPsec tunnel. You will see
the actual IP packet when it decapsulates it, right? So here's one example. Yeah?
I mean, I'm assuming you want an IPsec tunnel elsewhere outside of the router, but using that,
they wouldn't guarantee the router would actually re-IPsec it to the next .
It may not need to. Remember that, David? We're talking generally IPsec tunnel from the outside
to the firewall. That's what I meant. From the outside to the firewall. Then the firewall
decapsulates, and then it may re-IPsec it again, right? Or not. That depends.
Let's look at the fact of filtering examples. This looks at the TCP, right? It includes the
TCP header. These are blocks of rules, right? And this is just kind of one very simple language.
And what it says is basically a table. It says action, our host, port, their host, port,
coming. A coming is usually not present, but it's just for an explanation. So the block A
over there says that, okay, the action is to block. So anything that has source destination,
our host, their host, but their host is named spigot, okay? Like the name of the host is spigot.
We don't allow it, okay? That's it. Don't allow it. The next rule says allow from our gateway,
right? Connection on port 25. Well that means port 25, TCP port 25 is SMTP email, right?
Fail. So we allow connections to, from any port, you see that says port any on the second port.
It says any, it says asterisk. Their host is asterisk means any. So any foreign host can connect
to our gateway on port 25, right? Connections to our SMTP port are okay.
Block B says do not allow anything. That's a default rule. So if something falls through all these
and it's not, does not trigger any of those rules, block B is an effect, right? Everything
that's not explicitly allowed is denied or blocked. That's all it says. That's a default rule.
Block C says allow us, right, us to connect to them on port 25. That is an internal host can
go outside and connect to port 25 anywhere. Just for email purposes, right? Because email
is considered safe. Block B says explicitly a set of our host. This is just like a short
handle. You actually like list all the explicit hosts, you know? Like it's different from an
asterisk, right? Asterisk means anything. Our host means a fixed set of our hosts.
It says that our packets to their SMTP port are okay. Again, port 25. And it also says that
anything coming back to our port 25 with an ACK set, flags, that's DCP flags. When it says
flags, you see that flag? That's DCP. It means that it's an acknowledgement, right? What it means
is an acknowledgement of something we said. So we allow ACKs to come back. And finally,
block E says allow our hosts to go out. Anything going out from our host is okay. Initiating from
our host is okay. Anything with an ACK flag is okay. Meaning anything coming back with an ACK flag
an ACK flag is fine. And finally, traffic to non-servers is okay. That is, if you're going outside to
any client, right? To anything that port greater than 1024, that is reserved for non-servers. So
TCP ports 1024 and below are reserved. There are like specific things. Like 25 is email. 80 is HTTP,
right? 443, I think it's SSL, TLS, right? Things like that. But they're all less than 1024.
So here's kind of a deeper dive. So let's look at FTP. Everybody knows FTP, right? File transfer
port. Did you all know that it actually works with your browser? They don't try it like if you use FTP
instead of HTTP in your URL. It still works, right? Your browser understands it.
So what you have here is a client and a server, right? So a client that wants to transfer a file,
one or more files. So the client starts by opening a connection on port. And its own port is 5151, right?
Says my port is 5151, but actually what the HTTP has is it reserves two special ports, right? It has
24 data. This is where, remember how SSL, TLS works? It has like a record layer and it has other. So
this is like a record layer. It's for bulk data. And this one is for commands. So it's like a control channel
and a data channel and a data channel. And they have different port numbers. Okay? So like FTP, if you remember
FTP syntax, get file, file name, is a command. It's transmitted on the command port. The actual file transfer
will happen on that port will happen on that port. Does that make sense? Commands as opposed to bulk data.
So the first thing is a connection request comes in on a random, with a random port number, right?
5151. You don't know what it is. And it's some client. And then it's okay, right? So that connection opens.
Then the next thing is the data channel. The server, the FTP server opens the data channel. And these are two,
these, these and this are two different TCP connections. Different port numbers, different TCP connections.
Alright? And so at the end, you have the final TCP connection acknowledgement. At the end of the
handshake, a TCP act from the client, and then the connection is over. This is just a refresher.
So what would the packet filter rule say? This is a different syntax from the one. The one I showed you
before was kind of very verbal, right? Very, very easy to parse. This one is a bit obscure.
But once you get used to it, it makes sense. So what does this actually say? It says access list 100.
That's which set of rules? It refers to a set of rules. 100. Permit TCP, okay? Allow TCP traffic
So what does that mean? Outsiders, outsiders coming in on any port on any port greater than 1,023. I misspoke before I said 1,024.
Well, actually it's 1,023. Greater than 1,023. So which needs client, okay?
For host. 178.168.178.14.37x.18x behavioshiven, oke?
For host. 178.168.10x.18x.18x.18x equals 21. noticeable
So what does that mean? Outsiders, outsiders coming in on any port greater than 1,0244.15. It's not a server. It's a client.
connecting to our host explicitly named for the IP address see that IP address that's our FTP
server internally on port 21 is okay that's permit second line says permit blah blah blah
same thing with a port 20 just says it's okay to have traffic to our FTP server our file server
from any client the second list or the second set of rules 101 says permit TCP host this is our host
right again it's that same FTP server to talk to on port 21 to any port that is greater than 1000.3
that is responding to the client okay and the same thing for 20 right so that's the second line here
just a lot so it's a it's a bi-directional right making it uni-directional wouldn't make any sense
right has to be bi-directional and then finally it says here this is interface ethernet zero that's
every every firewall will have to have at least two interfaces right one to the outside one to the
inside can have more than two but generally at least two so which interface does this apply well
this interface is within zero access list 100 is for inbound traffic access list 101 to outbound traffic
i know since everything's obscure but i mean that's not it's not a canonical language just an example of a
specific firewall language for a given file file provider but they all essentially communicate the same
information what is allowed what is not allowed
but despite the fact that they are fast right they have problems right the packet filter or the packet
filtering firewall is the fastest firewall you can have because it keeps no state or almost no state
it just basically looks at this the static rules that are encoded like a previous slide it says
do i let it in do i let it out do i drop it let it in drop let it in drop it that's it packet at the
time that's it now the problems uh if the attacks are application specific right somebody's trying to
exploit uh something it's a vulnerability in an application the packet filtering firewall will not catch
okay like buffer overflow uh it doesn't do user authentication obviously
right because of the network layer or even a transport layer you cannot authenticate the user that
might be at the other hand externally because the user does not sit at the network or transport
layer so you cannot authenticate authentication based on ip addresses is useless because anybody can spoof
like okay and so this type of firewalls they don't have upper or higher or higher layer functionality
because they're supposed to be fast so there are other things that uh they are susceptible to for
for example fermentation attacks uh that i'll talk about next then there's this configuration there's this whole
area of research of how to take a set of rules and decide whether they make sense because if you
understood my example both with the simple one with the table and the more complicated one
one the previous slide configuring those rules is not all that easy and it's also but it is easy to
to make mistakes so there's like a whole area of research and security on how to automatically
detect uh contradictions or nonsensical rules or redundant rules
i mean right and so these days a lot of of course ml is being used by that
so i'll tell you i'll give you an example of kind of a clever pupelet fragmentation attack
that typical packet filters will not catch
so this is a reminder to you of what ip header looks like right we saw this slide before
right just remember that options are well optional so typical ip packet ends here at the destination
right so typically it's like this right after source destination address there's a tcp header
i mean assuming we're using dc okay so what is a fragmentation attack well generally a fragmentation
attack uh it requires an adversary to craft fragments on ip back there they overlap
does that make sense overlapping yeah so normally again because i don't have a marker i can't draw
anything for you but normally you expect them to do oh all right
yeah normally you want to you have a packet that was long packet that was fragmented
like one two three four and you want to make sure when it's reassembled it's really like one and then
two three and then four and how do you know remember the fragment offset in the previous slide showed
you right fragment offset told you how far for example this packet starts at i don't know uh 513
which means that this is 512 bytes and the fragment offset for this packet will be 513
and if this packet is 100 bytes then the fragment offset here will be 613 okay and this this packet
is 100 bytes that will be 713 here so they all fit neatly one after the other right
but what if you screw around with a fragment offset and instead of 613 put 313 well the reassembling ip
destination will say oh well 313 i am going to stick to this packet here
right because it says that now if you know of such attacks you would of course look you would change
your ip right smart programmers who know how to code will say oh i should always check that
a new fragment does not overlap with the already assembled fragments right because this is incremental
you're receiving fragments you're potentially out of board ah but you know checking for boundaries and
overlap that's extra code ip was designed where the world was denied so that is if you receive a fragment
with the fragment offset it must make sense it must never overlap so a lot of ip implementations maybe
not today today people are cognizant of this but they would just blindly reassemble and what that means
is that if you just overlap real data it's it's a it's a problem already because god knows what
happens in the application layer but a bigger problem is this if
if you have just two fragments
this is ib this is tcb and this is whatever okay and then you have now normally
this there should be another fragment here right that should go in here right it should come after
right it has its own ip header but if the adversary change the offset or crafted the offset to start
here you see what i'm saying so here the offset in this packet fragment offset
zero it's always like this first fragment fragment offset zero because it's it's a first but in the second what if it says fragment offset here
i don't know 12
well they will think that okay this thing this thing starts 12 bytes after
so what can happen is that the adversary can override the ip header and control which flags are for
example set in the dcp sorry in this dcp header and so remember the rules that said oh you can
always let in act packets packets with an act flag well if you have two overlapping fragments
and this reassembly reassembly results in the act flag being set the packet will be left
so that's a gist of the attack
so as you i don't know if you can see in red so if the act bit is set in both fragments an act bit is okay
right both fragments have an act bit set but the fragment offset is messed up
when you reassemble you can have a sin bit set remember sin not the original sin s y n
s y n the s y n flag should be set in the very first packet in a connection
so what does it mean it that if you only allow acts which means only connections from the inside out
were allowed right you would only allow act packets coming back in but connections must always emanate
from the out from the inside this allows essentially the connection to come from the outside
that by this clever reassembly and we will see the different in another lecture uh probably next week
we will see uh what is the what is the danger not only in principle like allowing connections
disallow connections from the inside in but actually mounting was called sin floods or denial of service
attacks on the inside of the servers and by the way if you ever wanted to know what dcp state diagram
is well if you haven't been exposed to this in the networking course you should have been
because that would make a grown person cry instead of staring at it for a bit don't worry you won't be
on the exam this is networking not security but dcp is a is a complicated beast
okay it's not at all like ip or even ibsec it's a complicated beast and this diagram by the way
this state diagram captures both client and server behavior dcp so the dashed lines are for the client
and the solid lines are for the server so if you recall the state guide the state well the actual dcp
connection is established after a handshake right you first have to have this three-way handshake
connection then the connection is established but the connection when it's alive it's it's not like
constant because there's something called window size that changes right in the dcp connection and
then there's an actual end right meaning when a normal dcp connection is over there is actually a
tear down okay and then it's like that's why you have these things so i'll just give you an idea don't
worry about remember everything here uh so this is a sort of a better illustration of the fragmentation
of that you're sending two packets okay from the client sorry with uh from the client they're here
one and two both packets like in my example here have acbit set we allow packets with acbit set come back
because they're acknowledging something right remember this is a packet filter in gateway it doesn't know
the state of a dcp connection it just looks it just looks it doesn't know if the connection has been
open torn down never existed it just looks we allow active set the dcp here if the active is not set we
don't allow right make sense so when they tell that client this is a evil evil client right since these
two fragments one after the other kind of like like i illustrated here they each have the active set
but when we reassembled they result in a synbit set and when passed through tcp they say open a new
connection which is not allowed but it just happened okay so this results in a synpack here on this stupid telnet server
so what it says is that essentially packet filters they have they have a place under the sun but by
themselves they are not very good and you cannot they do offer one thing which is speed they offer you
very fast processing but or even meaningful security at a high level and they are not useful so recall
less than 1024 are permanently assigned they are reserved uh port numbers above 1024 above is all clients so
when client on your browser or whatever your telnet client command uh connects to a server it can use an
arbitrary number above 1023 well up to 65 number uh so if a firewall sees an outgoing request
to a client 5151 it doesn't know right what to do with it i mean it sees that 5151 and that is not a well-known
port it's not assigned to any specific service it's like some client that came up with it so you must allow it
because internal service could be just responding to a previously established connection right
or this could be an attack so the main problem is again that a packet a packet filtering firewall does
not know the state of the connection
well this is just already talked about so yeah what's what's what's the alternative the alternative
is to do a bit more intelligence right to slow down the firewall a little bit
and to have it looped and maintain some state okay maintaining information about open connections
okay or state of ongoing connections not always open so you still make a decision for every packet but
you make sure that the packet is somehow associated with the connection if a spurious packet arrives and
there is no record for it right then you throw away
you only the important thing here if this is a new connection right whether it's from the outside in or
from the inside out you check your policy right before do we allow this if it's a current connection
then you look it up in the table and update the table because you need to take understanding is this
connection being established for example is the handshaking process or is it already established
is it ending right because there's also a tear down phase right and reset
at the very end of the dcp connection so you need to know or is it gone there's no such connection
so that requires maintaining a dynamic table this is so keep in mind this is very different from rules
rules are more or less permanent or semi-permanent right for what we allow in what we allow
that's configured by the fire by security administrator firewall administrator
but the table of connections is fully dynamic it's what happening right now in real time
so that that's better certainly better okay because you now know that a given packet whether it
comes in or out or trying to come in or out or trying to come in or out is a part of some connection
it's not some spurious packet but it is a problem for non-tcp traffic for example
stateless protocols like utp right the unreliable data data protocol and icmp internet control message
protocol that i said before used for maintenance they're stateless they don't have a notion of a connection
so that's harder so if you filter out if you don't disallow icmp then you lose certain network
functionality so that's a trade-off also you can try to use ip tunneling right so that's the ipsec tunneling
and then remember what i said about the firewall has to then be a terminal uh terminus of an ipsec tunnel
so whoever is coming in or out must first establish a tunnel to the firewall so this is a typical or
this is an example of a connection table a session filtering uh firewall will maintain right it says
source address port number destination address port number and then connection state in all of those
cases that is established i mean the other possible state could be starting or ending and that would
starting would indicate that it's in the middle of doing the three-way handshake
and ending will be in the middle of like tearing it down thin that's not for call thin wave reset okay but
in this case all of them are established what are these well the port 80s you see source ports are all clients
right right they're all over 1023 their clients
the destination ports are web servers except for one within 25 25 is male and 79 is finger
it's a bit obsolete finger is a it's a also a program that's used for fingering users right just you
you can do finger and username and host and it basically will tell you it's like a 1980s style
thing it'll tell you information about who this user is you have to actually configure your little finger
profile it predates the web uh a lot of a lot of the installations have it turned off because it has
its own problem right so if you run a linux machine for example and you see a finger d running god forbid kill
kill kill immediately finger demon okay
so next thing circuit level gateway
so here i mentioned it earlier this is a splicing and re uh and realigning of tcp connections
so one tcp connection ends at the gateway and another begins
and there is like a a line between them and what it allows the circuit leveling gateway to do is examine
these packets but in the context of a connection like what is actually going on in this connection
we do what's called deeper packet inspection
that is strictly more secure strictly more secure but as immediate is obvious from this picture
strictly less efficient because establishing a separate tcp connection from the outside host to the out
to the circuit level gateway and another tcp connection between the circuit level gateway and inside host
costs double yes right so
let me say no not necessarily because ssl tls could actually be might actually be unaware of this
because this is tcp so all you care at the end is that you get the let's say the inside host is some kind
of web server right um i don't think you should cause a problem
i don't think you should cause a problem as long as the certificate for that host includes the name
of this you know both the inside of the circuit level gateway because the certificate could have more
than one name they could share they could be hosts within the same domain right so their actual name
could be like firewall firewall firewall.abc.com and then www.abc.com and as long as the certificate is
issued for abc.com that should be okay
okay so again uh is faster uh than the application level gate that we'll talk about next but strictly
slower than the packet level gate um in order to use it you generally need to adapt the application so
in in the previous example packet level uh firewalls the applications were uh unchanged right you don't
need to do anything you just do your business as usual the firewall is transparent in this case it's not
transparent okay oh i'm sorry so in in both examples earlier in session filtering or packet filtering it
was application transparent
here it's not transparent you need to use something like socks which is a a library for socket secure
socket layer and that's a rfc that's a kind of standard how to do it um but it's a kind of a compromise
between something that is fast but not very secure and something that is much slower which is the next
thing we'll talk about an application level gateway as i already mentioned requires you to adapt to
write a proxy for each application so you explicitly have to terminate the outside connection at the
application level gateway that examines the actual context like it looks in case of telling it would
look at the actual characters you type right in the case of uh http will actually inspect the urls
all the inputs and gets and all you know all the other http commands so you'll actually see the clear text
on those connect so if you're using ssl uh tls there that makes it a little harder because yeah you have
to you have to modify all your applications
other filtering rules are simpler because there's a lot more intelligence in these in these proxies there's a
separate proxy for each application and you can make them quite intelligent but and to understand
the context of what is being sent and what is being received you can look for malicious commands like
you know actual command line unix commands you can look for particular patterns like jpeg files etc
so there's a much richer functionality but this is slow right so this is not for example the way you want
to do streaming videos so to compare these approaches this is again should be by now fairly obvious if
you're awake as far as performance package filter being in the network layer dealing with one packet at
a time gives us the best performance and the worst performance of the application everything the best
the best to the worst as far as modifying client or client applications or actually server applications
the first two do not require modification the second requires basically slight modifications you have
to essentially recompile everything with socks with this socket secure there for application level gateway
you need to modify client applications to work with these proxies okay now things like fermentation attacks
well only the last two really protect against fermentation attacks because if those attacks are attempted
they will be detected at the firewall okay and they will not propagate to the actual
host on the inside so the danger can be contained on the firewall
now remember i told you earlier about filtering outbound connections this is a real example from um early 2000 like 2007 2008
uh this was uh uh white house right actually the white house website that uh blocked all kinds of connections
right by the firewall but it had the web server right the public uh web server that uh allowed you to look at the
uh directory directory right and a phone book script sorry phone book script which is like a directory
but what it didn't do it didn't sanitize the irs right so you're not sanitization it's right it's looking
at the like a input whatever the program is and sanitizing that input like removing suspicious characters
a lot of times you'll see this in the in web forms you fill out they won't allow you for example when you
fill out a web form to use certain characters right that are on the keyboard some special characters you're
not allowed that's called sanitization uh this is explicit right the explicit is that you cannot use
this oh sometimes they won't let you even type them and sometimes you type them you press return and say no
okay you cannot use this character uh in url that means that you know you parse the url and you look for
these kind of suspicious characters and truncate them and get rid of them completely
okay well there was no sanitization done in the phone book script and so you could actually submit
a command now notice the magento pink color that's a relatively denied url right it's coming in from the
outside right outside to the white house and it's doing invoking this uh cgi directory fphf is a phone book
okay okay okay and there's some gravity i don't know what qa this x is but following it you have a percent
sign followed by oa x sorry uh qlsx and then away right and what it is is that it's ox away is a new line
so when it interprets when the phone book script looks at it it actually says oh
all i say is a new line so it splits it right here
right here it puts a new line and then this starting with this character right here it becomes
a new a separate line right let's look what it means it says bin cat bin cat is a program to title
right okay on the screen right here is cat which is in the bin directory bin cat
percent 20 is space space character that's the password so and then not only executes the cgi script
but after doing that it says cat the password type it and what happens is it appears on the screen on the
client okay but the interesting part is this is coming from the inside out right the command came from the
outside in but what is being displayed on the client on the outside of the screen is coming from the out
from the inside right so this is what you should do inside sanitization or checking what comes out
from the whitehouse.gov right so why filter outcome that's why all right so this will display a password
file that of course we know opens the door for you know the password attacks uh this is even worse
example this one also using the new line executes an x-window server essentially opens a window an x-window
that x is a window system right you've probably heard about it um but it opens an outbound connection
on the outsider's web server so essentially the outsider gets an x-window inside the white house network
so one big problem is that the cgi dynamic right did not sanitize the input but the bigger problem
that so ideally that should have been done right the input should be sanitized but sometimes there
are so many of these cgi's there right you can't possibly like maybe maybe it's you know not viable
to like fix them all but at the very least the last line of defense should have been not allowing things
from the inside to come outside which is executing this x command external x terminal command or
concatenating or typing the password file so that's kind of a silly example uh so in practice a lot of
people use or a lot of companies use what's called the bastion coast which is kind of it's kind of a
glorified firewall but the idea is that it's not just a firewall but it's like a fully blown uh you know
computer not just like a network layer device but a fully blown computer it has a packet level application
level gateway but it sits behind a packet level filter okay and so in that in that bastion host all
services are turned off there's no usb ports are sealed you know can't stick anything in no no uh what's
called air gap jumping uh and he prevents all these application specific proxies like what i said before
and applications gateway um supports direct user authentication so you actually first authenticate
when you when you log in you authenticate to the bastion host and then only you are allowed to proceed
and all traffic flows to that host it it it it does not make things fast but it makes things reasonably
secure typically like that so this is called a single home bastion host you have the back the
big bad internet you have the this is the firewall of the packet the packet level firewall then that's
the fast for packet filtering here you have the dmz like information web server and the bastion host sits
kind of between the that and the rest of the network now it says single home because you see it assumes
that there's like the bastion host only has one network interface right so it's certainly faster that
way but the problem is that if the packet filtering router is compromised right so that that thing is
compromised then bad traffic can flow in so if you want that not to happen you do a dual home bastion
host which actually means it has two separate interfaces that all the traffic even from the packet
filtering router must come into the bastion host be scrutinized and let out so in case a
packet filtering router fails the bastion host still remains in the last line of defense
and there's no physical connection right so the internal and external network no longer have a
physical connection everything goes through the bastion host
that's what's called this is called the screen subnet there's also this approach the screen subnet
where you only have this is really kind of for more for very secure environments where you have
this kind of a firewall in fact a little firewall here another finite level firewall here
this is in case the bastion host fails so you really separate this what's called this is called the
screen subnet where you only have these kind of dmz machines the bastion host maybe a dial-in module
not nobody uses those anymore but then some years ago they did and then the private network is fully separate
so what should firewalls do besides filtering and deciding what's allowed not allowed among the other
thing they should do is should not propagate ip addresses or any kind of network structure of
internal network to the outside that is super important right because knowledge of your internal
network topology right geography of your internal network is sensitive information and only those
services like a web server or some other kind of directory server only those that are absolutely
necessary for outside access should be made available meaning their ip addresses should be known
to the outside but the rest of the inside network does not need to expose its structure or its ip
addresses okay and for that if you've taken a networking course you probably have heard of a network address translator or nat
that will essentially translate uh in the packet the the source path the source ip address of a packet is going out
right to something that does not expose them for example a bastion host will typically push its own
ip address in the source instead of the internal ip address uh and it will similarly translate things coming back
right with it we'll have the destination bastion host it will have the exam says oh this yes this is for me
but really it's for this other open connection that i have okay so this translation uh and there are many
uh options you can map there's one-to-one end-to-one mapping and all kinds of variations another important
thing is routing announcement so uh i don't know how much you all know about routing protocols
usually assume not a lot uh but you definitely don't want a protocol whatever routing protocol you run
inside your network you don't want the routing announcements and routing changes on the inside to propagate
outside right right the only thing that on the outside should know about routing is whether your
network is accessible right meaning it's is it down is it up right they're gonna everything else
should be screened or not announced okay
uh
okay so what are the general problems with files this is all all types of firewalls well they like everything
else in security they eat cycles they slow things down nothing that is secure makes things faster
they don't solve some real world problems bugging software insider attacks with malware they don't
prevent malware from coming in from the inside they may prevent malware from exfiltrating information
through the firewall but they don't prevent things from just like happening on the inside
um they don't prevent bugs i mean protocol design if you have a badly designed firewall software yeah
that's of course a problem uh they don't prevent denial of service attacks if somebody knows the rules
of the firewall meaning that they allow traffic to an smtp server right so internal
external traffic to smtp mail server inside is allowed fine that is a safe rule no problem you can
armor your smtp server and protect but the problem is that if you allow any amount of traffic to smtp server
that allows anybody from the outside to essentially mount the denial of service attack by just sending a
very large volume of traffic to the smtp server by the time the smtp server just just discards their
traffic the internal network resources are consumed so that's something a firewall won't solve for you
and of course don't let's not forget this uh some sometimes some certain types of insider attacks won't
be prevented because an ambassador you can always uh if it's a real insider not a doofus who brought
the uh infected usb stick to work but rather an insider who but even a doofus by the way that
might work but an insider who brought something malicious and copied let's say all the personnel
files to usb stick how is the firewall going to prevent this only i don't know frisking him physically
might detect this uh even uh let's take the doofus example somebody brings that uh usb stick
with movies to watch during lunchtime the malware um jumps to the device to the laptop or desktop
steals information copies it back to the usb stick the doofus at the end of the day removes the stick
goes home plugs the usb sticks in his home computer malware accepts it hello world let me export all this
stuff now there's no firewall in doofus's home are you with me so won't prevent that
there's more complexity firewall configuration is not easy okay not easy and it's not static things
change in the real business world so it's and they're more static than let's say dcp connection but not
static and last but not least this few people know how to do it and even fewer have the expertise knowing
how to do it and actually having expertise do different things so firewall administrative security
in these states they get paid a lot especially in bigger companies like banks
and that's it thank you any questions by the way i hope you were here and uh like the our like a little
detour last lecture into automotive world maybe a bit boring for those already taking that class
reinforcement learning yeah how can we prevent the fragmentation attack if we don't feel all the
maybe the fragmentation flat how can we well one way to do it is so if you're using ipv6 that doesn't
happen because ipv6 does not allow fragmentation if you're using ipv4 one way to prevent it is to
simply throw away fragmented back and just have to say no fragmentation allowed uh icfp the protocol
i mentioned earlier for you that used for maintenance i uh allows you to generate that error message to
the source by says fragmentation not allowed so the source continues fragmented you just discard
not always but but these days it is extremely unusual for routers to fragment typically today fragmentation
happens actually it's even today what happens is mostly like this if it's a tcp packet tcp implementation
on your whatever device i'm going back will be aware of the empty and it will actually not generate
not pass to ip segments greater than the empty so it might not even happen i would be very surprised
that in the modern implementation on a modern operating operating system you will still have fragmentation
even inside the source i mean it might happen but it'd be very important okay see you next tuesday