It's the MCM syndrome that I recommend, it's, you know, tells you everything you want to know about spam.
And surprisingly, 20 years, not many things change about spam.
But, so why the parallel? Well, spam is annoying, right? This spam.
And so is the email spam or electronic spam. So that's where the analogy comes from.
I do some stats. I didn't, like, double check them, but I think they're reasonably accurate.
So, number of, like, email versus spam, right?
So you see the bars, the total bars represent total email spam.
The red part is the percentage of spam. I'm sorry. Total email, percentage of spam.
From this six-year period, ending in 2022, my guess is it hasn't changed very much.
It probably continued along the same line up to 20, 25.
Interestingly, more spam was sent as a percentage of all emails, like, six years ago.
And then it kind of sort of levels off, you know, right?
But it's still impressive, right? If you haven't seen this, it is impressive.
Email is still, right? Maybe not so much, you think, for your generation because you've never really worked outside.
Or many of you haven't really worked in real jobs.
But once you get a real job, yes, people use Slack and, you know, some other versions thereof and wikis and God knows what else.
But email is still there and it has no signs of going away.
So I predict email is not going to go away for at least a decade.
It's for the time it is here to stay.
So, an enlarged percentage of it is spam.
Spam is not only email-based.
You may have received robocalls, right? That's spam.
That's just another version of spam.
Text messages? Yes? Text?
A lot of SMS.
Sometimes WhatsApp, right?
Well, I get WhatsApp spam.
Not a lot, but I get it.
Like, once every couple of weeks.
SMS, I get once every couple of days.
Some of these I don't see because it's already, like, filtered.
Never have I ever received spam on Signal.
Anybody use Signal?
Highly recommended.
For secure messaging.
Okay?
If you want to be secure, do not use Telegram.
That's slimy through and through.
Okay?
Do not.
Unless you want the FBI to knock on your door.
No, seriously.
Do not use Telegram.
SMS.
Just assume everybody reads it.
Okay?
Just assume that it's not private.
WhatsApp?
Eh...
Meta.
Do you trust Mark?
Exactly.
Have you looked at him?
I don't trust Mark.
Signal.
Public domain.
Okay.
So, you can look at the code.
Eh...
I trust Signal more than others.
Not that I trust it, but I trust that I did more than others.
So, if I had to, like, send something securely today, I would do Signal, I might actually split
the message in two parts and send something by a signal and something by WhatsApp.
Are you getting what I'm saying?
Right?
Okay.
Yeah?
But I message is distinct, right?
Right?
I message is distinct, but I message is like a stupid overlay.
So, I message works for Macs and iPhones.
What about the rest of it?
It's a stupid walled garden religion that Apple imposed on us.
Right?
So, yes, iMessage, if you live entirely within Apple universe, iMessage is okay.
But the problem is, many of us, maybe not you all, but many of us people who use Apple
products communicate with non-Apple users.
And you don't often pay attention or know that your text message isn't an iMessage, but
goes out of the Apple universe.
And the moment it goes out of the Apple universe, it no longer has that security.
So, and then, so text messages and messaging apps, you know, have a lot that can present.
Phone calls, yeah?
If your phone number is somewhere, chances are, you know, you will get text spam.
I'm sorry, phone spam by robocalls, sometimes by live people, but that's, that's like not
really spam.
I mean, it's annoying.
And then email is, uh, the lion's share of, of spam is 50% or so.
So, this is a disturbing thing.
So this is, a graph is kind of hard to read.
Uh, so look at the red part.
It just claims, again, I didn't double verify it.
It seems reasonably credible.
Number of people who lost money due to like scams, spam based scams.
So we're talking here from under 20 million in 2014, all the way to what?
close to 60 million in 2024.
Now, I believe that this is cumulative.
So it's not like 2024, 60 million lost.
It's all these other accumulated stuff that, by 2024, 60 million lost money.
I think that it's not, I don't believe this is a discreet per year.
Although there's a dip here, but I don't, I don't.
There's a dip here, but I don't believe it.
They recovered their money.
Some probably did.
I would say very small percentage.
Very small.
What looks more is, uh, credible is, uh, the yellow part of the graph that shows the average,
uh, money per person lost.
You know, and these, uh, when it, when this talks about, uh, scam calls, it talks about also
email, right?
So it includes email.
So things like, oh, you know, we, here's a bill for, I don't know, Norton defender.
Or here's a thank you for your purchase of Adobe creative cloud.
Right.
You've seen those emails, right?
They say, and here's the bill, or we charged your card or something like that.
Right.
And you call the number.
Somebody does, maybe a relative or a friend, and, uh, they give up their password because
they're tricked.
They lose the money.
Typically these types of scams do not result in like emptying of bank accounts because banks
often have some safeguards in place, but, uh, people do lose money and no longer.
Uh, subjects.
What kind of subjects?
Well, it's no longer like Nigerian princes, right?
Right.
Or Malaysian, uh, multi-billionaires, right?
Who want to share their immense wealth, uh, with you.
Right.
Only if you provide a small amount of information on your bank account where they need to transfer.
Uh, but you've got prizes and giveaway job opportunities and banking, right?
The banking spams are typically the ones you've seen where, uh, we identify the problem with
your account.
Please immediately call this number.
Or please click on this link to confirm, uh, your data, right?
Or change your password.
Okay.
Um, and this goes, actually, that's a separate category.
Request to change your password after your account.
Then software download, right?
I mean, uh, you have, we have a new release of, uh, an XYZ package.
Uh, we see you're using it and enjoying it.
Please download the free, uh, the next beautiful version of that package.
Oh, my gambling.
Haven't seen that much.
I'm surprised it's 20%.
Adult content.
That used to be a lot more, a lot more.
Like 10 years ago, I would say half of the spam was porn or porn related.
Now it's, it's down.
There's probably a good, like social science explanation.
Cryptocurrency scams.
Are they out there?
Not a huge amount, but they're out there.
I see, I see spam.
I see spam with cryptocurrency.
Uh, especially, these are especially on WhatsApp and text.
Not so much by email.
And then all kinds of stuff.
Pharmaceuticals also used to be a huge thing, right?
Huge.
Uh, like 15 years ago.
Pharmaceuticals scams.
The usual.
Viagra, Cialis, boldness cures, weight loss.
Between those three, like lose weight fast, performance, sexual performance enhancements,
and hair.
Sometimes it was loose hair.
Yeah.
Usually it was like regrow hair fast, right?
So these three dominated.
Now they're very small.
I'm surprised.
And then, uh, okay.
Romance scams.
That's more like, that's a niche.
That's not in this country so much.
That's, that's outside.
And now let's not confuse the dating app scams, right?
That's a whole different.
I'm not, I'm ruling those out here.
You know, these dating apps where they have bots and, uh, uh, that's a whole different
Okay.
Uh, here's some more numbers for you.
About 160 billion spam emails are sending it.
Billion!
Billion, right?
This price.
We have what?
4 billion people?
5 billion people on this earth?
There's not many emails are sent every freaking day.
Um, and that's good part of the 350 billion emails overall set.
Uh, most people receive spam messages.
The problem is what, so how does spam work?
Uh, how, how do spammers harvest email addresses?
Well, the most obvious like they crawl, right?
They crawl the web and they look for email addresses.
And all these tricks that people used to do and still do with like, uh, you know, not
using the add sign, but say add or something, right?
Or, oh, it's my name at blah, blah, blah.
Those don't work because these, these crawlers can convert us into email address.
Sometimes the email address is a guest.
Like smith at yahoo.com is going to be an email address, right?
Joey at yahoo.com.
Uh, you know, uh, Gene Sudik at gmail.com.
Well, you need to know my last name, right?
But, but you know, more predictable last names and first names, any combinations that are
going to be existing email.
No, it doesn't take a rocket scientist.
Most of the spam of actual people who send spam don't do the crawling.
Crawling is done by whole other people system that then sells this harvested spam addresses
to the spam, right?
To the actual spam.
Also, they filter them.
So when they collect them, they actually test that they exist.
Right?
So you get this, what's called data clean in the database world.
So they clean the data and then they sell the giant, uh, collections of databases of existing,
uh, email addresses to those who actually want to send spam.
Uh, maybe it will surprise you that the US sends the most spam.
There is most spam originates inside the US.
It may have actually been crafted somewhere else, but the, the sender from the email point
of view is here in the United States.
Followed by China.
Uh, let's see.
Okay.
The rest of them are important.
Uh, financial.
Now, now this is some, because I was hoping we would have a lecture on phishing.
I'm not sure if we, at the speed we're going to have that.
Phishing and spam are like fraternal twins.
Okay.
Now, spam can be without phishing.
And if I draw a Venn diagram, there will be a giant overlap.
You know, everybody knows a Venn diagram, right?
Between spam and phishing, but they have distinct parts.
So, spam is a vehicle for phishing.
Often.
Not always.
Spam can be also selling, I don't know, pharmaceuticals, right?
Is that phishing?
No.
A lot of that stuff is like you want to buy, uh, Adderall.
Maybe because it's without prescription.
It may be illegal for you to do so.
But if you go to the website and enter your credit card, they won't steal it.
They will ship you Adderall, maybe.
Or if you want to, uh, I don't know, buy something else, right?
I mean, uh, a walk, what is it?
The typical one?
A walk-in bathtub.
Everybody knows what that is?
For some reason, there was a favorite subject of spam for a while.
That's for old people or people who are handicapped.
A walk-in bathtub is a bathtub that has a door that you don't have to, like, step in.
Yes?
You've seen those?
Ever?
No?
Ever seen spam on that?
Very popular stuff for a long time.
So, surely there is a walk-in bathtub you can buy, probably overpriced.
Okay?
So it's not phishing.
It's just selling crap.
It's the same idea that you get in the mailbox, right?
You get these useless things, if you ever check, like, actual mail, physical mail.
You get these useless advertisements, right, for stuff that you don't need most of the time.
A sail in some, you know, Nordstrom's rack or whatever.
That's physical spam.
And, you know, a walk-in bathtub or, I don't know, cheap solar batteries installed in three minutes.
That's also that kind of spam.
It's not phishing.
Phishing is what they want to extract something from you that is, like, very personal.
Like, credentials.
Right?
Okay.
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Oh, yeah.
Delivery services.
We have a package for you, right?
This is typical via text, right?
Typically SMS, right?
Because a lot of the delivery services, FedEx, DHL, right?
Amazon, right?
They use SMS.
Many do.
And so you get this unsolicited text from some special, like a four-six-digit number, right?
That's not really typically a real phone number.
And it says, we have a delivery.
It's waiting for you.
We just need you to confirm your credit card.
Details.
Maybe you won't find that surprising.
Men 65 and over received the most spam calls.
No.
Not.
No, no.
No.
No, I'm not.
All right, I'm sorry.
Very.
Holy shit.
Oh.
No.
No, no.
and men 18 to 34 the less the least
any explanation when you might think that's so
what happens at 65? usual retirement right?
yes but retirement right? so you have
idleness right? so you're a working man
you're a working person you don't have time to talk to spammers
right? or follow up on some email
you just ignore whatever you're retired
now all of a sudden you have a lot of time on your head
you're bored and you have money
yeah? you have money you save money you work all your life or whatever
65 not that long maybe but so these are the most ripe
the most ripe soil for spammers
people with disposable income who are idle and bored
these people I mean crypto millionaires aside
right? these people have no money
and they have the attention span of a food flight
right? not a good target for spammers
these people also remember these are like boomers
here 65 and over are boomers
different generation more perhaps more trusting
a little more serious you know
these people roughly your age
I mean these are men mind you but I think women get fewer
but I don't know how to explain that
list not obvious questions
alright let's switch into something a little more technical
so email have you ever wondered what your email does when it leaves your hands when you click send?
was that covered in any networking courses? yes?
not here
thank you
where?
I want to go there
yes I suppose it wasn't covered in networking courses here unfortunately
which it should be
so you are the sender
you have your
are you all like browser email users?
who is a non-browser email user?
anybody use an email front-end?
like an email program?
no
wow
sign of the times
okay
it's a little different in your case
because
you are essentially using a front-end
kind of a fake front-end
your client browser
to access your gmail
right?
anybody here non-gmail?
you seem almost hesitant
look at this monoculture
you are all gmail users
is that because UCI dictates it?
do you have any other non-gmail accounts?
yeah
okay
but you use the browser as well to access those
interesting
well I don't think the browser on mobile devices
no
on the mobile devices I guess you use your mail app right?
well that's essentially the same thing right?
everybody uses like an API phone
well no
that's a different thing
okay
so let's think about your mail app
like
do people use mail on phones?
do you all use mail on phones?
like that?
okay
so you have an app
right?
good
so now we can connect better
you click send
your app is that
is that box over here
right?
that's your app over there
in that box
it's a computer but it's really like in this case be your phone
and so it's a client
it's an email client
and
when you configured it
you had to put some stuff in there
do you remember?
like you have to say what is your outgoing server?
Nicole doing that?
no Nicole
oh they give you a profile?
it's just one of your most login
oh my god
okay
so
with google
even if you are using gmail
with a client
it goes to
something called
smtp.something.something
which in this case
will be smtp.google.gmail
blah blah blah
and that's your relay
relay
now if your destination is in google world
that same mail relay is going to deliver it to the recipient
so you won't have this stage
this mail relay
if it's google
and your destination if you have it is google
it will just hand over to the recipient
actually it won't handle it
technically it just stores it
that some people either pop or imap server
but that's not interesting
but generally if you send email to some
let's say you have a friend in
I don't know American Samoa
and you send an email and they have an address with like
ending with S
I guess it would be ASA or something like that
it will be given to the mail relay
which is the outgoing server
and that server will figure out
what is the recipient's mail relay
okay
and it will hand over over the internet
generally this can actually be over the internet
and it will hand over the mail
and then it will get to the recipient
but that's a funny detail here
the recipient may have a separate server
where the mail is stored
that's usually what's called POP3 or IMAP
depending on how you configure it
mailbox
okay
so you actually fetch email from there
when you refresh
all right
but the important thing is to understand
is that this is not real time communication
remember I kept saying that email is stored forward
so like
if for example
this mail relay is down
this one will buffer your mail
you might even try a different mail relay
so that means it's kind of tolerant of delays
and failures
TCP is not right
so this is
if this was end to end TCP
it wouldn't work
but with mail relays because they are running
application layer right
yeah
setting up your own mail relay
you could in principle do that
you would have to get your own domain
probably for that
you can get a domain
you can buy one
you can set up your own mail relay
you can right now
let's say you are
you live in Irvine here
you are sort of stuck with COX
internet
you cannot set up your own mail relay
at least not easily
right
but if you buy your own domain
then you can
well I was saying
so if you set it up right
and then you are up to your own Gmail
and you are trying to send
if you set up your own mail relay
then it's a front end
so when you send mail
you would go for that relay
and then to Gmail
but if you are using the browser
it will still go directly to Google
your mail
your mail really will be irrelevant
you see because when you are using a browser
you are not using
you are not using the actual email
you are using like an interface
through the email
so it's like a storage forward component
can you like do a denial of service attack on the storage forward
like I assume there is only a limited amount of memory
generally mail relays have a lot of disk space
they don't keep those things in memory
they only keep them when they
if they try to send
if they cannot send
if the send does not succeed
they buffer on this
but you could presumably do like a malicious attack
you could make
but that will still
there is a limited amount of time
that it will try to retransmit
then it will delete
you will see mail undeliverable
how many of you have seen this?
undeliverable mail
that's an error message saying
he tried
and then he gave up
so
ok
mail relay
forwards mail
to the next
hop
in principle
there could be more
most of the time
today
you will have
at most
two mail relays
meaning you will have something like this
if you are sending mail
from
a domain
to a destination
in the same domain
you only have one relay
because that one relay relay
will deliver it right away
to the destination
does that make sense?
so
the way that email works
is governed by
a protocol called SMTP
simple mail transfer protocol
not extremely simple
but not too complicated
ok
not like TCP
but it is a protocol
not a packet form
right
so
here you have
Bob
and Bob is
like
think of Bob as like
somebody writing an app
on their iphone
a mail app
or
like me
kind of Neanderthal
who has an email fronted
I run Thunderbird
so my email
is
is done by
Thunderbird
program
on my
laptop
so
I'm that guy
and
when I click send
SMTP
governs
how my
message
is transferred
to
my
nearest
outgoing
server
that is configured
in my profile
it is configured
in your profile
if you look into your mail app
on your iphone
or android
ok
you can actually see
what is the
address
the host name
of your outgoing
relay
this guy
here
it's
it's there
and then
so if the email goes to some organization
where Alice works
well that organization has its own
server or relay
and that
transfer
between
relays
or between servers
I use server and relay
interchangeably
is also governed by SMTP
ok
but it's
hop
by
not end to end
hop
by hop
and then here
between
Alice's mail server
and actual recipient
there's something called
there's several
protocols for fetching
actually fetching email
because
what email does
is SMTP
delivers it
to the last pop
but not to the client
not to the recipient
the recipient has to explicitly fetch
mail
and that's done by
several protocols
one
you know
pop three is one
and IMAP
is another
and there might be others
as well
but these are the two
the two most popular
pop
post office protocol
and IMAP
stands for
internet mail
and something
agent protocol
or something like that
but we won't be talking about those
those are not very interesting
the most interesting part is
this
there are two
ports
and I'm gonna tell you a bit about SMTP
because I figured you never heard
how it works
alright
it actually
it's a little confusing
because it works
it works with two different ports
remember port socket
port
port 25
is a standard email port
it's been around since 1982
and
right around
very soon after IP and TCP were first proposed
it is beloved by spammers
because it is insecure
so the port 25
is essentially supporting what's called open relay
which I'll tell you about in a minute
it is supported by
it shouldn't be used
by your email front end
so your app for example
if you look at your email app
and the configuration of your email app
one of the things it will tell you there
is what protocol to use
maybe you have
you've tried to add an email account
to your email app
has anybody done this?
add an account
does it ask you a set of questions?
mine does
but that's because mine isn't set up in the standard way
but in my experience
all of them ask you questions
yeah
like you say
what is your username
right
what is your email provider
what is your username
it asks you password
right
then it asks you also like
what protocol
and that will give you choices
ok
so
25 is one choice
it might not be supported
and for good reason
because it's not secure
ISPs
right
the cloud hosting provider will often block it
what is it actually used for?
it is used for
this
relay to relay
server to server
originally
everybody used port 25
for like several decades
and then when spam became a problem
they introduced port 587
and that's the one you're more likely to see
when you configure your email
you know
even if it's done automatically
you can see it
in the configuration
okay
there's an internet rc
that's discussed
it has
what's called
a start
TLS option
it's not
it's an option
it's not a requirement
but when you use that option
your email
is transferred
over a
TLS connection
and that is primarily
for this
from your app
to the outgoing server
or from your front end
of your laptop
to the outgoing server
okay
it's a little bit confusing
but that's how it works
so
there are a lot of
what's called open relays
out there
meaning relays
that do not require you
to have an account
to establish a secure connection
they exist for various reasons
sometimes they exist because
you know
operators of those relays
get money
from spammers
and other businesses
sometimes they exist because
people who configure them
and set them up
believe in
freedom of speech
they just don't allow
anybody to send email
through them
okay
now
what does an open relay do
or what does a relay in general do
it is
processing
so it receives an email
from the previous
haha
it looks at the header
and it looks to where does it need to go
right
what is the destination
like alice
abc.com.au
which means
the company named ABC
AU is in Australia
so it needs to go to Australia
and so
it finds out
what should be the next relay
topic
maybe
smtp.abc.com.au
let's say that's the next email
it establishes a TCP connection
and then via smtp transfers the message over
but as it transfers the message over
it adds
a received from
a line
okay
into the header field
and maybe if you looked at the actual raw email
you might have looked at the raw email message
in plain text
have you seen that it has several usually several lines that say received
that is essentially the path that your email took to get to you
okay
that tells you exactly the sequence of relays that it traversed in order to get to you
and an honest relay according to the scientific protocol needs to add itself to the received
right
so the header grows as an email hops around the internet the header grows never shrinks
so when you receive it you actually see the exact route it took
not IP route not IP route but a mail route
now if the relay is hacked or it's malicious it doesn't have to do this
it doesn't have to abide by the protocol
and that's why for example spam may be very confusing
you might not exactly see the hops it took
especially typical thing is that the spammer has a
as the first hop a malicious relay
that does not add its name or adds some incorrect name
and why to confuse you
so you don't know where the intel actually comes from
SMTP will not surprise you
does not have any built-in authentication
no built-in security whatsoever
okay
like IP
like TCP
it was an internet program
one of those protocols designed in a different at a different time
right
50 years ago
when things were very very different
let's see
mail from
right
you've seen it
if you look at the raw text email
mail from is supposed to be where it actually comes from
right
bob
xyz.com.ca
which would be
company xyz in Canada
okay
but
can you trust it
no
of course not
I
just
it's like the sender
sender can put anything you want
who wants to put
you know
moron.trump
and whitehouse.com
go ahead
chancellor gilman
fbci.edi
whatever
he can do it
so
and then the recipient
right
only sees the IP address
of the direct peer
meaning that
the last hop
from which
so the only thing you can trust
is that of the IP address of the last hop
from the email
that's it
of their relay
so here's the language of India
this is what actually happens
right
between
a sending mail server
like on a client
so this is in case of your app
your mail app
on your app
on your phone
and the first
mail server
first it says
some people
hello
right
so this is on port 25
port 25
in a
sorry
let me
let me take that
sorry
this is between two relays
not between your client
not between your email client
on your app
but rather
between two relays
the sending relay
and the receiving relay
okay
so this is using
port 25
because that's allowed
between
email servers
hi there i want to send you email
so it says
this is not after TCP connection
is established
i don't show it
here
then it says to some people
hello
it's not going to spell it
that's how it is called
uh
and now the reply is
okay
i'm ready to receive email
from you
then it says
uh
the mail i'm about to send you
is from
uh
hello
dot com
and uh
what the receiving mail server is supposed to do is look at that address and say
do i want to do i trust this address do i want to forward email that came from this address
right
and generally
i mean unless it
so you can have a blacklist for example it can consult some spam address database or it can have its own configuration it says okay good 250 means okay here is where it's going to then the sending server says it's going to mary at sweet tooth dot com the receiving server says okay let me check that address do i know where that is
what that is
do i like this address
is it
is that a
suspicious address
maybe it's a non-existent address
if it's fine it says yeah looks good 250 okay
and then
this
here
is a data transfer
right
actually it's one line at a time
text
bam
the last message
is a dot
a one line with just a period
that signifies end of message
i know
weird
so
when you said
if you were to insert in your mail a period
like when you type when you type out in your email
if you insert a period on by itself on a line
it's masked
so that otherwise writing would be misinterpreted as the end of email so it is masked with a slash i think or something like that
so
it has to be like one period on a line that says okay we're done
at this point we're done then there's a quit command and then they acknowledge that this is kind of an error message but it means i acknowledge we're done
yeah
is there any particular reason it has to be six back and forth or is it just the first thing they thought
uh
good question i don't know
clearly this could be done differently right
but that's that's how they're that's how the purple works
you mean these hello okay mail from okay but uh yeah i mean of course you could you could imagine um
hello is not just okay we're talking this is the beginning of the email of SMTP
right because TCP is is below it's already established but above it is SMTP protocol right
so the first two exchanges are they need to be there right just to say we are i i speak SMTP you speak SMTP
the second two exchanges like mail from okay recipient to okay those could be combined indeed
i don't see a reason why they're separate but that's just historically how it works
so it looks more complicated than it is right it's not that difficult
now this is how port 557 works this is also SMTP protocol but this is between your email client on your
the app on your phone or a front end on your laptop and the outgoing server that's supposed to be more secure
so uh instead of hello it's hello which means extended hello why because it's more sophisticated
okay mail from same as before okay bob looks okay then sending to alice yahoo.com okay check that is okay
then send data all right every piece of data is line by line until you see a period period is the end
quit blah blah blah right so it's very very similar except that if you wanted to secure it you could do it
you could do it you could use a tls option that's called a start tls this is a version that would use start tls
tcp handshake i showed you here but the beginning then there's really hello 250 means okay and then
then the receiving email server adds an option count saying start tls it means i support tls
tls the email client acknowledges 2.8 means go ahead and then there's a tls negotiation there's actually a tls session
set up here okay and that email is sent over that tls and chances are in new york now stock tls is due
i can definitely see when i configure a new email account one of the options is pick start tls and
sometimes your email provider if you don't pick it will not will refuse to work because they say no no no
i want you to use start tls make sure the email is secure now the typical header fields in an email i can
attach that you probably see are like these this is not there are more there could be a lot of extended maybe
you see a lot of fields there called x dot dash have you seen if you look at the email remember
the same thing feels like s dash that's extended optional fields but the required fields are these
two to whom is this email this is one or more destinations carbon copy right who is copying on
these emails and then blind carbon copy okay everyone knows what dcc is what's the stupidest thing anybody can
have a doubt do with bcc have you ever received email by bcc i've never replied to an email by bcc
that's the stupidest thing you can do
does everybody see what i'm saying if you receive a mail by a bcc you use your address is in bcc that
means everybody else does not see your email as one of the recipients you are a hidden recipient
but if you do reply all
everybody will see that yeah you got that email and you weren't on the address list
you must have been bcc so don't do reply all if you're a bcc on email okay bcc then from who created
this email the email address usually with a name sometimes with a name not always with a name right
sender
usually the same receive okay this is where you have one or more lines of the path
right in this case just that is line added by each trip but it uses the word transfer agent but the
sftp relay or server to show you the hops it went through return path right path back to the center
let's look at this mail plain text
received by received by so return path received received
spf we'll talk about this message id from to subject
okay you see the first receive gives you an ip address
that was done 12 in a time stamp the second says
received actually the same time stamp is possible because the time stamp is in seconds so
uh it is quite possible pacific standard of time uh sftp id is a typically a
hash of the message some kind of hash that can be assigned every email server can use its own
heuristic to assign it but the ip addresses are supposed to be legitimate ip addresses
return path some email address
uh spf is called the center policy framework we'll talk about it it's basically a um
this distinction between trusted and untrusted uh sources at the particle uh okay and then there is the
person presumably who sent this email uh it generally should match return path you see return
path path and and the front should match
this is the destination so the victim here is this person
so this stuff is inserted by relays all of that
this one link pr is a isp in puerto rico okay
it claims to have and you see what's there in a uh parenthesis in the brackets is an ip address
it's supposed to correspond right so the one link pr.net is supposed to correspond to that address
actually that is somewhere in mongolia
how do you know if you ping right if you trace your output it's in mongolia
so already we have that's the spam which means it's an artificially crafted
uh message
one in the game of bingo so why do spam spammers want to hide their sources
right so there is this fundamental thing right when you get spam
it obviously wants you to do something right if you fall for it it wants you to take an action
like buy viagra or walk in bathtub or you know order some i don't know some crap on the internet
right i mean it sends you somewhere right it's not a spam saying it's usually not like oh i don't know
vote for uh candidate this you get the spam around election time right but um that's different so
typically it wants you to do something so why if they want you to do something
meaning go to some website or reply then why would they hide their sources you see the problem
they hide their sources not so much from you the recipient but from your provider your isp and others who want to kill spam
you see the distinction they don't really care so much that you know where it comes from they don't want
others to know so they can't be blacklisted what was your question
that's true that's true but typically you say you think right intuitively that oh you know it's the
some even it's either that seller or the agent of the seller that's advertising this product right that
that they're trying to get me to buy there should be a connection but that doesn't have to be right
the seller for example could be in a place where they they you know in some other country
and their email address might be filtered by policy like so what they do is they say you can
contract the spammer in the united states they send the spammer a template i want you to
to send to this 10 million addresses this type of message that says dear so and so i am god knows who
a nigerian prince recently deceased with a lot of money to give away right but the idea is that okay
if it comes from nigeria right if you see the head of nigeria it would be it would be thrown away but
if it comes from the us source it won't be right if it's a us isp so that's the reason
now of course spam filters they they do check the bodies of messages so you you you have these various
like uh sophos and spam assassin and you might sometimes get from uci write these messages saying
that we quarantine some messages right have you seen those you have to like to get them you have to
clicks that go to some link and you know click that's true but spammers are really good at like
evading them that's a whole separate subject right how do they evade spam filters because spam filters
basically you know use some heuristics of ai but you know anything that they do can be circumvented if
they know if you know the algorithms anyway
there are these clearing houses i think they're still around spam houses spam spam cop dot net these
are non-profits that you maintain giant data banks of uh spam addresses right there's spam providers
spam relays um these and this is where your relays these are the typical databases that your mail relays
will consult in you know as they try to deliver emails and so they will stop like between 15 and
40 percent of spam but majority of spam still gets through okay uh the other problem is that by the
time they check the bandwidth is already consumed right so the email can email consumes a lot of
bandwidth as you can imagine especially if you have uh html inside email right or or some other markups
right now you have s- does everybody know the s- is secure multimedia mail extension this is when you
you receive email that is like signed or you know it has multiple parts and so on these these are giant
or can be quite large uh messages not the typical text email that you get and so that if spammers use
that it's very difficult um to prevent them from consuming bandwidth so for evading plot tests sorry for evading
for evading for evading blacklists with blacklists typically don't say oh filter everything with the word
viagra or anything with the word uh bathtub no they typically list uh ip addresses and host names of known spammers
so one time trial and very effective trick that spammers use is called thin pipe thick pipe
and it works like this so you have a target server let's say that serves uh let's say a particular company
let's say uci ready right so this is our uh sftp server and the spammer wants to send a lot of spam to
uci uh people like us okay so the spammer controls a botnet a botnet is full of zombies okay zombie botnet
lsz stands for low speed zombie so this could be like one of your desktop computers in your lab or
you know it could be a an old laptop that you have at home some would be even an iot device
then the high speed bot is somewhere else this is geographically far away not near anywhere near the
low speed zone low speed zombies are many there are thousands maybe tens and thousands of them so
so the bot picks a zombie and says hey do a tcp handshake with that server right open smtp connection
then pass on the tcp sequence numbers remember tcp sequence numbers offset
to this high speed bar you might be getting where what i'm about to say bam send bulk mail with a source
low speed zone
remember ip addresses are not a form of authentication so so the high speed bot takes over the tcp session
you see what's happening here this session was initiated by a low speed zombie as soon as the
three-way tcp connection is established it passes on the sequence number to its big brother here
the big brother says all right and sends a lot of spam over to the target server
a target server thinks that this craft comes over on that connection you see
cool what happens
the high speed zombies ip address is hidden from the target server because what will happen
okay remember how tcp works right it's all acknowledgement right data acknowledgement data
acknowledgement and data can flow both ways but in email right in email what's happening is one relay
has mailed message to send the other one is the receiver so the receiver does not send big data back
right there's no messages to send back it's the sender that sends the message so the sender splits the
message into chunks remember like tcp segments right because that should be long the email message can be
long and it sends them with this via this tick line
with the ip address of the low speed zombie now that that target victim server is going to do
acknowledgments remember tcp acknowledgments they're not going to come on the thick pipe
do you see why they cannot right because the acknowledgments will go to the ip address of the
low speed zombie we don't assume that these guys are controlling internet routing
so that this guy cannot force the tcp acknowledgments from this target server to come to it
he cannot
they will come here and that's okay they're in cahoots with each other
so
he's going to keep passing the offset now low bandwidth and this is a low bandwidth channel right low bandwidth
the bulk of the data gets transmitted here it's a beautiful arrangement and it works now
eventually the target the cdp server will say hey this is spam right somebody will mark it as spam
and you'll say oh when did i receive it i received an ip address belonging to the low speed zombie
okay let's left list the zombie done no more email from that a b address is accepted that's okay
the high-speed bot goes on to the next zombie because he has thousands okay that other zombie that's done
barrier that g you get the idea
there are seven like amazing front-end tools for sending spam this is like one a bit old but it's an
example this is a sensei program for windows it's a it's a spam automator you can configure it
to send you see that it it from emails you can consider you can configure it to be like administrator
at uciadu president usa.gov uh god at heaven dot earth whatever you want you can put it in the from
uh you see the two aliases right this is to whom is this supposed to go webmaster administrator database
okay you can vary all of these things subjects you see the subjects vary the subjects right hi hello
how are you doing montano c etc okay and here's the actual middle text
it's marked up dear black right so the name will go in there meaning the name two
dear webmaster we'll go in there or or you see there's like a you don't want right here there's a
or there is an or or dear colleague don't even need to like specifically address the person or
hi account this is the typical way to identify when you see when you know it says hi john at uciadu
have you ever received non-spam that says hi john at uciadu or or anything any greeting followed by your
account name obviously that person does not know your name right so that's like a 99.99 indicator of
spam when somebody refers to you by your account name but i guess people fall for it sometimes
but it's a very nice automator
all right uh if you're wondering where you know where the open proxies are that you can actually
spend uh spam through well there's whole clearing houses of these of these proxies that you can what
does it mean you can go there find a proxy that is alive and configure that proxy to be your outgoing
smtp server so when you send email instead of going to google right or instead of going to uci
uh smtp edu it will go to that open proxy okay so you can set this down through
blacklisting turns out not to be enough because most ip addresses just like in a thin type
thick type example with a low speed zombie most ip addresses send very little standards
so blacklisting that's why is is very limited uh effectiveness because you blacklist something
and it will never spend some time again anyway by the time you blacklist it it's too late
right what does it show you it's a fraction of clients that says crap in number of appearances
it means most of them said like once and then they go away
okay because they're disposable where they come from well this is a while ago okay this is uh this
is a this is a this is a while ago but at the time this is like almost 20 years ago these were i
see the as number these are the organizations where spam originally it doesn't mean they spend spam it means
their clients sent spam
the the picture would be very different today i already said that
ah this was around 2010 2012 the world was ruled by uh what like half a thousand giant spam bots
yeah that was the world back then two particular had the lion's share swisbee and rostock they dominated
the world of spam they were not themselves creators of spam they were the engines of spam do you see what i'm
saying they were sending spam they were not creating it they were taking it from their clients and amplifying it
most of them used a provider in northern california nisp
okay that was uh very happy making money on them right uh it was not a bot but it had all these
clients right it hosted these command and control servers command and control server is the brain of a bot
right as the word name suggests command and control and so both rostock and frisbee were hosted right
there by this isp now you all know what the difference between hosting provider and isp
there's very they're similar but not the same you know the difference what's the difference what's the
difference what's the difference between a hosting provider and isp uh a hosting provider is like
so an isp provides the internet service and that's it pretty much yeah
a hosting a hosting doesn't provide internet service it provides like yeah it usually does i mean
yes true technically no usually does but but its primary purpose is to let you put your stuff on there
exactly so you can put your web server yeah on a hosting provider okay a world world press is a
hosting provider right like that google is a hosting provider uh but uh you're also tiny
this was a relatively small one but it hosted all this now when it was disconnected imagine this three
quarters of the spam in the world disappeared overnight that was incredible i remember it because uh
all of a sudden i heard of it like two days later i realized i used to receive a lot of spam i went
to my phone for the first time in 10 years there was no spam um now swisbee was it was an interesting
character it was a rookie and a mailer right so basically it was a combination of malware and spam
in order to have a a botnet you need to have zombies and you have zombies you must have malware they
created those zombies and zombified them so there's always malware involved in creating a botnet
it was at one point responsible for more than half the spam worldwide
and when the mid-color uh hosting provider was taken down the zombies did not disappear right they
still lived it's like you decapitate the head of the snake but the rest of it is still moving
so the zombies were motherless all of a sudden right the mother ship has gone away but whoever created
that botnet was pretty smart and they wanted to essentially for the zombies to look for a different
mother or a different command and control center and they were programmed to do so and they started
generating backup domains like this like weird looking backup domains and trying to connect to them
thinking where's my mother where's my mother right and sure enough the people who were behind this
botnet created for you know regain control of the zombies by creating a backup mother uh not surprising
through a registrar registrar is the assigned name authority that uh assigns domain names in a given
country every country has one well they did it for a russian registrar and hosted new commanding control
service in estonia so all of a sudden that was like a phoenix from ashes the zombies like in a
movie they arose and found themselves a mother a new mother it was then disconnected and shut down but
it was an interesting state rust talk no no no okay we're right all right i just want to well the rest of
it i guess we'll see either we'll cover it next time or if i decide to switch to a different topic then
you'll just read it on your own the thing i want to point out is there are legal ways of uh encountering
spam there's a can spam act that u.s uh uh federal government was passed by the congress in 2003 there
is something called spf which i mentioned earlier that is a technical way of fighting spam and there
is something called the main themes maybe we'll talk about it a little bit next time all right any questions
before we go yes in practice uh if you're like a user of say gmail and someone else is using gmail would
they would gmail actually use the smtp protocol or would they just like use standard you know in the
google universe you don't even need smtp protocol unless you're using an app so from your app to google
google is smtp with a 587 right what he said and after that there's probably no really right it's
totally internal to google it's like you know if you have hotmail account it's the same you're sending
to another hotmail very very very similar yeah now when you start crossing domains right what he's saying
from gmail to hotmail then you are you're going to have this relay to relay okay okay so other than
uh sample final anything else okay see you thursday
hey uh did you say uh the final date is it on 10. sorry the final exam date did you say anything
uh it declared in canvas yes yes okay you can see it from the uh