like SSL that we're going to go over later and there's some wireless, I think it ends
with some firewalls which also will go in depth and wireless.
Any questions from us?
So again, I would like to have your new proposals by next Tuesday, like last time.
If you have any fundamental questions there about what I expect, ask.
I'll have officers on Monday.
Again, I want to deal with two people.
No double dipping means not to use material that you did already or you're doing in parallel
in some other course.
So there has to be something distinct that you do for this part.
And if you plan to do writing, survey or something like that, no chatbots.
That should be you.
If you do use some tools that you are not sure, or you want to use some tools, you're not quite sure if this transcends the boundary, just ask.
It's easier to ask now than to explain later.
Okay, so user authentication, one of the basic topics in computer security.
How do we authenticate humans?
That means us.
All right, basic problem.
Somebody claims to be Alice or Bob, and now how do you prove that you are that Alice or Bob?
Now why do we do authentication?
We do authentication in order to enforce access control.
All right, just authentication for the sake of authentication isn't useful.
What's the point of authenticating you if nothing happens?
And any form of, any time you are asked for anything that identifies you and authenticates you, it's for some purpose.
Whether it's a policeman that stops you and says, where's your driver's license?
The driver's license is to let you go.
If you authenticate you, you let you go.
Then you get a ticket.
And without the driver's license, you might get arrested.
So no access to driving privileges, right?
If you work for a company, you use a badge and maybe sometimes a camera to authenticate you as an employee, right?
So you can have access to the premises.
You get into the UCI's Google space, right?
Google Docs and Drive space.
You authenticate it via a dual and password username so you can get access to those resources, et cetera, et cetera.
So there's always a reason for why you are being authenticated, right?
There is something that you are given access to if you succeed in authentication.
Okay.
So this pops up just about everywhere.
So, of course, as you know, there are many ways to prove that you are.
Say you are.
The most familiar ones are passwords.
Their demise has been predicted for the last 40 years, and yet they are still here.
Moreover, they show no signs of going away anytime soon.
An interesting parallel, email.
Email has been around since early 80s.
Pretty much the same way it is used to be.
Maybe the WYSIWYG changed, you know, the here and there, but the interfaces, et cetera.
But email is pretty much the same.
Same format email addresses, and every year somebody says, yeah, I guarantee it.
You know, it's like a doomsday.
You say, oh, yeah, the end of the world is coming tomorrow.
Just you wait.
And tomorrow comes, ah, you know what?
My clock was wrong.
I was like, yeah, it missed you.
Anyway, ah, the stars did not align.
So the same thing about email and password, doomsday predictions.
Email is still here.
Password is still here.
No signing going on.
Right.
So passwords we know, and nobody loves them, but we're used to them.
And then we have passphrases, right?
Or answers to personal questions.
Like, what color eyes do you like the most?
Or, what was the make of your first automobile?
Really difficult questions, right?
And then there are, of course, secret keys, right?
So we can use some secret keys.
If you can remember them, you can use them, right?
Or you can write them down, which will be a lot of fun.
But these are things you know, presumably.
Pins are, of course, another form.
It's a variation of the theme of passwords, right?
Because they're supposed to be numbers, not alphanumeric characters.
Then you can do authentication based on where you are.
So that is, if you are in some space, and you can prove you are in some space, geographical
location, then you must have access to something.
You might be giving access to something.
Like, if you are in some secure room in the Pentagon, by virtue of being in that secure
room, you're allowed to access some computer system or some database.
I'm not saying that's how it should be, but it can be like that.
It could also be an IP address given to you by your internet provider.
So, for example, if you live in the campus housing, your entry is provided by UCI, right?
As opposed to, say, me, I also live on campus, Canada campus, I think on Union Hills here,
next to campus, my address is provided by Cox.
And all my neighbors are in the cost of Google to buy them.
So the IP address tells you something.
If you believe me, the IP address, of course.
It could be home phone, right?
Of course, people don't use home phones anymore, right?
Landlines are rare.
Cell phone.
Cell phone used to be able to, many, many, many years ago, if you had a certain cell phone number,
then you had to be in a particular space, because back then there was no roaming, right?
So if your phone number worked, that means you were, you know, with a 949 area code,
you were in North County.
It doesn't work anymore.
Now, MAC addresses, could they be used for identifying where you are, right?
Or for anything at all?
Everybody knows what MAC addresses is, right?
Theoretically, MAC addresses supposed to tell you something about the interface of the device.
Any ideas?
No?
Too early?
MAC addresses have a special format.
They actually should tell you who the manufacturer of the device, or the interface.
It doesn't tell you necessarily where you are, and that's why I put a question mark there.
Also, MAC addresses are impermanent.
There was a time when most devices that have MAC addresses, you couldn't change them.
Today, you can change MAC addresses on most laptops, industrial or desktop systems, most laptops, cell phones, and other guys.
Also, even if MAC addresses were impermanent, MAC addresses are only used for the one hub, right?
That's a data link layer.
So, in this room, the MAC address is only visible to the access point.
But beyond the access point, it has no meaning, right?
There's nothing.
It doesn't longer go there.
Okay, then there's what you are as a human, right?
Now, what you are are your intrinsic features, like your DNA, right?
Your fingerprints, your eyes, your face geometry, your hand geometry, your vein pattern on your wrist.
There's gait, where you are, not a very good biometric, but that's in you.
All kinds of other things.
And then there is the one that you are familiar with the most, which is what you have, right?
It's a possession of something.
We know this, right?
This is the most frequent two-factor.
You have the app on your phone, and it's visually secure.
You trust the app.
The app will pop up, right?
Either with the approve, disapprove, or a code, right?
The temporary code, that essentially, by entering that code or hitting approve,
you're saying, I'm in possession of this phone.
And because this phone has been pre-registered as associated with you,
there's a reasonable assumption that because you have this phone,
and previously you entered the right password and username,
must be the case that you are a police agent.
And if you think of it, any other?
Might I miss something?
Any other basis upon which you can be authenticated?
What you know, where you are, what you are, what you have.
Some people suggested where you've been, but that's hard to remember.
So, how do our passwords work?
No.
Quiet track.
Yeah.
Without a sign.
So, must not be able to remember.
Right.
So, you have a secret password.
You pick the secret password, and the system checks to authenticate that password.
Now, sometimes, of course, you don't pick the secret password,
sometimes the secret password is given to you.
Like, how many of you have used a browser to select a secret password?
Then you don't actually know anything.
Right?
All you do is, what?
You log into your computer, or your, uh, smartphone computer, like that.
And, the idea is that the browser, especially something like Chrome, let's say.
I want to pick, I use Firefox sometimes here, but let's say Chrome, which is popular.
Um, you also have to log into your profile, right?
On Chrome.
So, you log into the computer, you log into the browser, but the browser doesn't know what
you log into the computer.
So, in fact, you log into your profile on Chrome, and that essentially unlocks the so-called
password vault, or password bundle, that is stored in your profile on Chrome.
Not super reassuring, right?
But, convenient, because as long as you use that Chrome, right?
Actually, it doesn't have to be Chrome there, right?
You could be using Chrome somewhere else.
You know, if you set it up correctly, that password that Chrome picked for you will be available
once you authenticate with the right folder.
Right.
So, initialization, but typically the password initialization is you pick the password based
on some password rules.
Which vary, of course, from site to site, from time to time.
And, um, how do you actually communicate with the log in time for the first time, right?
Or for subsequent times, right?
There is always this risk of eavesdropping.
Right?
So, if you imagine the most naive way of communicating a password is you type your password and then
it just goes somewhere.
Now, if it's a local computer, maybe you can have a little more trust.
You trust the operating system that the log in prompt is actually from the operating system.
Right?
So, when you turn on your laptop, you have tablets and laptops, and when you open it, so turn
it on, and the log in prompt occurs, and says, usually it doesn't say username, right?
You can't, right?
But usually it just ends your password.
Do you know who's asking you for a password?
Who's still a computer?
Do you know who's asking?
Should be the operating system.
Is it the operating system?
Do you have any way to verify that, in fact, the window that shows you the login is the operating
system window?
I say no.
I don't think you know.
Maybe if you have an encrypted disk, would you type in your password and connect it for
But even then, I mean, if it just scrolls the right things, it says bias, blah blah blah blah, authenticating, initializing, enterprise, you don't know.
So, I'm not trying to cause panic here, but you should be aware that, so you have a little more sure when your computer is doing a cold boot, right?
Because it's functionally like turned off, although that's a whole other story.
How do you know your device is turned off?
We will touch upon this in a couple of days.
You often tell it to turn off, you press the button, and how do you know it's off?
Well, you say, well, you know what, I'll just unplug it from the wall.
Are you sure that's on?
Are you sure there's no battery?
Do you know what's inside the device?
They have CMOS battery, too.
Ah, yeah, but you should like disassembling the device, voiding the warranty, and causing electric shock, potentially.
So, actually, you don't.
So, that's a depressing thought, right?
You actually don't know who is asking for the password.
But we trust.
Okay, but that's the password that goes to your operating system, right?
It doesn't go on the wire, right?
It's not sent anywhere.
What about if you're logging into Facebook, or, you know, your Instagram, or whatever, your favorite website, or any kind of service?
Like, you're going into UCI.
A window pops up that looks like UCI's little pop-up, with blue and stuff, you know, all the right colors.
How busy is this to copy?
So, you enter your password, and then it goes.
So, you don't know.
But let's suspend our disbelief, and say, okay, we trust that it goes, it goes to the right place, okay, okay, okay.
But what about how is it sent?
Is it sent in clear text?
That's bad, right?
It can't be sent in clear text, because then it gets used to the other part.
Okay, well, you hope that actually in reality, it sends over a secure connection.
And sort of prior to you entering the password, whatever the stub application, whether it's a browser, a client browser, or some other application on your laptop, or your phone,
has already established a secure, usually TLS, or VPN connection, to the other end.
But even then, you might not trust that connection.
So, probably not a good idea to send the password unencrypted, even over the connection.
So, what's typically done is the password is, like, hashed.
Remember hash functions, right?
Yeah.
Now the question is, where is it hashed?
So, who gets to see your password locally?
Maybe it's hashed in software, with a client software.
Maybe it's hashed in hardware.
Maybe there's a way for the login prompt, or if it presents you with a password prompt,
to communicate directly to some hardware inside your laptop of a smartphone,
that actually takes that password, hashes it, and that's it.
And then there's a template resistant, because if it's not, maybe, you know, somebody can hack it.
And then, how does the other end check the password?
Well, and of course, is your password guessable?
Right?
None of this other stuff is important if your password is weak.
If I can, with reasonable probability, guess your password,
all the other measures to prevent theft and misuse of password, they're useless.
Because guessing a password means somebody is going to try to log in, just like you would.
So, whatever measures are taken after you enter a password and hit return,
they're useless if the password is being guessed.
Also, on most operating systems, it's difficult to keep a password file secret.
Especially like multi-user systems.
So, I know that you are all used to, essentially, single-user computers, right?
I mean, how many people usually have, like, multiple profiles on their Android?
I mean, you can do it, but it's a pain.
How many of you share your laptop with others?
My guess is not many, if any.
Maybe when you were younger, and you had, like, a sibling, and you shared your laptop.
Or the parent will let you use their laptop and create an account.
But most people, like, you're 80, they don't share laptops.
So, this does not seem relevant to you, but think about a bigger world out there.
Like, an organization.
Where you have multiple users, multiple, many users,
and they all need to log in and access the same system.
So, you need to store the password database somewhere, the password file, right?
And so, in modern systems, at least one of the Unix derived,
historically, the password file is accessible.
It's called world-readable.
And the reason it's world-readable is because it's not just the password file.
It's, essentially, the user database.
And so, programs that run on Linux, or Unix, and whatever,
all these Unix-derived operating systems,
they need to consult that file, not for the password's sake,
but for account's sake, to figure out what accounts have rights for what resources.
So, it's mostly for access control.
Okay?
This was done a long time ago, when Unix first was born, in the 80s.
Now, with hard-to-remember passwords,
if you don't pick a weak password, you pick a hard-to-remember password, you're good.
And if your memory is good, wonderful.
But what about reusing passwords?
A lot of people can remember one difficult password.
Right?
I'm sure you can remember one difficult password.
That is not, by any standard, weak.
But then, can you remember 10, 15?
These days, most of us have well over 10,
some of us, I would say, around 20 different accounts.
There have been some studies about this, but I don't think it's an immediate number.
You could carry around an object, like some kind of a device, like a smartphone,
maybe, that has your passwords all stored there in plain text.
And you unlock your phone, you access your password, and you're like, oh, great.
What if you don't have your phone?
What if somebody steals your phone?
What if a malicious app on the phone exfiltrated that file?
So there is a cottage industry out there called, you know, Password Vault.
Maybe, have anybody used Password Vault?
I mean, some of them are, there are some free, but most of them are cost-mine.
And some companies do use those.
Okay, but guess what?
Well, when you have a company that runs the services, Password Vault Vault,
a third-party Password Vault Vault, they become like honey or a swarm of bees.
They are a super attractive attack target, and just like this DA that we talked about last time,
it's like, attack me.
Because this is where the friendly jewels are.
You get into a password-drawn company, you get into their databases,
whether through outside or inside attack, and you wind up with a big dirt.
Big prize, right?
Tons of passwords.
So I'm not clear that that's a good solution.
Then there's like denial of service issues, right?
If you store your passwords on your phone, if the phone is lost,
or like what happened to me a couple of months ago,
the phone just died, and there's no way.
I mean, it's dead beyond all salvation.
There's no way you can take anything out.
So now it's stuck with having to change all the passwords.
It's like a denial of service.
And for a while, your account's essentially off-limits to you.
One of the more interesting and super easy attacks, by the way,
with a denial of service goal.
Let's say you want to attack a particular company, right?
Let's say you have a company called XYZ Incorporated
that provides access to, I don't know, cute squirrel videos.
And they specialize in cute squirrels only.
No ugly squirrels.
And all the squirrel lovers in the world create accounts there
and just love, you know, it's like popular, right?
So all this community, probably not large,
because how many squirrel lovers out there,
they actively use this service,
and then somebody who wants to just piss them off
or maybe has a competing company decides to mount it in our service.
All they need to do is not break any passwords.
All they need to do is get a large enough sample of the usernames
or people who have an account.
All you do, you can program this.
You can run into this by hand.
Essentially, try to log in.
So for every account, let's say Alice has an account.
Write the username Alice, random password, click.
Username Bob, random password, click.
Do it three times, do it four times,
whatever the little threshold.
Use it, it's a little threshold.
For number of failed logins, right?
What happens?
You're locked out.
So when real users come back to log in,
due to the large number of successive failed login attempts,
you need to contact this 1-800 number in Mauritania.
Good luck.
With awful hours.
With, yes, of course.
We're only open between 3.30 and 4.30 p.m. Hawaii time.
Good luck.
Good luck, right?
Because then, of course, they want to make sure it's you.
Even if it's done in automated fashion
with some other second factor,
all back email, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
It's a giant waste of time.
And a logistical nightmare.
So, a great attack.
You can program a bot to do this, right?
You can go for, like, even random usernames.
Eventually, you're going to find usernames that are existing.
Login, login, login.
Bam.
Locked out.
So, no passwords need to be broken.
So, let's see.
Then there's social engineering.
Social engineering is, like, this whole thing in its own right.
You can teach a class on that, just on social engineering.
But it's not really computer science.
Social engineering is all about how to trick people.
So, maybe more appropriate than psychology or some other department.
But it's a wonderful opportunity for attackers, right?
And a lot of spectacular hacks in this world that you've heard about
that sound really, really technical.
I suspect it's TouchNet and Mirai and all these other things.
I think they all, I'm pretty sure,
they all somehow involve elements of social engineering.
Social engineering means human.
Right?
Human interaction is elicitation of sensitive information
in verbal form.
Non-analog form.
Okay?
The typical social engineering attack
probably doesn't work at night today,
but, you know,
a CIO or a, let's say,
no, it's an IT person,
in the middle of the night,
in some department of some random company,
receives a panicked phone call
from the vice president
of, I don't know,
toilet affairs,
and says,
I am stuck in
Timbuktu
on a
very important company trip.
I'm dealing with clients.
All of a sudden,
my phone broke.
I cannot log in.
Help.
Millions of dollars
of business are at stake.
The panicked IT clerk,
who's sleepy,
and probably has,
I don't know,
DeVry Institute course
or education or something,
says,
oh, of course,
yes, sir.
And says,
okay,
here's a one-time login code,
go in this,
do this.
Yeah,
that's it.
That's the end of it.
That's the back door.
That allows the attacker
to get in.
It's still super common.
Yeah,
I'm sure,
you know,
every once in a while,
in a research literature,
or even at, like,
Black Hat,
DEFCON,
you will hear talks
about people saying,
okay,
we did this kind of
probing attack
against 500 companies
than, like,
Brazil,
I heard one talk.
And the particular talk
I heard is that,
you know,
when this was about
the attacks
on the Brazilian banks,
right,
and essentially utilizing
what I just described,
calling at random hours
and pretending to be somebody.
They didn't even invent somebody.
They actually pretended
to be somebody
who worked for the company.
So, you know,
the hackers know in advance.
They've done their research.
They've looked
for the company charts
and said,
who is awake?
Oh, this guy is on vacation.
So,
it is really believable
when most of it is true.
So, they call it,
say,
I'm so-and-so.
I'm on vacation
in Florida.
Oh,
so-and-so.
Yes,
he's on vacation.
Element of truth
goes a long way.
Right?
That's kind of
human psychology.
It works.
In the U.S.,
there were studies that,
oh, you know,
just like infomercials.
I don't know
if you even know
what infomercials are,
but this is a curious thing.
When Americans listen
to a voice
of a salesman,
it helps
if their voice
has a refined British accent.
Maybe you should wonder why.
If somebody speaks like they're
from the deep south,
forget it.
If somebody speaks like they're
from Brooklyn,
forget it.
But if somebody speaks
with a refined British accent,
carefully enunciating
every single syllable,
I'll do every single word
they say.
Most of us,
this country,
oh, yes,
I'm you.
What can I do?
Right?
So that's part
of social engineering.
Right?
So,
another reason is,
another way that it works
is the attacker
will know some information
about you.
Right?
So if they want to impersonate you
or want to get into your account,
they will know information.
Social security numbers,
days of birth,
those are a lot of difficult
things to find out.
Right?
Social security numbers
used to be believed
to be secret.
Nobody believes
to be secret in these days.
Even though we still
keep them private,
but I can buy
your social security number
if you have one.
It's not going to cost me
very much.
And so if I buy it,
even if it costs me
a couple hundred dollars,
it allows me essentially,
well,
not just social security,
but along with
other information
like David Burr,
driving the last time
in December,
maybe open a bank account
online.
Great.
If I open a bank account,
I can rent something
in your name.
Like an apartment.
Establish a gas company
relationship.
Electrical company.
Right?
Essentially,
start stealing your identity.
Yeah,
so,
this is like entertainment,
but anyway,
passwords are a pain.
So we're going to focus
for a moment
on the passwords.
There have been
tons of breaches
in the middle,
but by the way,
this is super old.
All these examples
are super old,
and yet,
I don't refresh them.
They're like 20 years old.
But,
this happens every year.
The similar things
that happened
20,
25 years ago
still happen.
Right?
If you go to the
website,
passwordpresearch.com,
they have lots
of interesting
articles.
Right?
So,
why do people
want your password?
So,
of course,
one of the reasons
they may want your password
is just to log in
and just delete your files.
They just hate you
and they want to
suck.
That doesn't happen
very often.
It can.
I mean,
you make some enemies,
you probably can.
But,
this is very personal.
Generally,
what somebody wants
is more than just
your password.
So,
installing a key log
or a sniffer
is another way.
And then,
basically,
you sniff for more passwords.
Especially if your account,
getting into your account,
is privileged.
Right?
So,
maybe it will be able
to run a sniffer
that will sniff
on other people's passwords.
The other thing
is to steal the password file.
And once you steal
the password file,
well,
then you can run
password cracking too much.
Because the password file,
as you can already imagine,
doesn't actually store
a real password,
but stores hashes.
Right?
So,
all you need to do
is try a brute force adapt.
Alright?
So,
Unix-style passwords
work like this,
right?
You enter your password,
it hashes,
and then this is
the etc.
etc. password file
that has one line
for a user,
generally,
and it contains,
among other things,
so the line,
the one line is like,
it's a text file.
So,
one line for a record,
oh,
one line is a record,
and this record
is for a given user,
and it has some
non-human accounts,
okay?
net, like root,
and admin,
or whatever,
some other,
some other cron account,
but it also has one
for every user.
And so,
when you enter a username,
the username is also
stored there in the clear.
So,
people realized early on
that it's not a good idea
to store a password there,
so why don't we store a hash?
So,
great,
the system doesn't know
your password,
it only knows the hash,
and because,
presumably,
we use a good cryptographic hash,
like the kind we talked about
briefly last time,
hash is supposed to be
one way.
Yeah?
One way means that,
yeah,
the inverting,
like knowing a hash,
and learning what the input
to the hash was,
is hard.
But is it really?
If the input space
is very large,
it is hard.
But if the input space
is constricted,
it might not be so hard.
But wait,
there's more.
Hashing is better
than encryption,
maybe you will realize why.
You know why?
I mean,
encrypting a block,
it should be,
it's usually roughly equivalent
to hashing a block.
All you think encryption
is not used.
And hashing is used.
No decryption.
Yeah,
that's a reason,
it's not that.
Major reason.
I hope you've never
had to see the thing
that's passed through
and that's been honest.
Okay,
now you're getting close.
What else does encryption
mean?
You want to encrypt the question.
No,
it leaks the length,
doesn't it?
Hmm.
So you want to have
the uniform
value,
right?
There are other reasons,
then you can think of some.
Encryption is not,
now encryption,
that's,
let me rephrase
what I said,
be very careful.
Encryption as in
something that can be reversed
is not used.
You can use encryption
to build a hash function.
An encryption function
can be used
to build a hash function.
Okay,
so it's okay
to use encryption function
to build a hash function
that you can use
for this purpose.
But what we don't do
is encrypt
the password itself.
Okay?
So remember the
properties of hash functions,
right?
So if you are a password hacker
and you want to
break the password,
what property
would you like
the hash function
not to have?
Well,
one way is we agree.
We all must have,
right?
Because it should be
difficult to go back
and figure out
from the hash
what the password
is going to be.
But what about
these other things?
Remember,
there's a strong
collision resistance
and weak collision resistance.
Which do we care
about?
Yeah.
Strong
would be nice to have
but not super important
because
the password
is specific,
right?
It's given.
It's given
to the hacker
but it's fixed
by the hash,
right?
So in order
to break
the system
without learning
the password,
the hacker
has to find
another password
that hashes
into the same value.
Does that make sense?
So if your password
is Apple
and it hashes
into
and I pick
Pear
and it also
hashes into
the 345
I don't need
to know
Apple.
I can just
log into your account
by typing Pear.
OK?
So
that weak collision
resistance
and that's
what we need.
So
I'm not sure
how many
to do it
but historically
that's what
has been done
is that
Linux
was using
DES
encryption
as a hash
function.
Now how
does it do it?
Well,
it takes
a null
string
a 64-bit
now you remember
DES is a 64-bit block
so it takes
a string of
64-bits
long
and then
encrypts it
repeatedly
OK?
Repeatedly
25 times
using
a DES
key
that is
derived
from the
password.
OK?
Make sense?
So it converts
your password
into a key
now that's
also
an interesting
detail
because
DES keys
are actually
56-bits
long
I mean
they're 64
but 8-bits
are parity-bits
so
that's an
interesting one
so we'll come
back to that
in a second.
The idea
so why do
they do this
or why did
because in
order to
mount a
brute force
attack
on a password
you would
have to
guess the
password
and perform
encryptions
or
if you like
decryptions
and at
the end
OK?
If you
hit 0
if what
you decrypt
after 25
decryptions
and 0
and a
string of
0s
you guessed
correctly.
OK?
Or
alternatively
you would
take
a string
of 0s
and encrypt
it 25
times
and see
if that
matches
the result
in the
password
file.
Am I
with you?
Any
questions?
So
it's a
clever idea
right?
The idea
was to
slow down
the
attacker
that is
for every
guess
of a
password
or every
possible
password
the attacker
guesses
it would
have to
perform
encryption
or decryption
operations.
that's
a lot
and back
then
DESC was
implemented
mostly in
hardware
it was
very slow
in software
so it
seemed like
a good idea.
And then
of course
passwords aren't
really random
right?
Doesn't matter
how old you
are, doesn't
matter what
culture
or which
country
which
ethnicity
you come
from
within the
group that
you come
from
you're
likely to
pick a
password
that is
not
truly
random.
There's
no such
thing as
humans
picking
truly
random
passwords.
Even if
you say
well
I know
a certain
date
where
let's
say
I
don't
know
I
graduated
from
college
or
I
had
my
first
date
or
something
auspicious
happened
on a
particular
date
and
nobody
else
knows
it
just
you
think
that
might
be
random
but
actually
it's
not.
I
think
about
are
dates
really
random?
There's
a lot
of
people
use
them
professionally.
Think
about
how
we
structure
dates.
Forget
hours
a
minute
just
dates.
I
mean
depending
on
which
notation
it
used
to
them
in
the
United
States
we
use
month
day
year
right?
How
many
months
are
there?
Well
last time I
said
how many
days are
there?
Let's be
generous and
say 51
in every
month
right?
They're
honest
right?
Let's say
they're
out because
the maximum
and how many
years is it?
Well
there are a lot
of years
but you're not
likely to pick
a year from
dark ages
history
and
yeah
if you're
a fan
of history
you might
pick
something
ancient
Egyptian
era
or
something
from
the
time
of
William
the
Conqueror
but
most of
us
would pick
something
reasonably
more
21st
century
so
that
does not
be
vulnerable
that's
not
random
and the
space
of that
is
very
small
so
don't
pick
dates
in any
format
right
so
but if
you just
look at
the
upper
and
lower
case
letters
that is
being
generous
assuming
that
whatever
system
we're
working
distinguishes
between
upper
and
lower
case
because
some
systems
do
not
right
they'll
just
convert
everything
to
upper
case
or
lower
case
so
in English
that's
26 times
plus
digits
and
punctuation
symbols
although
many
password
rules
will not
allow you
to use
punctuation
they might
allow you
to use
like
exclamation
point
the question
mark
the dot
and maybe
that's it
but okay
let's be
generous
so that
gives us
plus 10
plus 32
that's
and let's
say we
limit to
8 characters
because
that's
pretty much
how many
of you
have
passwords
that I
exceed
8 characters
yeah
I buy
a lot
how many
exceed
12 characters
look at
you
okay
you like
entering
passwords
don't you
because
there's
a big
trade-off
here
right
the big
trade-off
is
okay
so
let's
say
I'm
not going
to
triangulate
your
password
here
but let's
say you
have
character
password
and
he has
an 8
character
password
now we
have
usability
issue
let's
say
you're
young
smart
you can
remember
characters
obviously
you can
right
but what
about
making
mistakes
in
those
characters
as you
type
have
we
never
did
mistakes
right
how likely
let's
put it
another way
how likely
are you
to make
a mistake
in an
character
password
as opposed
to a
character
password
much more
likely
there are
some
people
fatigued
right
I mean
finger
fatigued
you have
to stare
at the
keyword
so
there's
that
second
issue
is the
time
it just
takes
longer
to enter
that
password
so
while I
find it
commendable
that you
guys use
this long
password
that's
great
that doesn't
mean you're
out of the
woods
with attacks
you know
but
there is a
trade-off
right
and most
people
I mean
they're okay
with like
not super
short
passwords
but like
research
show that
8 is
about
the right
mix
but with
characters
which is
I think
for most
people
and I
suspect
most people
your age
have picked
some better
passwords
than let's
say your
uncles
and grandparents
and parents
because you
know
who are less
confused
having
you're going
to wind up
with roughly
6 quadrillion
possible passwords
well to a
kid this
sounds really
impressive
right
you just
explain how
many zeros
are
but we're
all adults
here
6 quadrillion
is not a
large number
okay
not at all
right
and
since
given
freedom
to pick
right
without like
actual
restriction
most of us
will pick
things like
human and
pet names
and dictionary
words
we're going to
wind up
with
2 to the
essentially
a 20-bit
password
which means
that
even if
your password
is 8
characters
the real
entropy
there
is
about
minutes
meaning
that
human
death
names
and all
the dictionary
words
will roughly
be about
2 to the
point
that's
assuming
the language
is known
so you
assume
your password
is English
like
if you
are
Swahili
speaker
then a whole
different
thing
will apply
it will
be based
on the
vocabulary
of that
language
but
you
have
to
assume
that
hacker
knows
about
that
yeah
so
and
if you
think
pins
are
better
they're
not
because
you
get
with
maximum
2 to the
with
digit
pins
and
that's
something
that
any
software
on your
phone
you can
do
in
seconds
just
iterate
for all
of those
so
that's
not a
scary
number
on
the
websites
they often
restrict
length
for
I get
they have
to store
in a
database
somehow
but why
in the
world
would they
ever
that
takes
no sense
to me
either
symbols
they
so
I think
the reason
okay
you're asking
two questions
why do they
restrict
the length
and why
they don't
allow
symbols
none of
those two
make sense
to me
but I have
a potential
explanation
for why
they don't
allow certain
symbols
is because
they think
these are
executable
some kind
of like
they're
trigger symbols
that somehow
some of
these things
like
slash slash
or back
slash back
dollar sign
can be used
if you somehow
cause a buffer
overflow
they can
so there's
some like
suspicion
of these symbols
dating back years
nobody really
knows why
but that's
my suspicion
why
do they
truncate
and allow
only
fixed
up to a certain
number of
characters
I don't know
that
that may be
it makes no
sense because
it's hashed
and it may be
again that
whoever programmed
the front end
no
they're also
afraid of
these kind
of buffer
overflows
and so on
and memory
bugs
because
you allow
unlimited number
of characters
they're thinking
you're going to
enter 2,000
characters
something is going
to break
in the code
I know
I'm with you
on that
I think that's
silly
right because
there's no
justification
it's only the
front end
because of the
back end
they're hashed
and they're all
the same way
it's a heat
map
some of the
stuff I'll show
you is really
dated
dated as in
like 10 years
old
more than 10
years old
none of it
changed since
people still
think
similar
faster
because the
fundamental
human
mentality
hasn't
changed
what is
a heat
map
what does
it mean
is that
you see
where
things are
really
hot
there
yellow
right
and so
over here
it's a heat
map generated
from a
leaked
password
database
a giant
leaked
password
database
okay
so
this is
a pin
sorry
this is not
a pin
heat map
and so
over here
where it's
really hot
dates
dates are
different
from other
pins
this is
you know
day
month
type
dates
right
and then
related couplets
meaning repeated
things like
they're all
along this
diagonal thing
okay
and these are
years of
specific years
of 19 something
because probably
birth years
people
for people
to take
passwords
back
so
as I said
before
the
Unix
and all
the other
Unix
like systems
have this
etsy
password file
and it's
world readable
for reasons
I already
explained
so
if you don't
do anything
and just
store the
hashed
passwords
in that
file
the attacker
will
easily
before
even knowing
what that
file is
before breaking
in or getting
an accident
the attacker
can precompute
a large table
of all the
hashed
passwords
yeah
I mean
passwords are
passwords right
you can just
pick all the
dictionary words
all the dictionary
words are
reversed
all the
two word
combination
let's restrict
our discussion
to English
for now
okay
because
similar things
apply to
other languages
but let's say
yeah
all the date
in a standard
US format
all the
even times
of day
using
you know
after a second
let's say
granularity
you can precompute
hashes of all
these values
combinations
of all these
values
pet names
city names
state names
university
mascot names
right
all of these
can be precomputed
in a large
database
stored in a large
that is something
a task that
an adversary
could do
and would take
maybe a day
or two
maybe less
this can be
stored
and it can be
done at your
own leisure
now
at the time
of intrusion
when the
adversary gains
access to
the password
file
all the
adversary
needs to
do
is extract
the hashed
passports
and do it
database
basically
am I with you
very simple
so a little bit
of work ahead
of it
and then
no work
essentially
once the
password file
becomes available
not only that
but the
adversary can
break into
multiple systems
and reuse
that same
work that
we did
earlier
right
it's not like
he has to
brute force
anything again
just a bunch
of database
who comes
so that's
nice
for the
adversary
bad for
us
right
this is
called an
offline
attack
because the
adversary has
done the
bulk of
the work
offline
and online
just does
lookouts
so that's
why salt
unlike what
the doctors
say is good
for you
we don't
store hash
passwords in
new
password file
we store
salted
passwords
means
at the
time of
the initial
creation of
a user
account
the system
or the
administrator
will pick
a random
number
called a
salt
that random
number is
only used
there in
the password
file
it isn't
stored in
the plain
text
but it's
not reused
so different
systems will
have different
salts for the
same user
so you
have a record
something that
looks something
like this
this is maybe
a little outdated
that green box
you see
gts would be my
account name
the salt will be
that number
right
the first blue
number
the second is
the hash
then you have
like user
identity
uid
i think that
the 14510 is
uid
30 i don't
remember
group id or
something
then the full
name
like what my
actual name is
and then the
login shell
right
and today is
probably like a
lot more
at least that
but we're not
interested in
the rest of the
stuff
the important
thing is
the salt
and the
password
that has
together
okay
so what
happens
very simple
little mandate
right
but makes a
big difference
that offline
attack
is no longer
possible
why not
well let me
give you an
example
suppose the
salt was
one decimal
digit
would the
offline
attack
be
possible
one
just one
decimal
digit
meaning
it's a
number
from zero
to ten
would it
be possible
to mount
this offline
attack
of course
it's possible
why not
right
just the work
increases tenfold
right
but okay
now it depends
on how long
exactly you make
it
but suppose
you make it
128 bits
oh
now
one digit
128 bits
instead of
like what
one digit
is like
three digits
right
so from three
bits to 128
bits
now the
adversary
cannot do
an offline
attack
because remember
for every
guess of the
password
that the
adversary
makes
he has to
multiply
do it
two to the
128 times
per password
so it
will be
two to the
128 times
whatever
even two to
the 20
right
is
beyond reach
of the
adversary
today and
for
what it
would be
so originally
they made the
salt
32 bits
I'm not sure
exactly what
it is
because it
varies
I think the
length of the
salt varies
from unique
flavor
to unique
but if I
were using
it today
I would
want the
salt to
be at
least
80 but
probably
more like
than salt
is
healthier
okay
but salt
makes a big
difference
now once the
attacker breaks
in
okay
now there's a
crucial difference
between offline
and online
attack
once the
attacker
breaks in
and reads
the
lc password
file
okay
the attacker
sees the
salt
so then the
attack becomes
much cheaper
but it can
only be
mounted
once he
breaks in
not ahead
because
by knowing
the salt
you shave
off the
2 to the
okay
and that
basically
the explanation
is the same
thing
just take a
second
to read it
well you shave
off the
2 to the
number 28
but it's
no longer
only off
line
fully attack
no no
it's online
it's not
offline
at all
the attacker
breaks in
learns the
salt
and now
has to do
with that
salt
whatever
2 to the
however many
password
guesses
there are
per user
yeah
so there's
still a bit
of work
but it's
not a scary
amount of work
I'm sorry
I mean
we can
let the salt
expire
well
you can
let the salt
expire
but you
have to
replace it
in the
password
file
so
what you're
saying
is that
you know
if you
know
that
they
have
the
so
it
takes
at least
hours
to
mount
an
online
attack
once
he
learns
the
salt
then
you
could
change
the
salt
every
hour
you could
but the
problem is
okay
so this is a good question
let's think about this
that what you say
would be useful
or would be
possible
if
just
a password
attack
a brute force
password
attack
would take
hours
but remember
once the adversary
breaks in
and learns
the salt
he then
also knows
the hash of the salt
and the password
right
so the adversary
knows this
right
that
the
well
that
the adversary
knows this
right
once he breaks in
he knows this
and he also knows
the salt
so you can change
but he learned
the previous salt
and the hash
of the previous salt
plus password
he's gonna break
the password
see
he's gonna break
the password
so changing the salt
at that point
not effective
because
if he's breaking
it locally
maybe
but
you know
others
he's gonna
exfiltrate
and break
it on his own
path
so
the password
hasn't changed
that's the main
problem
but here
it says
I think
I may be wrong
it wasn't
I think
it was even
less
it was 12
bits
originally
well today
12 bits
is laughable
right
so what
is it
saying
if the
passwords
come from
I don't
know
2 to the
space
and multiplied
by 2 to the
you still
get 2 to
which is
a laughably
small number
or password
bracket
right
it takes
a minute
or less
to go for
the 2 to the
password
choice
right
so
instead
what happens
these days
is that
most systems
actually
kind of
separate
the two
things
they separate
the password
from
the account
information
in Unix
and that's
kind of
a good
practice
anyway
so
they create
what's called
shadow
password
and so
instead of
looking like
what you saw
before
the account
record
in the
etsy
password
file
has
the name
and then
all the other
information
but there's
like an
x
following the
accounting
that says
actual password
isn't here
it's a
special
hashed
password file
which is not
world readable
like it took
only 30 years
for people to realize
that the passwords
and user account
information
shouldn't be stored
together
well that's what
happens
right
because all
those other
programs
application programs
running on
this Unix
like operating
system
they still
do need
the account
information
to figure out
who can access
what
etc
and distinguish
between users
but
they don't
need to know
the passwords
right
so
let's create
a file
that has
all the account
information
that also
store passwords
in
passwords
should only
be visible
to the root
or the admin
account
right
so instead
it's stored
in an etsy
shadow file
which is only
readable
by the
system
administrator
okay
also
very trivial
thing
and of course
it also
added expiration
date
for passwords
right
so that's
why on
most
production
Unix
like systems
you'll be
asked to
renew
or
change
another
password
every so
often
okay
so
you've probably
heard of
keyloggers
right
so these
are things
you generally
have to be
afraid of
not so much
on your own
devices
because
it's not
all that
easy
to install
a keylogger
unless
somebody
has
direct
access
and an
account
on your
device
but
more like
when you're
using
public
facility
like
any of
you ever
use
ICS
terminals
or ICS
machines
but that's
where you
have to
be worried
about
because
there you
have no
idea
what software
is running
who has
been there
before
you
essentially
these
machines
are
sort of
like
public
toilet
you have
no idea
what's
going on
there
and
what
is
running
there
really
so
if
these
drugloggers
are
problem
they
can be
hardware
based
or
software
based
hardware
means
somebody
actually
inserted
something
you
know
external
keyboards
not the
kind
you have
right now
in front
of you
but
actual
keyboards
move on
they have
a wire
some of them
do
don't
but most
have a wire
well
the wire
goes in the
back of the
computer
somewhere
or
some
USB
interface
well
somebody
could have
installed
something
between
the USB
interface
and the
back
of the
computer
you cannot
see
especially
publicly
and
essentially
it
sees
every
keystroke
you have
okay
some
government
computers
in various
agencies
do this
on purpose
they tell
employees
your
keystrokes
are locked
and there's
a keylogger
for
auditability
and logging
purposes
but
do you
yourself
whenever
you use
a public
or at least
not personal
but do you
have a look
to see
that the
wire
goes directly
into the
USB port
in the
back
of the
computer
or
there's
some
other
little
creepy
crawling
that
is in
between
I bet
most people
don't
with
wireless
oh
with wireless
it's even worse
because the
wireless
keyboard
typically
use
encryption
but the
kind of
encryption
you use
is often
homegrown
by the
manufacturer
or really
crappy
and so
you don't
need to
put a
hardware
device
you can
just sniff
on it
externally
right
because
they use
some
kind of
either
infrared
or some
other
kind
of
wireless
so
beware
but
attacks
keylogger
especially
hardware ones
are not
common
they are
targeted
right
somebody
has to
target
a specific
computer
person
in order
to do
that
software
keyloggers
are different
that often
happens
with buggy
browsers
or buggy
it used
to happen
once in
a while
with microsoft
windows
where there
would be
some malware
that would
warm itself
and usually
again
with some
degree of
social engineering
preceding it
and then
will
install
itself
and actually
take over
the keyboard
driver
or worse
yet
update
the keyboard
driver
right
because
the keyboard
is a
peripheral
right
there's a
driver
for that
peripheral
to
insert an
illegitimate
fake update
of the
driver
that would
contain
a keylogger
not nice
and then
there are
like
lower tech
ways of
sniffing
on
keyboard
input
shoulder
surfing
everybody
familiar
with
shoulder
surfing
yeah
people are
getting
too close
to you
for comfort
you're entering
your pen
whether it's
on the
door
block
or
on your
bank
ATM
somebody's
like
breathing
down
your neck
that's
shoulder
surfing
I mean
easy to
avoid
but you have
to be
coming
center
right
but
shoulder
surfing
means that
human
eyes are
looking
at something
but it's not
always human
eyes
it could be
a tiny little
drone
it could be
a camera
from farther
away
with a
telephoto
lens
that is
shoulder
surfing
right
so
it could be
think about
it
you go
let's
say
take
example
of
the
ATM
anybody
ever
go
to
the
ATM
anymore
I think
I go
once
twice
a year
but
still
people
do
I can
see you
every time
I go
to the
ATM
there
are
people
so
you don't
trip
in
do you know
how many
cameras are
looking at
you
well
there's
a camera
in the
ATM
right
they usually
have
a camera
but what
about
other
cameras
on the
street
do you
know
if
they have
the
right
angle
maybe
they
do
maybe
there's
something
right
above
you
that's
looking
directly
at
the
ATM
keypad
no
there are
thermal
cameras
that's
something
also
fairly
scary
thermal
cameras
what does
that mean
it means
when you
type
your
password
or
pin
on
some
surface
like
keyboard
or
pin
tab
what
happens
is
your
fingers
touch
the
surface
you
are
human
last
time
you
checked
were
human
last
time
you
checked
were
alive
which
means
as a
live
human
you have
a certain
temperature
on your
body
and your
fingers
reflect that
temperature
and when
your
live
human
fingers
touch
the
dead
plastic
cold
this
what
happens
heat
transfer
even
if
you
go
boom
well
that's
the force
right
that generates
heat
cut off
mainly
the
skin
so
if
you
type
in
your
pin
or
your
password
and
then
somebody
snaps
a
photo
keyboard
they
will
see
heat
map
they
will
see
the
keys
that
won't
press
most
recently
they
might
not
directly
leak
pin
or
password
information
but
it
leaks
a lot
information
that's
about
in
particular
which
keys
were
pressed
recently
maybe
not
exactly
the
sequence
but
how many
combinations
that
are
right
so
something to worry about
then there is something called acoustic emanation
there's a whole body of research literature on this
starting in like 25 years ago
people realize
that when you type on any surface
be it a keyboard
or a
thing
even on the phone
on the
on screen keyboard
there are sounds that are being named
and sound propagates
right
when you type
especially in some of those
people like me
etc
aggressive
times
sound propagates
farther
than the human ears
right
so if you put a very sensitive microphone
you know
ten yards away
people still pick up
keyboard emanations
isn't that scary
I think it's very cool
I have a lot of research on this
still these days
there are people who work at it
but
the sound
that your
fingers make
when you type in
anything
not just the classroom
is unique
not because
so much
that you make it
but the keyboard
itself
produces a different sound
for any different key
every key
on your plastic keyboard
makes a different sound
the same
to a lesser extent
old story about the keyboard
you have
but every time you press a key
the sound that it makes
when you press a Z
is different from the sound
that it makes you
when you press a D
or slash
or a question mark
or space
okay
there are different sounds
and so
if I record those sounds
I essentially can key log
without installing a key log
isn't that fun
but it gets worse
much worse
even if the manufacturers
and some made an effort
some didn't
to make all the keyboard
sounds sound the same
it's possible
it makes people
more expensive
there's still a problem
does anybody see the problem?
yourself as a person
what about yourself?
I mean
some people
have just
and they find
and they just
make themselves
because of the finger
and
uh-huh
yeah
so remember
it's true
that
what I said before
is that there's you
who types differently
depending on which key you type
and then there's the actual keyboard
that makes different sounds
so even if you press
the same way
on the same
like
you have this finger
like you're one of those
hunter tech
people like me
like
you move the keyboard
hit
move the keyboard
hit it
so you see
my angle doesn't change
so I hit the same way
right
but the keyboard sound
is different
but
manufacturers suppose
now fix the keyboard
that all the sounds
are the same
but I haven't changed
right
so
when I use my
this finger
that goes straight down
on this one letter
it sounds one way
when I have to angle my finger
to press shift
right
or press question mark
it sounds differently
not because of the keyboard
but because of the way
I angle my fingers
and the force I apply
correct
but it gets worse than that
that
so
you can indeed
still mine the information
like I said
about the individual
humans typing
characteristics
but
it's harder
it's easier to extract
from the manufacturer
introduced
distinction
though
the problem is
what did you say
time
like time between keys
time between keys
that's the problem
turns out
on a standard
QWERTY keyboard
let's assume
that we're using
QWERTYs
right
which is an American
keyboard
as you move
from key to key
right
from let's say
typing key
to typing H
to typing E
to typing N
to typing X
to typing E
right
you type one letter
at a time
even if you are
touch typist
you type one letter
at a time
well
the intervals
the timing intervals
between successive letters
are unique to you
also
and the keyboard
they sound like
that's right
they're slightly different
yeah
but
that's right
they sound
that's true
but that's actually
related more
to what he said
but just
the sheer timings
between the keystrokes
so you don't have
to have any idea
but
guess what
there are
let's say
forget the
exclamation points
forget those
special characters
let's suppose
there are
I don't know
26 keys
on the keyboard
and you're just
typing words
right
so how many
possible
two word
combinations
are there
two letter
combinations
are there
26 times 26
right
so after a while
if you
record
the sounds
of somebody
typing
a lot of text
right
over the day
or two days
or whatever
you're going to
start distinguishing
between transitions
between keys
right
believe me
it's totally doable
because
assuming
somebody
is typing
English text
right
like writing
email messages
or filling out
forms
well
the probability
of occurrence
of two successive
letters
are quite distinct
and essentially
becomes
a simple
decision
so anyway
that was a little
detour
but what about
good vibrations
well good vibrations
refers to another
thing that
actually
if you're using
your phone
and that has
been some
published research
on this
and your phone
is like this
on your
desk
or whatever
in front of you
right
and
as you press
every
on-screen
button
right
on-screen keyboard
your phone
makes like a tiny
vibration sound
like a moment
that the other
phone do
right
just to confirm
that you actually
type
well
those vibrations
when you put a
microphone
underneath your
desk
they can actually
calculate your
typing
other analysis
include taking
photos of
smartphone screens
and looking for
quadrants
little areas
on your screen
that are
most
like smudged
that
leaks information
about your
password
or the
unlock pattern
you know
this
like
anybody use
unlock patterns
like five years
ago
everybody in this
class
was like
yes
I guess
they are
faster now
but apparently
you know
if your human
fingers leave
like oil
residue
on the screen
and so
if you take
a high resolution
photo of
somebody's
smartphone screen
you've got to
figure out
what the
unlock pattern
is
yeah
so all this
is good stuff
but the problem
is of course
like that
the passwords
right
why do I
talk about
all this
previous stuff
because that
would be
not only just
a way of
snoop on
what you're
doing
but of course
to snoop on
your passwords
right
that's the way
to actually
and sort of
learn your
password
the worst
thing we can
do is write
them down
because then
writing them
down
whether it's
on a device
or a piece
of paper
that becomes
a way to
like cause
denial of
service
etc
we can
pick passwords
that are
easy to
remember
some places
don't even
have passwords
I've seen
a few
systems
websites
which
completely
have no
passwords
but instead
have these
special
questions
like
they give
you five
special
questions
every time
you want to
log in
you have to
answer four
out of five
friends
but they all
tend to be
of this
variety
what's your
favorite pet's
name
rover
bio
jerry
and they
give you
some of
them are
worse
than others
some of
them allow
you free
text entry
which is
better
and some
of them
give you
a choice
like
out of
these five
pet names
which one
is your
favorite
really
seriously
terrible
easily
guessable
alright
I think
we should
be
done
for today
yeah
I'll
forget
this
candle
to me
ok
let's be
done
for today
see you
next
Tuesday
come
out