I don't want to share your screen before you have the flag.
Oh, I don't know what this is.
Okay, so we went through face recognition, I think, right, on fingerprints, fingerprints of issues.
We'll talk about a couple of examples where fingerprints fail.
If you know anybody who works in the medical profession, especially surgeons,
there were only attempts to install fingerprint recognition in hospitals that failed miserably
because surgeons, if you know any, wash their hands extremely frequently for good reasons,
and their fingers tend to be, you know, like when you keep your fingers in water for an hour,
they wrinkle, the fingertips wrinkle.
So, totally not good for fingerprint recognition.
Not to mention all the other stuff.
Iris scans. Iris scans are a relatively accurate way of biometric authentication.
No two irises are the same.
It's random.
Knowing anything about a person, even knowing a person's DNA, you cannot recreate the irises.
Stable.
As you grow, as you get old, they remain the same.
Even with cataracts or some other issues.
Now, if you gouge out an eye, there's no more iris.
You have an injury, obviously, but that's rare, right?
Works in with the blind people.
That's because they're still in irises.
They're different.
If you wonder, they're different for both of your eyes.
There's like a set of concentric rings.
So, it's actually not too different from the fingerprints.
There's, except the fingerprints are not exactly rings, right?
They're more like parabolas or something like that.
So, error rates are pretty low.
It's not the best, but I think it's one of the best biometric applications you think is currently known.
It is expensive, right?
To get accurate iris scans, you have to be very close to the device that's going to scan the iris.
There has to be stable lighting.
It's not instantaneous.
It takes a couple of seconds.
Not quite light because people generally do not like sticking their eyes and their faces into things.
The early ones had like a kind of a mask almost like the device where you have to stick your eyes.
Or something a little more evil looking where you're like goggles where you stick your eyes and go bzzzzz and scan your irises.
It can be done on a smartphone.
I believe there are apps that will do it for you.
I checked a year ago.
There were a couple of apps.
At least on Android.
I'm not sure about iPhone.
There are apps you can download that will essentially use your camera to do an iris scan.
Not as precise.
Slower.
Other methods.
Hand geometry.
So hand geometry is in this.
Your hand print.
All these things that fortune tellers like to use.
Right?
Life line, love line, death line, whatever.
Sickness line.
All these lines.
The geometry of your hand.
Not just the relative things but also the size of your fingers.
What we call phalanges are.
Now calluses won't matter because they're generally okay.
If you have severe cuts or injuries clearly it wouldn't work very well.
But hand geometry.
Relatively stable.
Of course as you grow, as a child grows, the hand gets larger.
But the actual lines remain.
But the size of course changes.
Let's see if you have some hand conditions like eczema also doesn't work well.
It has been used in nuclear premise control like for entering say national labs, nuclear
reactors, that kind of thing, nuclear plants.
You would just place your hand on a tablet.
And it would be like a surface that will do a scan.
Kind of like you do a document scan.
This continued because it was expensive.
And at the time did not really check for liveness.
Now this may sound a little morbid.
But liveness is important.
Okay.
Ear shape.
Also.
Ear scan.
Can you imagine?
It has some of the same issues as iris can.
Ears are not something you'd like to stick in places.
Right?
There in our head, next to our brain.
But it has been used.
At the bottom of the ICS2 building, the red building next to Brent Hall, across the ring,
there was a lab which is called K-some-day lab downstairs.
I think it's still there.
I don't know what it has.
It's useful.
But for many years, not anymore, it had a biometric scanner at the door.
And it was vein patterns.
So you would just place your wrist on the scanner.
Not your hand.
Your wrist.
You would scan the veins.
That's another method.
A little better than irises.
Generally better than hand because you don't get calluses here.
You don't get eczema here.
It's usually a little more stable.
One other thing.
Voice prints.
How many of you have ever seen voice prints?
My sibling company, I think one of my banks uses voice prints.
When I call them, they're like, would you answer these questions for us?
But they're not really looking for the answers.
They're looking for my voice.
And the questions actually aren't the same every time.
So it's kind of a challenge response, if you will, kind of voice prints.
Now to enroll, at some point, they have to ask me to stay on the phone and enroll.
Okay.
Yes?
Would the phone be using matter a lot for the voice prints?
Speech processing has seen very important advances in the last ten years.
So they can pretty much filter the noise.
Ambient noise.
They can filter ambient noise.
I mean, if somebody's screaming down your ear at the same time, they can filter out the road noise,
classroom noise, that kind of thing.
The artifacts of a metallic voice on the phone, sort of that.
I think there may be some issues.
It's not super robust.
I would not use it myself.
Because voice-based authentication is, well, fundamentally very fragile.
Okay?
And easily, it turns out, there have been studies that show that it's fakeable.
Okay.
DNA.
Yes, DNA.
So I used to have this slide.
I don't know why I removed it.
But it was sort of, you can imagine, it showed iPhone 55.
In 2039, Apple comes out with iPhone 55.
And it has this feature called Lipton Lock.
Immediately sequence your saliva and DNA and says, ah, it's you, I'm unlocking myself.
I've used it in a few talks.
And people actually, some people come up to me and just say, really?
Really?
I couldn't do that.
No, I didn't mean.
Now, I don't think that's coming to the store here, you, anytime soon.
But, in principle, DNA can be used for identification because, for identification, excuse me.
Because it is unique to you.
There's no probability of match.
They say, you know, if there is, it's so astronomical, it's not even worth mentioning.
Now, the problem is, DNA is like fingerprints.
If you leave them at the scene of a crime, right, that's one thing.
But how do you test the liveness, right?
So, in order to test the liveness, you have to make sure it comes from a live person right now.
And that's a problem.
Also, if you're wondering, well, can you sequence DNA?
Well, today, it takes minutes.
Even in a faster hardware.
So, your smartphone can do a sequencing.
There are attachments to the smartphone.
You can buy today a peripheral.
That will cost you probably more than the phone.
But it plugs into your phone.
And, I forget, it's not actually licking it, but you can insert like a sample of saliva or something like that.
It will sequence and digitize your genome on your phone, right?
It can be done, but it's okay.
And, okay, keystroke dynamics.
So, keystroke dynamics are, remember we talked about how attacking keyboards, right, listening to these?
Well, remember about keystrokes, right?
The way you type is fairly unique.
Unless you are particularly like, I don't know, tired or injured or somehow sick.
You know, you generally type in the same way.
So, imagine the system and it has, it is being deployed.
It is deployed in many industrial and government organizations, usually larger organizations,
where you enroll by essentially typing stuff, maybe for training the model for a few days.
Then sort of a profile is created, right?
Features are extracted.
Machine learning, obviously, is used to extract the features from your typing model.
And that becomes your biometric keystroke profile.
What is the idea?
The idea is that you don't come to the building and start typing for a few minutes on a keyboard in order for the door to open.
That's not what this biometric is for.
It's really for monitoring dynamically whether you are the same person who authenticated to begin with.
So, the idea is you came to work, okay, typical scenario, you came to work, you logged into your terminal, desktop, whatever, okay?
And then you walked away.
Never happens to you?
Please tell me it does, because I know it happens.
Right?
You log in and you walk away.
Now, at home, maybe your cat will walk on the keyboard.
Or your roommate will, you know, type an obscene message, because they prank you or something like that.
But, at work, there could be an insider colleague who may not be so humorous, may actually want to cause harm.
Right?
So, they will come and start typing, but they cannot replicate your typing pattern.
So, the idea is that the system will recognize, oh, that's not the same person who was here before.
So, that's the form of biometric.
The best biometric, hands down, that I've ever seen in my life, was done by IBM.
And it was done actually as early as, like, late 80s or early 90s.
And I believe it still exists.
Like, just two years ago, it still existed.
It was extremely expensive.
But it was based on writing.
Not typing, writing.
The idea was very simple.
You have a pad, right?
Dedicated like a hardware device.
It's like a pad.
You write on.
Kind of like the one, you know, when you sign your signature in a grocery store, when you
buy something, you know, and ask it to sign here.
But nobody cares what you actually sign.
You can just, like, put a dot there and nobody verifies.
Well, but imagine something much more sophisticated, which is the size of a laptop screen.
But it's, like, horizontal.
You come to it, it has a stylus, right?
Everybody knows what a stylus is.
And it says, write something.
Right?
It challenges you to write, like, a sentence.
Today I went to work.
So you write the sentence using your handwriting.
Remember handwriting?
It's still a thing.
Right?
And what it does, it's not just measuring the shape of the legs.
Because if you just do that, that's easily spoolable.
Right?
It's just the shape of the letters because I can probably, I'm pretty decent in calligraphy.
I can probably imitate your writing style.
If I see how you write, I will write a sentence, but it's not a sentence.
But what I'm really going to do is, you know, I will write a sentence.
Today I went to work.
So you write the sentence using your handwriting, remember handwriting, still a thing.
Right?
And what it does, is not just measuring the shape of the legs.
And so many people are able to do this, algorithms are even better at this, right?
In fact, algorithms are better than people today, so if you can train an algorithm on somebody's writing style,
give them a few scanned, you know, letters, handwritten letters, et cetera, notes,
it will generate excellent quality fakes.
So shape is important, but it's not negligible, but it's not what's being used.
What is being used to other things? Pressure, you put on the stylus,
because when you write with a pen or pencil or anything that is a writing implement,
you're putting a certain amount of pressure.
And that pressure varies depending on what it is you're writing.
As you're circling the letter O, you're putting a different pressure than when you're completing the letter R.
Okay, that turns out to be unique for you.
The other thing that is unique to you is acceleration.
The acceleration of the stylus as you write those letters is very important and it is unique.
The combination of shape, acceleration, and pressure are a winning combination that makes this an amazing biometric technology,
but it is incredibly expensive.
So how would you attack it?
Well, shapes can be attacked, as I just told you, right?
You can train an algorithm to generate shapes the same as anybody is.
Acceleration might be, might be attackable if you carefully and very precisely film somebody, right?
Film somebody, write it.
Because you can measure the speed, right?
If you have a camera, like a hidden camera place somewhere,
and it's recording how somebody is writing, you will know the acceleration.
And you might be able to design, not a human,
you might be able to train a robot to do this.
But what you cannot replicate is at least the pressure because that's not something you can film.
So the only way to attack a system like that is to actually get the user to use a fake entry device.
To present the user with a tablet that is fake and record both pressure and acceleration over time,
then maybe.
But the barrier to this attack is high.
Now.
My question would be, is handwriting considered stable enough though?
Because a lot of people, like, even on a day-to-day basis, if you're angry, you write more aggressive.
Exactly, exactly.
Yes.
Handwriting, generally there is some stability.
The way you're shaped.
You might shape your A's differently, but there's a finite shape of A that you use when you're angry,
when you're relaxed, etc.
Okay?
So your jerkiness, right, might be different, right?
Sometimes you write smoothly, slowly, and sometimes you write quickly because you're under pressure.
But generally the shapes stay more or less the same.
But again, shape is just one.
The pressure and the acceleration.
You might fail.
I mean, I don't know actually, to be fair, what is the insult rate of this.
But I know it has been used specifically in insurance companies and banks.
So when they came up with it, they had this huge number of customers, all these big banks.
And they wanted to make sure that all the, you know, high level officers of the banks and insurance companies were authenticated using that.
Because they dealt with, obviously, a lot of money.
Would it be stable over time though?
They claim it was.
I've used it myself.
It seemed very natural.
Not very burdensome.
I mean, again, not something you want to use instead of badges, right?
But it's something you want to use if somebody wants to access a highly secure facility.
Or there's a terminal, right?
You want to log in instead of typing username and password.
Just do this.
That's reasonable.
If you're interested, there's an article about that.
Okay, so there are a couple of biometrics that we've played around here at UCI in my research group.
And one of them, well, one of them is not on the slides because it's just too hilarious.
It's called, so I won't bother you with showing you anything because you could probably imagine the picture.
It's called ascentication.
Basically, the idea is to instrument a chair, an office chair, with pressure sensors.
And if you think it's a joke, it's not.
There was actually a paper published about it.
And it was part of a student's PhD thesis.
So imagine an office chair.
Not this crap you're sitting on.
This looks like kindergarten or old folks home or something.
I don't know if it came up with this stuff.
But like a regular nice comfy office chair with a cushion, right, or something.
So underneath, in the cushion, there are pressure sensors.
Now geometrically, you kind of like arrange around where a person would sit.
And if you're wanting to know, it is not measuring your ass size.
And it's actually not even measuring your weight.
Well, it just measures pressure distribution.
Because most people tend to sit the same way.
So the idea was the same as keystrokes.
So when a person sits down and logs in, the system takes measurements of their pressure points, right?
Or they sit in the chair and creates a profile.
And so when a person walks away to get a coffee or use the bathroom or go to a meeting and forgets to log out,
and somebody else sits in the chair, well, their thought is going to be different.
It's just different, right?
Trust me.
We've done experiments.
And people enjoyed those.
Generally.
And so the only way to subvert that biometric was essentially to create a very careful fake butt with just the right distribution of pressure.
Quite a high barrier of pressure.
The other method we experimented here is this.
And that also is a little strange, but it was pretty effective.
It is electricity and human body impedance or resistance, right?
So as you're familiar with static electricity, right?
You're familiar with maybe lamps that you have to touch in order to turn them on.
So you've seen those?
Yeah?
Well, they work kind of the same.
So essentially you're closing a circuit, right?
When you're touching a lamp like that.
So the idea here is to essentially measure human body's conductivity, right?
By sending an electric pulse from one hand and measuring that same electric pulse in the other hand.
Now clearly not, you know, we don't want to electrocute anybody.
That would be one and only way to measure, right?
And that's it.
No.
Sending a very weak electric signal, one volt.
That's the idea.
Okay?
And so one volt signal, maximum current, 0.1 milliampere, exposure about 100 nanoseconds.
Now this is opposed to, say, a regular battery.
You know if you lick a battery?
You know if you lick the battery as a kid?
I know a lot of kids did.
I did.
You know the ones with two terminals?
You get the sour taste?
Well, you know, you actually get electricity to pass through.
But it's much higher than what we would do.
So humans don't feel this amount of electricity.
And we had to, of course, obtain authorizations because the university would not allow us to do something that's dangerous.
So we had an authorization for this.
And the idea was, what was the use case?
The use case, suppose you have an ATM machine, right?
And you want to have your own money.
So you enter, today you have a metallic pin pad, right?
On the ATM machines.
And then imagine, in addition to that, you had a little metallic surface, right?
Like some kind of circle.
When you put one hand here and you type with the other hand, your pin.
You don't need two hands to type a pin, right?
Most people do not use two hands.
Pin is one hand.
So while you're typing the pin, it's sending this signal and measures your body connectivity.
That's one scenario.
The other scenario is just a metallic keyboard, right?
So today, most consumer keyboards, cheap ones, right?
Are plastic.
They have the other issue.
We might talk about something at some point.
But there are some more expensive, more fancy keyboards that are metallic.
Okay?
And if you're typing on a metallic keyboard, while you're typing, you can send this.
Especially if you're not a, like, you're a hundred-pack type.
So this is more.
Right?
So that's the idea, continuous authentication.
Yeah, so we actually had a setup with a scope, a oscilloscope, waveform generator.
And you see these brass handles.
Big brass handles.
So the idea was that the human would sit.
The participant in our study would sit there and we would vary a little bit like the timing
and send this very weak signal and measure the response in the other hand.
And it actually turned out, we didn't have a lot of people, but we had 30 subjects for snapshot measurements
and 16 for long-term measurements, just stability.
As you can imagine, unfortunately, the male to female ratio is difficult in computer science
or in this part of campus.
So they weren't, it wasn't always very well split.
But there was no difference between male and female subjects.
The snapshot data sample basically misidentification was very low.
So most of the, most of the measurements were quite encouraging.
Well, it didn't work as well as over time.
It was measured over days or weeks.
The accuracy went down.
And one of the reasons it does is that if you are dehydrated, right, as opposed to well hydrated,
the connectivity changes a little bit.
If you drink alcohol, which by the way also dehydrates you, but if you're just buying things alcohol,
that also changes.
Not that we didn't measure people after going to alcohol or anything like that, but we noticed that alcohol does change it.
And, but otherwise, it doesn't matter what mood you're in, how much sleep you got, their connectivity stays the same.
Yeah, so the only way to subvert it, yes, there is a way to subvert it, but it's not easy.
What you have to do is measure the victim's false response yourself, right, get the measurement from them,
and then strap essentially a contraption like this that provides exactly the same impedance or resistance,
and then use kind of like insulated gloves.
So then you might be able to pull this by metric.
Alright, so what are risks?
Of course, there are a lot of risks of using biometrics.
If you're using fingerprints in a wrong way, like for example, this was a trick that was quite common before,
it has nothing to do with digitization.
It was in the analog gaze that if a criminal managed to distract a law enforcement officer
and give the fingerprints in the wrong order, that they essentially will not be identified.
Okay?
Today, it's impossible to do that because every finger is identifiable as where it is, its location on your hand.
So it's not possible to do that.
Voice prints are easy to attack with recordings and also with advanced machine learning techniques
and bots that can generate based on training data.
If I record enough of your voice, you talk enough in class, I record enough of your voice,
I will be able to generate pretty accurate on-demand utterances by you.
So, if you wind up in the real world working with biometrics or choosing what kind of biometrics to use for your company,
stay the hell away from voice, okay?
Or anything audio.
Terrible.
Then there is the grainings fingers in a jar.
This was actually a case, at least not in this country, in the UK, where the pensioners, right?
They retired people were paid social security based on physical prints.
They had to authenticate using a fingerprint.
And so, you know, there was this case, I'm sure you can still find it, like 2003, where the grandma was dead for like five years,
but the family used the finger in the jar of Vaseline they preserved, you know, to essentially obtain payments every month.
Let's see.
Now, there is also the false negatives that accept rates of one in a million, and this was back like 20 years ago,
that there would be one in a million error, which means that if you know anything about the,
everybody here knows the birthday paradox.
Yes?
Okay.
The birthday paradox goes like this.
How many people does it take, at random, for them to have at least two, well, how many people should we select off the street, at random,
in order to have at least 50% probability of at least two of them having the same birth?
And the answer is, what do you think?
For like 6-0 million.
Well, no, that's for a million.
No, no, no.
No, no.
Hang on.
Just listen to my words.
People and birthdays.
Maybe birthdays?
You're close.
So most people will say, well, you know, if you want to make sure you have to have, like,
the easiest answer is, oh, I've got 365 people, right?
And then you'll have a duplicate, right?
That's, of course, guaranteed.
But what if you pick, I don't know, 180 people?
Will there be, what will be the chance?
It turns out it takes 23 people.
23, or square root, roughly square root of 365.
So if you have a million acceptance rate of one in a million, that means with only a square root of a million, like a 1609 or so, you get a 50% probability of a mismatch in a fingerprint.
Then there's Play-Doh fingers, right?
Where people, because you see the fingerprints are liftable, right?
You leave a fingerprint, right?
And once I get your fingerprint, or I lift your fingerprint, I'd say, right?
Exactly how the police does it, right?
I can build a 3D object with that fingerprint on it.
And so think about Play-Doh.
Play-Doh has this nice characteristic, right?
That it's malleable, and it's soft, right?
That if you imagine you impress the fingerprint that you lifted onto a Play-Doh, it will look just like a fingertip.
Also, it's easy to warm up Play-Doh, right?
So if the fingerprint reader takes temperature, just to make sure it's a live, warm finger, not a cold, dead finger, it's also easy to do with Play-Doh.
And there were stories about this.
And so there was a study in the 90s, I think, at this Clarkson University of New York event, how you can make it.
And they actually succeeded in pulling some, at the time, fingerprint authentication systems.
And what they suggested is they should do like a perspiration test, because even if you think your fingertips are dry, actually they're not completely dry.
There's like some kind of moisture there.
But it's also easy.
So fingerprints are yesterday's news, right?
Then there was this case also like 20-something years ago when Mercedes, high-end Mercedes, started using the fingerprints to unlock cars, right?
There are still some cars out there that use them, by the way.
Maybe you've seen them.
So, yeah, some business consumer was cut off just to steal his Mercedes.
Handwriting.
Again, I mentioned this earlier, but you can use, you can trade, this was already 20 years ago, you could trade a machine learning model to generate very believable looking,
or very, very authentic looking duplicates or fakes of somebody's handwriting.
And stare at it as all you want is very difficult to recognize without me showing you this, which one is, you know, without labels, which one is fake.
So, in summary, biometrics are, can be helpful, they are nice because they put no load on you generally, on us humans.
You sit in a chair, you sit anyway.
You put a fingerprint and what's the load, right?
Even with iris scans, typing on a keyboard to type anyway, right?
So, if you're being authenticated as you type, that's no longer new.
But, they're tricky to use on a large scale.
They require in-person enrollment.
In order to have secure enrollment, and you will see this if you haven't yet, when you work in the real world and you have a biometric system that is in place,
you will be required to have an in-person enrollment, even if you are a remote worker.
So, they are hard to re-block.
And they require this pervasive infrastructure, right?
So, if you're using iris scans, they have to be iris cameras everywhere you want to protect.
Every computer, every secure office, everything has to be protected with that equipment.
So, let's see.
So, biometrics are about what you are, inherently what you are, but now, remember, the other factor is what you have, right?
What you have.
So, what you know, what you are, and now what you have.
So, imagine you have something like a dongle of some sort, right?
You know, something like a little tag, a phone, some object, right?
So, it's not part of your body anymore, and it's not inside your brain.
It's rather an object that you have in your possession.
So, now, imagine that you, user, and the system share a secret.
Now, not password, not password, okay?
Long, strong secret, okay?
So, very simple.
You want to log in, the system says, here's a challenge.
It generates a random, unpredictable challenge, and tells it, prove to me that based on this challenge, you know the secret.
That you and I share.
And you reply, with some function, cryptographic, obviously, of the key that you have, and the challenge that was just sent to you.
The system verifies, right?
Because it can recompute the same function.
It knows the challenge, it sent it, it knows the key, it shares it with you, compares the two values, success or failure.
This is strictly better, right?
If someone eavesdrops on this communication, what can they do?
Good force, right?
Same as put password, except with password, the adversary was in luck.
The passwords came from a very small, pathetic space.
But here, the key comes from a truly random space, right?
So, if the key is 160 bits long or 256 bits long, good luck to the adversary doing brute force.
Not possible, not viable, right?
Now, that's a big question.
If we could get the user to compute the f, that would be nice, but the users aren't good at computing functions, right?
So, it has to be done by something else.
Okay?
By some other object.
So, this is what's called challenge and response certification.
And here, like I said, user and system share a key, right?
Challenge, response.
The idea is, the key stays secret because it's random, strong, and nobody leaks it, right?
And the adversary only sees that function of the key and the random challenge.
And it's fresh.
Fresh means, if a challenge is short, let's say we were stupid, or we didn't take a security course,
and we said, let's make challenge 16 bits.
What happened?
Remember, challenge is random.
What will happen over time?
In fact, we will see every challenge and we will answer everything.
Uh-huh.
But it's worse than that.
The birthday.
It's worse than that.
Right?
The adversary will see, will record all the challenges and responses, and will just wait
for a repeat.
And when the repeat comes, or the adversary will record enough challenge responses that
when it wants to impersonate the user, user isn't there, but the adversary wants to log
in as the user.
The adversary will say, log in, and the system will say, there's a challenge.
The adversary quickly looks at a database of challenges that recorded, says, do I have it?
No.
Okay.
Abandoned login.
A little time later, not right away, because that will arise.
There's no suspicion.
The adversary will wait.
They're patient.
Another login.
The system generates another challenge.
The adversary looks in this table of reported challenges and responses.
Oh.
Got it.
He can respond.
Does that make sense?
With a sufficiently long challenge, like 160 bits, 256 bits, the probability of challenge
repeating, astronomically small.
Okay?
So the challenges need to be long enough.
Indeed, the birthday paradox tells us, right, that they should be, today, you want to have
at least 160 bits of challenge for decent security.
So, which means that the system needs to be assured that when the response comes back,
it is fresh.
Right?
Because the user here isn't going to remember if they have seen the challenge before or not.
This is just the user.
Maybe with some dumb device or token of some sort.
It's not going to remember or cache all the previous challenges and say, ooh, I've seen
this one before.
I'm not answering it.
No.
It is the system's responsibility to make sure the challenges don't repeat.
Because it, when it receives back the reply, it wants to make sure, the guarantee that
this reply is here and now.
Not from yesterday or a year ago.
Okay.
So this works.
And you probably use this kind of system without even knowing it.
It's used in badge-based identification.
So, you know, people use badges ever?
Here?
Anybody work in the real world?
Yay.
Okay.
Badges?
NFC?
Yeah?
Or insert badges?
TAC.
NFC.
Okay.
A lot of those systems use this kind of challenge response.
Cars.
Key fob.
Car.
Challenge.
Key fob is the user.
You are the user with the key fob.
Key fob has the key.
Car.
You want to unlock the car.
You press.
The car goes, challenge.
The fob goes, response.
The car says, oh, correct response, unlock.
Here's an example where these things don't work well.
So far everything seemed good.
This example dates back to a long time ago.
Back in the 1980s, before you were all born, there was a war.
There were many wars, but this war took a long time.
It was kind of a slow war in Africa between a country called Namibia, which still exists,
and a country called Angola, which still exists.
And so Angola was allied with the Soviets, with all these countries behind the Iron Curtain,
and Cuba.
So, essentially, Angola was aided by the Soviet Union, Cuba, and all the Eastern Bloc countries.
And not surprisingly, Namibia was aided, well, not directly by the United States, but by South Africa,
which at the time was a very different South Africa issue today.
It was an apartheid regime, very right-wing, very conservative, blah, blah, blah.
So I'm not here to teach you politics, but just to illustrate a problem.
So they've used, already then, challenge response-based authentication.
And this system is called Friend or Foe.
F-O-F, Friend or Foe.
This is how, like, planes identify each other in the air.
This is how ground stations know that it's their planes and not enemy planes flying overhead.
Okay?
So the idea here, these people were at war.
They used aircraft.
Right?
Aircraft.
Bombers, et cetera.
Cause damage.
So, you have a following situation.
South Africa, remember, was supporting Namibia, right?
In this war.
So South Africans would launch a bomber, this is a ground station, to bomb Angola.
The ground station is the system.
The bomber is the user, right?
In this picture, the analogy, right?
They share a long-term secret key K, unique to that bomber.
Right?
So for every such bomber, you know, the ground station knows a separate key.
Meanwhile, Angola launches a Cuban MiG.
MiG is back then a Soviet airplane.
A Soviet bomber.
Okay.
It's flying over Namibian.
Namibians detect a plane, a radar.
Right?
Radar.
Anybody knows?
See a blip.
You don't know what it is.
That's why you need this kind of identification.
Are you one of us, or are you one of them?
Friend or foe?
So he says, here's a challenge.
Whoever you are, you better answer, or I'll shoot.
Right?
Air defense.
This has to be done super fast, right?
What?
Normally, Cuban MiG would be like, uh, I got nothing.
So it would hope that it won't get shot down.
But now, Cuban MiG would take that challenge and quickly retransmit it to the ground station in Mangola.
You've been following me so far.
Which will then transmit it up to whatever plane is flying there.
Turns out, oh, South African bomber.
Well, when South African bomber receives a challenge, it is programmed to reply with a function of a challenge and a secret key.
Everybody here awake?
Following?
Nope.
No rocket science here.
Pun intended.
Response.
Some function of the key, right?
I use a different notation here, but some function of the key and the random number, right?
Which the ground station in Mangola quickly retransmits back to the MiG, which is, you can see where this is going, right?
The MiG transmits it back to the ground station, and the ground station says, yay, one of us.
One of us.
Perfect.
And drops the bomb.
Now, you don't have to feel sorry for Namibians or South Africans or whatever, but do you see the problem?
Right?
If you design this system, you'll be court-martialed, probably, right?
So how do we fix this?
Do you see the problem?
Right?
And the problem should be obvious, that there is a problem.
Well, how do we fix it?
Well, back then, well, actually, I'm not 100% sure.
I'm pretty sure they didn't have GPS.
Or the military equivalent of GPS.
Right?
If they had GPS, would it help?
Come on, exercise your noodles.
Maybe limit the response time, because it takes time to...
Right.
Okay.
Good.
That's one.
You could say, look, if there is a plane over here, right, it can be only, I don't know,
10 miles away or something like that.
Whatever.
However the height, whatever the height of the flying altitude of the airplane is, right?
Some miles.
10 miles.
Whatever.
You know what the round trip is for a 10-mile radius.
This is obviously more, right?
You see how many packages are?
Well, normally it should be challenge, response.
Now it's challenge, relay, challenge, response, relay.
So we have four extra transmissions.
One of them, or two of them potentially longer distance.
So timing is of value, isn't it?
But GPS makes it even easier.
All you need to do is to make sure that this American bomber includes in that function of the challenge, right,
that it replies with, its coordinates.
And then the station says, ah, ah, it's not here.
Whatever this replies comes from, it's not from a plane flying overhead.
It's a plane somewhere, or he knows exactly where he's flying.
Does that make sense?
Now, in reality, you probably want to use both.
You want to use the time and the geographic coordinates.
So, just by itself, this is a problem, right?
It's called a relay attack.
Right, so, let's forget the war and then look at it again as a general problem.
We have Alice and Bob, or user and system, they share a secret, and they want to authenticate each other and identify each other over a network.
They do not see each other physically, so they are far away.
How do they authenticate and identify each other, right?
So, that's the main problem.
The adversary here is not just eavesdropping.
I may refer to the adversary as eave, but that's not just the limits of the adversary.
The adversary can eavesdrop, delete messages, modify messages, retard messages, right?
Maybe slow them down.
It can, yeah, insert messages, right?
So, the adversary is pretty capable.
And, what you have seen, essentially, is an example of this attack.
Right?
Which is called, sometimes it's called man in the middle.
They'll probably come around to changing it to some general neutral form one day.
But, the way it's still in the books is MIT and we're man in the middle of that.
Here's the adversary is in the middle, right?
So, the idea is, again, Alice and Bob know the secret.
When Bob challenges Alice and says, hey, here's a random number.
Prove to me that you know the secret based on this random number.
Right?
And Alice replies with a function.
Now, here we use a hash, right?
Like a crypto hash.
That's an example of a function you would want to use.
Because it's non-invertible, right?
No collisions.
Remember these properties we talked about?
Right?
You want to have all the good, both types of collision resistance, right?
So, Alice replies and that's a correct reply.
There's nothing wrong with the reply.
Except the adversary can be in the middle and he can essentially impersonate Alice.
Okay?
Now, there's a subtlety here.
The subtlety is this.
The adversary does not actually learn the secret in this attack, right?
The adversary is just a relay, right?
He's sitting in the middle and he's basically handing messages from Bob to Alice and handing messages from Alice to Bob.
So, he could be like a hostile router, right?
Or like an access point, a malicious access point.
So, what does it gain?
Well, it gains only the fact that if the system is configured so that when authentication succeeds, Alice gets access to something immediately.
Right?
That becomes an attack.
However, if this is followed by encrypted communication using the key K, the adversary gains that.
Do you see that?
Because the adversary does not know the secret.
So, it's attack on authentication.
It's not an attack on secrecy.
Now, if the key itself, remember, I assume the key is a strong key, right?
A binary, sorry, bitwise is long enough, at least 160 bits or so, and not a dictionary, not a big from a dictionary like a password.
There is another way to do this.
And the other way to do this, and this is actually also used in practice for something called one-time password, OTP.
It's based on a data structure called the Lamport's hash.
Has anybody ever seen this before?
No?
Lamport's hash.
Basically, Lamport's hash is the following.
So, you start with the random value, generate the random number, and then you repeatedly hash that random number, like over and over and over and over and over and over.
Remember how we did encryption?
So, imagine you just hash it.
Take X, hash of X, hash of X, hash of X, et cetera, hash, hash, hash, hash, hash, hash.
How many times?
As long as you want.
That's a parameter.
Okay?
So, the idea is you do this and Bob, who will be modeled here as a system, knows what's called the root of the chain.
That is the last hash value.
Okay?
Alice is the one that computed the chain to begin with.
Started with some secret.
You see that secret in quotes?
Okay?
So, she started with some secret value, and she computed a repeated hash over that secret value, n times.
Then, she gave the result.
You see that Y over there in the green cloud?
She gave the result to Bob, and she also gave him the index n, which is, at that time, the length of the hash chain.
Why do we call it the chain?
Because they are linked, right?
Hash, hash, hash, hash, hash, hash, hash.
Okay?
So, in the beginning, Bob knows that Y is the root of Alice's chain, and n is the length of the chain.
In other words, the chain has n links in it.
So, the first time Alice wants to authenticate to Bob, okay, she says, hi, I'm Alice.
Don't show that message, because it's a clear text message, nothing in it.
And Bob challenges her with the current index, int, which, at the beginning, is n.
Okay?
And Alice replies with something that hashes into n.
So, you start with a secret, hash once.
Then you arrive at hash of secret, then you hash again.
Then you hash again, et cetera, et cetera.
And eventually, you wind up with this Y, which is hash n of secret.
Okay?
And this is why it's called the chain.
So, in the end, here, at the very end, there's this hash n minus 1 of secret.
Right?
We computed n minus 1 hashes, all of the same, repeatedly.
And so, the last link is a hash.
Right?
And it becomes this.
Well, consider this value, this value here.
This is what Alice will give Bob.
And the idea is, if Bob hashes this, he should get that.
But he knows this already.
So, Bob is thinking, okay, who could have given me this value?
Only Alice, because only Alice knows the input to the hash function.
Because only Alice computed the entire chain.
Right?
And because of the cryptographic properties of the hash function, it's not invertible.
So, nobody could have inverted the hash function.
Or found a collision, because that's supposed to be, right, computationally hard.
Ask questions.
Don't hesitate if you haven't seen this before, which I think none of you have.
Do you see how this works?
And then, what Bob does, this is called one-time authentication.
Because this same value, h n minus 1, cannot be reused.
So, once Alice released it here, in this message in the reply,
Bob has to adjust it in his index to n minus 1.
So, the next time to authenticate Alice, he expects, Bob will expect this.
Because when he hashes this, once hash, you should get that, right?
Some of you look very puzzled.
It's okay to ask questions.
Yeah?
I'm kind of wondering what happens when they get all the way back.
Ah, good question.
What happens when you deplete the change?
When you are...
Now, the truth is, you have to either budget on never depleting it completely,
and then manually resetting with a new change.
Manually mean offline, offline resetting.
Generating, Alice generates a brand new change.
Or, there are some clumsy techniques to use digital signatures to...
I won't bore you with it.
But there are...
That's the problem with this space here.
Now, so this...
The change has to be long enough that it lasts for like a lifetime.
So, let me give you an example.
You have a...
It's like a small IoT device you bought.
Like some kind of a...
I don't know, smart clock or something like that.
And it typically...
The lifetime is like, I don't know...
A year.
So, you can provision it with a hash chain that is good enough for...
I don't know...
One authentication every hour for a year.
So, that's 365 times 24.
That will be the length of your change.
Right?
And then you know you're not unlikely to be depleted.
Because you're not going to authenticate the device every hour.
Right?
So, it is a useful technique.
But it's...
And it has been used in...
In...
What's something called one-time passwords.
Right?
It is a useful technique.
But it has this limitation.
And eventually you will run out.
And in a way, it's a kind of a public key scheme.
And it is...
Why is it...
Why do I say that?
Because...
That root...
That y...
That Bob keeps...
Is like a public key.
For Alice.
And every link is like a one-time authentication.
Using...
Only Alice can come up with the next authentication.
Bob cannot impersonate Alice here.
Okay?
Well, this is an attack.
But you know what?
I'm not going to...
Oof.
We're out of time.
I'm not going to bother you with this attack.
There is...
So, there is...
Finally, in this lecture, there is one thing that you will see out in the real world.
And you may have seen it already.
In some...
In some ways, the dual that we use is kind of an example of this.
A weird example of this.
But...
Anybody ever seen this?
Use your security ID?
Yeah?
They've been very popular.
And they're still around.
They may not look like that.
That was maybe like five to ten years ago.
It's still...
Essentially like a...
Like a fog.
Right?
Think of it as a fog.
But...
It doesn't have NFC.
Or any communication at all.
There's no radio anything.
What it is, is just a little display.
And...
The idea is that every user...
Let's say you work for an organization.
Every Alice gets her own fog.
Okay?
And...
Inside the fog is a master key.
Well...
For that fog.
That it shares with the system.
With the central system.
Bob here.
And...
So...
At setup time.
In...
In the factory.
Or whatever.
This thing is produced.
It's seated with a key.
And Alice and Bob share a key.
Okay?
So Bob is like...
You know...
A security administrator.
There's a database of all these devices.
All these bobs.
For every user.
Etc.
So...
In the beginning...
They go by counters.
So...
There's a counter.
Usually based on time.
So...
The way that Alice authenticates to Bob.
Is not using challenges.
There's no actual challenge coming in.
Rather...
Alice just reads the current value.
That she sees displayed.
And enters it.
Kind of like we do with the dual.
When it challenges us with the code.
Right?
You may always use dual.
With the code.
I know.
Most of the time it's approved this.
And...
Soon it's gonna change.
You know.
It's gonna be code based.
There.
The OID.
As your best interest in mind.
So...
Soon you'll say goodbye to just approve.
Well that looks the best part.
I know.
But that's all.
The idea here is very similar to the code based dual.
So...
You just enter a code.
And that code...
You see the little bar next to the number one there?
Like...
It has a little...
Like a stack of bars.
And it tells you how close...
As the bars go down.
They disappear.
Like...
It has...
How close is the code to be changing.
So...
When these bars...
Right now...
It's like...
It shows what?
Five?
Five bars?
I think it starts with six.
And then it goes down, down, down.
Because there's a clock inside.
And eventually it will show you a new code.
Based on time.
Here I just use the counter for simplicity.
But in fact it's based on time.
So what are you proving, right?
When you enter this code?
Okay?
What is the code?
So the code is generated from the key.
From the master key that the device shares with the system.
And the current time.
Never mind.
I use the counter here.
But that counter is not really appropriate.
It's more like a clock.
And because the clocks are reasonably synchronized between this fob and the central system.
The central system will know what to expect from Alice at this time.
Right?
Because she knows exactly what the serial number of the fob registered through Alice.
And she knows what to expect.
Or...
Bob knows what to expect.
Now, the original RSA ID was a bit...
Well, it's aged, right?
It wouldn't be used today.
But, you know, it had only 64-bit key, 44-bit counter.
But the idea was that the six-digit value, like for us we do...
I mean, it's more burdensome than just clicking approve.
But it's not too bad, right?
Just copying six-digit numbers is not a huge amount of burden.
So, that was the idea.
It was kind of user-friendly.
Right?
And then, it's verified on this end.
Counter increases, right?
But basically, time it takes, right?
Which is not really counting.
It's time.
Et cetera, et cetera.
Right?
So, the counter is usually based on this sort of 60 seconds.
That's customizable.
You can make it from 15 seconds to several minutes.
Also, it deals with clock skews because clocks are not perfectly synchronized.
So, the system here will allow you to enter a code that it does not expect as long as it's
a code from like the previous epoch or maybe the future epoch because sometimes clocks run
too fast, too slow, so it has some tolerance.
Anyway, that's it.
Let's quickly...
I was hoping to cover more, but let's try at least another...
Oops.
Let's see.
Here we go.
Alright.
So, this type of thing is the last batch of slides that have to do with passwords,
and then we want a much bigger and better thing.
So, remember passwords.
Now, forget all these fobs, forget the biometrics, remember passwords.
This is kind of a research direction, an idea that has taken hold also partially in industry.
That's why I'm covering it here.
And it's about something called honey passwords.
Now, the only of you know the term decoy.
Right?
Decoy is a fake object that pretend to look normal like a real thing.
Actually, the word decoy comes from Dutch language, from Dutch language, where decoy means a cage.
This is what the duck hunters would use to put a cage over their head and go into the bogs
and swamps and try to hunt ducks without being noticed as humans.
So, that's where we didn't get that word.
And I see fake objects that make you look real.
It's also a long-term tool in security and intelligence and counter-intelligence.
In computer security, decoys are used quite a lot.
If you know anything about intrusion detection, in the real world, something called honeypots
are often used.
Honeypots are fake resources, like fake web servers, et cetera, fake databases, fake portals,
that are used to entrap adversaries.
Okay?
The military is not very good at doing this.
Banks often do it.
Some larger companies do it, too.
They set up these fake sites, fake resources to attract adversaries and to entrap them.
Sometimes we feed them false information, make them believe that they broke into a system
where they actually have it, to observe the adversaries in the wild, to record their behavior.
Okay?
So, honey tokens, honey accounts.
Honey accounts are basically fake accounts for users that don't exist.
Right?
And let's say that user never logs in, doesn't exist, but there's an account.
And so when somebody logs into that account, you know, it's like a tripwire, right?
You know that something bad happened, right?
Because if that account does not correspond to a real user, when a login to that account
occurs, you know you had a problem.
Right?
You had also decoy documents, or honey documents, that is like, you set up a web server and you
put some like a, or a Google Drive, or you put some sensitive company documents that are
completely fake.
And then you wait for any news of these documents leaking to the real world.
Right?
So that tells you somebody broke in, but what they are releasing to the real world is complete
chock.
Right.
So these kind of undervalued things, I mean, they're not used as much as they should be,
so the key question we're going to try to answer, what kind of decoys do we use for security
problems?
Like password breaches, compromise of device data, etc.
And how to use them in a sort of a principled way?
And more, a bigger question is really how to deal with powerful adversaries that will sooner
or later compromise our systems.
Right?
So, the particular topic here is passwords.
And this work is not my work, it's a work by, by a fairly well-known researchers.
One of them is Rivest.
The guy, Rivest is the R in RSA.
The other guy, Ari Jules, is a cryptocurrency, actually no, sorry, he's a professor Cornell
these days.
So, here's the good news and bad news.
The good news is when you give talks about passwords, there's always news.
Right?
So, for example, this type of news.
And I know this is dated, but I'm just too lazy to update it because there's always treasure
trove of stuff in the news.
In the last six months I've seen at least three or four, you know, giant password breaches.
Okay?
So this was a while ago, but nothing changed.
Password breaches occur all the time in enormous quantities.
The bad news is that it's all bad news, of course.
Now, remember we talked about how passwords are protected?
Hashing, right?
Hashing, shadow files, salt, yeah?
That is still how things are done today.
Now we have Alice, has a password, she logs in, it gets hashed, the system compares the
hash, salt and hash, and lets Alice in if she typed in the right password, and if she
doesn't.
Right?
So, that's how we do things.
Just recall.
Right?
So, the password is hashed, but we're not compared.
Okay.
Hashing and salting is good because the adversary, remember, cannot mount a completely offline attack.
It forces the adversary to first compromise a password file, which contains salted caches,
and then break it.
But, salts are not that long, and that means the adversary will eventually win.
It doesn't change anything.
Right?
You can harden this by slowing down encryption and using very expensive encryption functions,
but in the end, real passwords are weak.
Right?
That doesn't change anything.
Real passwords are weak.
So, the problem is, remember, the salts, you can have to make the salts sufficiently long,
but once the adversary breaks in, right, and learns the password file, the salts for every
user, they're in clear text.
So, they are no longer secret.
Before the adversary breaks in, they're secret, right?
That's why the adversary can't mount an offline attack.
But, once the adversary breaks in and copies the password file, he doesn't know the passwords,
but he learns all the salts.
Okay?
So, the problem, then, for the adversary is just dictionary attacking passwords.
Okay.
So, forget this.
Anyway, there are plenty of good password hacking tools.
There's all this stuff, even from the RockU database that I use today to create dictionaries
of plausible passwords.
Not important.
Right?
The problem is, no matter what you do, no matter what you do, no matter how big your
salt is, no matter what rules you enforce, like, you know, must be 8 characters, 12 characters,
at least one special character, one capital letter, one number, blah, blah, blah.
Those passwords are still weak.
Okay?
And you might as well assume that you can be cracked.
So, the point of the matter is, preventing adversary from learning passwords is a losing
battle.
Let's accept this as an axiom.
It's a losing battle.
We can't win.
Right?
And, basically, the adversary will get that copy of a password file.
Somehow.
Okay?
And, once he gets the copy of a password file, he might as well assume the passwords
are in the clear.
Because it's only the barrier is this high.
So, that's bad.
But, not all is lost.
What can we do if we cannot protect our passwords?
I say, at the very least, we can detect.
Right?
If you cannot prevent an attack, at least detect.
Because the biggest problem is not detecting an attack.
If you cannot detect an attack, the adversary will stealthily get in.
The adversary will slow, smart adversary, will not do anything grandiose or, like, anything
large, anything big, like, start exfiltrating terabytes of data.
Right?
Because most organizations, they have, like, routers and all kinds of other logging things.
Logging facilities where doing something at scale will, like, raise a flag.
Like, for example, if you have a router that says, all of a sudden, gee, there was a spike.
Suddenly, you know, the rate was, I don't know, 200 megabytes per hour in the middle of the night,
and then suddenly I see a gigabyte of data in packets passing through.
What's wrong?
Why is there a gigabyte of data?
Right?
That will raise an alarm.
Smart adversaries will not let that happen.
They will try to shake their traffic not to exceed the normal traffic.
Think smart, right?
At least, assume this, obviously, is at least as smart as you are.
So you will get this.
And now you can impersonate users.
Now, eh, given the time to stop, I'll try to improve.
I really wanted to finish this today, but we'll do it in the first 20 minutes, half an hour, all the next time.
See you Tuesday.