I'm Drew Zee, if you don't die, no excuses.
Now, let's share a quick show of hands.
Do you want me to post a few example problems?
Yeah.
From prior years?
Yes.
Let me ask this.
How many don't want them?
I'll throw it together, a few examples.
But I won't post solutions.
Because many of the type of exams I give in classes I teach
generally have more than one solution.
Rarely there's just one.
It's like for undergrad when I teach crypto,
there's just one solution.
It's a numeric answer.
But other than that, the type of questions you have,
that will require one, maximum two paragraph answers.
Okay?
Do not write me an essay.
Please.
Save yourself, save me.
Don't write an essay.
Okay?
Also, just as a rule,
there are no devices allowed in the essay.
The phones, calculators,
everything that you normally bring
has to be inside your backpack
or somewhere else away from you.
Okay?
No virtual reality AR type devices like this one.
No earphones.
No headphones.
Right?
None of that.
No smart devices whatsoever on your body
at the time of your exam.
Nice.
So your backpack, whatever stuff,
inside, next to you, under you, whatever.
No problem.
Okay?
You need to bring something to write with.
Pen?
Pencil?
Both?
Sure.
Okay?
I will give you paper.
I know.
It's old-fashioned.
It's 20th century.
You write it on paper.
Okay?
I will give you an exam sheet.
You will have some number of problems.
Not too large.
Not too small.
Same rules apply to the final type.
And you will have blank sheets of paper
that I will bring.
And I will give you a couple to start with.
If you need more, you'll come up.
Make some up.
You can write on one side or both sides.
I don't care.
The only thing I absolutely care
is that you do your best penmanship.
I am not here to decipher encrypted text.
It's not what I paid for.
That's beyond my call of duty.
So, if I can't read it,
I'll assume it's not decipherable
and it requires a deduction of points.
I mean, I don't want to be calling everybody in
and saying,
what did you mean here?
What is this encrypted word?
What is it in scrambled sentence?
Please, write legibly.
If you have to print,
use printed letters.
I don't care.
Just write legend.
Okay?
And if you erase,
make sure you erase well
because sometimes, you know,
when you erase something,
it's smudgy
and then you write on top of it
and then it's hard to read.
I'll give you more paper.
No problem.
Okay?
So, that's the exam
and it will cover everything we covered
including today.
I might ask you questions
about the background stuff
from that,
remember that lecture one background?
Why, like, not specific?
Like, not in big detail, right?
It's not relevant to what we covered.
Otherwise, so far,
I won't ask you, like,
how does elliptic curve DSA work?
So, I'll be reasonable
and you'll try to be reasonable.
Yeah?
Are we going to expect
to know, like,
the specific numbers
associated with different protocols?
What do you think?
I don't know.
I'm not happy.
No.
If I ask you something like,
okay, so how does,
let's say today's lecture
was more about IPsec.
So, I'll say,
how does IPsec parse headers?
You should know how it does it
but you don't need to know
the vertical numbers
and, you know,
this kind of thing.
That's minutia.
I don't care about that.
I do not hear.
You're not here to, like,
for growth learning
to memorize some boring numbers,
you know.
Okay, so, on the last episode
of 203,
we went for SSL-TLS
and I know you're probably
more confused than you were before
but you do know a bit more about it
than you knew before.
It is a complicated protocol.
Nobody learns SSL-TLS
in one lecture.
Okay?
It's an effort that took years
by a whole lot of people,
smart people, right, mostly.
people with degrees
and experience
and security experts
to put together this protocol
and to evolve.
So, don't expect to, like,
understand everything
in one lecture
or even two.
What I give you here
in almost every lecture
is essentially
an appetizer
and if you're interested
in the meal,
you go further
and do a dig on your own.
Okay?
So, you will know
just enough to be dangerous.
but it's not enough
to be any kind of an expert.
So, remember,
what the key things
about SSL
and SSL-TLS
is that they operate
at this thin sublayer
above transport.
They are primarily oriented
towards the web
or HTTP traffic
but not exclusively.
People use SSL-TLS
for other things.
But the biggest consumer
is the web traffic.
So, we covered
the handshake, right?
Remember
the handshake protocol?
Right?
That's the main
thing about CLS
is without the handshake
nothing else works.
The handshake protocol
is very important.
It is
a full handshake
meaning that
it requires
an initiator,
the client,
to send something first
usually not authenticated
because the first message
cannot be authenticated
if there's no prior
contact.
And then the server replies
also with usually
not authenticated message
saying,
here's my certificate
and then the server
already computes
a session ID
because remember
the client supplies
a random number
a nonce
in the first message
client hello
the server replies
with a certificate
and the server hello
and that contains
a nonce.
So, given the two nonces
and some other stuff
they have a session ID
so they can identify
this particular session
between this client
and this server.
Okay?
And recall that
99%
more than 99%
of the cases
client authentication
isn't done
in SSL TLS.
It can be done
but it isn't done
for reasons
that I already discussed.
Right?
And
most of the time
today
you will see
that most
key exchange
right?
Not
Key exchange
is done
using RSA
where the client
picks what's called
pre-master secret
encrypts it
using the server's
public key
all this is
after you check
the server certificate
right?
You don't do this
The client abandons
the protocol
if there's something
wrong with the
server certificate.
Do you remember that?
Yes?
So the idea
in security protocols
is you don't
do heavy work
before you do
light work.
So the light work
means you make sure
that the server name
in the certificate
matches the URL
the domain name
of the URL.
Otherwise
you're being phished
and attacked.
Okay?
You're being scammed.
So test the map.
Of course
it doesn't help you
if you mistyped the name.
If you went
wanted to go to
wellsbargo.com
and you typed
well guess what?
If somebody
if somebody
has a website
called wellsbargo.com
and registered it
and has a certificate
that's where you're
going to go
and SSL TLS
will not help you.
It doesn't sound
too good
does it?
That's called
that kind of attack
was called
type of squatting
where
adversaries
or sometimes
not even adversaries
are like
porn sites
or like
marketing sites
will set up
a domain name
that closely
resembles a
legitimate
well-known
domain name
hoping that
the users
will mistype
the name
and they will
land on their
site.
In the worst case
you will see
some questionable
content
or you know
a walking tub
will be advertised
to you
by Akron.
In the worst case
you'll be fished.
Okay?
Meaning that
they will present
to you something
that looks like
a wellsbargo page
and you'll
blindly
most people
type their
username
and password
and that's it.
Bye-bye.
And so
SSLTLS
won't help you
with this
but if you
click
let's say
on a bookmark
that you put
a long time ago
that says
wellsbargo.com
SSLTLS
will help you
because there's
no typos
right?
Right.
So most
common
in
TLS
before
version 1.3
remember
I told you
there's like
two real
versions
out there
today
there's
really
TLS 1.2
and 1.3
they probably
used
the most
there are
lower versions
older versions
still in use
but they're
being deprecated
so a lot
of web
servers
will simply
not accept
a conversation
and TLS
session
with a client
that does
not support
at least
1.2
TLS
now 1.2
and 1.3
differ
I already
alluded to
that
but my
discussion
last time
was focused
on 1.2
so in
1.3
unlike here
you can
no longer
use RSA
to encrypt
okay
in 1.3
you have to
basically use
signatures
and use
Diffie-Hellman
or something
similar to
Diffie-Hellman
for key exchange
you cannot use
RSA
for key exchange
right
we looked at
how key is
derived
right
because remember
there's
pre-master secret
then there's
like a
master secret
well
in TLS 1.3
I believe
there's no
pre-master secret
because actually
both sides
contribute to
the key
and compute
what's called
the master secret
because Diffie-Hellman
is symmetric
symmetric
meaning both sides
contribute equally
and then
using the master
secret
we derive
using
something called
the k-derivation
function
a set of
other keys
right
that we actually
use for
encryption
and authentication
during the
data transfer
okay
we looked at
this
and then
there was
a summary
right
we stopped
around here
no
this is a
summary
of
a
handshake
client
below
followed by
three messages
essentially put
together
server hello
server
certificate
change
server hello
down
then
client returns
to server
saying
okay
this is client
key exchange
message
right
so now
that message
can be secured
already
client finished
by the way
contains
in mac
of all
of everything
exchanged so far
computed
with a key
that they just
agree on
master secret
key
and the last
message in the
exchange
is server
goes to client
says confirming
that we selected
this
I mean this
wording is confusing
change
they're not changing
any cyphers
today
right
they already agreed
on what cyphers
they use
important one
is server
finished
that can also
contain
a mac
of all the
messages exchanged
from the
service
perspective
so if the
survey of the
client have
the same view
of messages
sent and received
that means
no one
has interfered
with the
protocol
not a single
bit has
changed
then they're
sure that
they're talking
to each other
and that
completes the
handshake
we talked
about this
talking about
this
there's some
options
yes
so the other
thing you can
do
is if
client and
server have
previously
established
SSL-TLS
connection
there is already
a session ID
remember there
was a session ID
derived
that identified
the SSL-TLS
connection
the client
can resume
the connection
yeah
resume
means
hey
I'm still
here
there's two
purposes
for that
this one's
kind of like
saying I'm
around
don't
flush
the state
right
I'm still
here
and the
other one
is
the other
purpose
is
oh
let's
change
keys
let's
refresh
key
okay
so
if you
have
what's called
session resumption
right
you can
essentially
maintain the
same
not have to
redo the
handshake
right
you can
maintain the
same
master secret
but the
nonsense can
change
remember
nonsense
these
randoms
they can
change
and so
the actual
encryption keys
and authentication
keys will change
as a result
you can
theoretically
also change
the cipher suite
at that point
most of the time
that doesn't happen
but you can
change
say ah
we'll be using
I don't know
RSA
with
AES
let's switch
to something
else
you could do
that
if the
policy allows
if both
sides
agree
you can
do
never mind
this
so
the main
I'm not going
to go in
such detail
over 1.3
it is actually
in some ways
a simpler
protocol
let's
zoom
on this
this is a
handshake
so what we've
seen is this
right
the first
four messages
are the handshake
and then you get
the HTTP
get
HTTP
right
because this
is what you
really want
right
you want
to fetch
a URL
so this
and this
gives you
like
this timeline
gives you
approximate
like
for comparison
an average
timeline
for how long
it takes
so if you look
at
it starts
with 0
and
it's 200
milliseconds
until you get
here
okay
that's two
round trips
and that's
pure overhead
and so now
it's pure overhead
as far as
the user
is concerned
and then the
real useful
stuff is
get and put
right
here
now with
version 1.3
there's just
one round trip
and then
two packets
plan
hello
key share
and then
server
hello
key share
certificate
verify
blah blah blah
blah blah
okay
we're not going
to go
through the exact
format
but
essentially
the time
is cut in
half
with pretty
much
the same
result
that the
two parties
there's still
a handshake
it's just
a two message
handshake
not a four
message
handshake
and it's
faster
obviously
right
so 100
milliseconds
you might
not really
care
but over
time
this adds up
right
for many
users
over time
right
a lot of
traffic
delays
so cutting
things in
half is
better
you had a
question
what's the
improvement
that
okay
many
there are
a number
of improvements
one of the
things is
simplification
so
TLS
1.2
and B4
they have
way too
many
cipher suites
some of
them
got deprecated
because they
were like
RC4
is a
cipher
MD5
a hash
function
they are
broken
or at least
they are
no longer
secure
DDS
triple
DES
no longer
considered
secure
or too
expensive
I forget
exactly
yeah
I think
it's
no longer
considered
secure
so
most of
the
time
today
you
will
see
AES
as
the
encryption
as
the
bulk
encryption
you
will
see
SHA-256
you
will
not
see
SHA-128
anymore
so
rather than
hundreds
of
cipher suites
I think
the
main ones
are like
five or six
today
and
they're not
using RSA
anymore
so
also
the names
of the
cipher suites
changed
like
I remember
I was showing
like
TLS
RSA
with
blah blah blah
blah blah
and
the first
thing
that
this
string
would
tell you
is
how
are we
exchanging
keys
which is
how
RSA
when you
client
increase
a random
number
for the
server
and the
second
one
was
how
does
server
authenticate
also
RSA
because
he
decrypts
right
and
something
that the
client
sent
to him
and
can
implicitly
authenticate
so
that's
gone
instead
of
that
they
no
longer
say
how
you
exchange
the
keys
everything
is
done
essentially
by
a
DPA
element
or
some
version
of
DPA
element
which
is
either
elliptic
curve
or
normal
and
the
signatures
are now
required
so
there's
no
more
implicit
authentication
so
now
both
you
know
both
clients
and
the
server
have
to
stop
well
the
server
has
to
stop
basically
and
the
client
can
sign
with
the
ephemeral
key
they
just
generated
okay
so
it's
a
strictly
stronger
syntax
strictly
more
higher
security
at
half
the
cost
so
that
higher
security
enables
the
reduction
in
messages
no
it's
just
no
not
higher
no
it's
a
reduction
in
messages
and
shading
off
some
of
the
questionable
currently
algorithms
allows us
to do
this
because
what the
client
can do
now
you see
the client
hello
is still
in the
form
the client
says
I don't know
anything about
this server
right
I just
know the
URL
so what I want
is I want a
certificate
that says
that this
URL is inside
the certificate
and it's signed
by somebody
I trust
right
so
it's like
essentially
you come
to
I'm a
hiring manager
at a company
you come to me
and you say
I have a UCI
degree
I may not have
ever heard of UCI
okay
and I've never met
you
but if you give me
a signed
diploma
signed by UCI
register
and then I look up
UCI register
and I see that
they are certified
by University of
California
Central Authority
and that one
is certified
by a California
Department of Education
well
I trust
the Department of Education
of the state
of California
you see what I mean
so I know
their root certificate
I will verify
the UC certificate
then I will verify
UCI certificate
your certificate
make sure it's valid
make sure it's not revoked
right
that kind of thing
so that's still the case
the client
before this starts
does not trust
the service
just knows the URL
and so
that remains
in both versions
the web
the fundamentals
of the web
don't change
but what we're saying
now is a client
for example
can generate
like
think of it
as a temporary
public key
there
right
where he knows
the private key
and what he does
is he can now
send a message
with a public key
to the server
and he can say
and by the way
I do know
the private key
and how can you do this
he can sign
with a private key
that message
that includes
the public key
kind of it was
essentially like
a self-signed certificate
the server said
oh look that's cool
because now
you're not joking
you're not messing around
with me
you know the key
which you
you know the private key
for which the public key
you'll be just sending me
so then the server says
okay now I have
my own certificate
here's my certificate
oh maybe a chain
of certificates
and I only use RSA
certificates can be signed
with RSA
but my public key
is no longer RSA
it's some kind of
D.K. Hellman type
public key
which can be used
for many things
but
there it is
so now
a server has a public key
from the form
remember G to the B
or something
and the client
has a public key
remember G to the A
and then they can
each compute
G to the A B
okay
so that's basically
the idea
and
when the server
receives that message
one
he's able to
compute the key
right away
because
he knows his
you know
he knows B
right
that's his private key
and he receives
G to the A
so right away
he knows it
and in that second message
the second green message
he can already sign
using that key
or MAC
okay
so that message
can be secure
they already have
a secret
in common
so
what is
yeah
I would like to know
for the client
when the client
decide to
choose the
TS 1.2
and 1.2
so
this is
the client
hello
did you get
that announcement
I posted
yes
did you see
that announcement
I posted
about this
there's a very cute
little site
that if you expand
everything
it will tell you
in excruciating
detail
everything
you want to know
about this
now
if you
in that pointer
that I sent you
link
right
there's a 1.2
if you substitute
with 1.3
you will see
the same
gory details
of a 1.3
handshake
okay
now
the difference is
the client
hello
is present
in all of them
so
at the client
hello stage
the first thing
that the server
sees is
the setup
or the highest
version
that the client
is supporting
so if the client
specifies
the highest version
he supports
is 1.2
that server
says
okay
if I'm allowed
for example
the server
could be
federal government
saying
go away
I don't
I don't talk
to anybody
who doesn't
speak the latest
version
okay
but if it's
an e-commerce
site
they're like
I don't
sell this one
I don't care
if you're using
the latest version
so it will say
okay
1.2 is fine
you see what I mean
if the client
says
oh
1.3
in the client
the server
could say
yeah
but I'm in
I don't know
Slabonia
and we don't
speak 1.3
here yet
we're still
like living
10 years ago
so then
we regress
to 1.2
you see what I mean
so server will
reply with
1.2
but yeah
for the previous
slide
yeah
for the previous
slide
it seems that
the client
sent more
message
if it
uses
1.3
so if
no
less
because
look
both of them
say
client
hello
right
but the client
hello
is not exactly
the same
if you look
at the
that's why
I told you
if you look
go into that
website
right
and you compare
the client
hello
messages
for both
1.2
and 1.3
they're not
exactly the same
but the beginning
is the same
do you see what I mean
they are the same
in the beginning
so
if you
if the client
hello
is a 1.2
the server
will realize
that
you see what I mean
so if the client
is willing to speak
1.3
the client
hello
should be 1.3
if the client
hello
the client speaks
only 1.2
up to 1.2
he will
it will be 1.2
but the server
will recognize
by looking
in the first byte
yeah
so
no
because
the server
will simply
reply that
my check
cipher spec
I will pick
1.2
now
don't quote me
on this
but I think
one is a superset
of the other
so it's still
parsable
you don't have
to trust me
you have to trust
all these hundreds
of people
that work
on this
to make sure
because it's all
made for programmers
right
it was all
made for people
to make it easy
to code
to parse things
right
so even if
the format
changes
the preamble
almost never
changes
right
so you should
be looking
at like
the very
first few
fields
in the header
and say
ah
that will tell
me the version
right
and if I don't
support this version
then I can't
then it's an error
but if I can't
support this version
then we can
downgrade
right
if my policy
allows me
right
so for example
maybe
that depends
very much
on web
web
web service
policy
whether it's
like a client
might come
from
within the
US
and say
I speak
1.2
and the web
server says
okay
I'll speak
1.2
with you
and the client
comes over
from Botswana
and the server
says
uh-uh
I don't
trust Botswana
I don't know
where the hell
you are
really
so for foreign
clients
I will
bunk with
three or nothing
it's totally
fine
to do that
so primarily
what do we
use this
to sell
for
I mean
the primary
thing
has always
been
some kind
of e-commerce
right
because
we're buying
stuff
right
internet
was built
essentially
on e-commerce
internet
of today
not
the original
internet
I would say
sorry
correction
the web
right
the driving force
of the web
is e-commerce
so
as I
already motivated
before
client-less education
is generally
not needed
why
well because
with what
right
you're going
to an e-commerce
site
you're buying
widgets
from
ADC
incorporated
and you may
have never
visited
ADC
incorporated
you're
bargain shopping
right
using google
saying compare
prices
oh look at
that
a company
in Kravistan
all right
cheap stuff
let me get
it
they don't
know you
you don't
know them
okay
so you
authenticated
them
but why
should you
authenticate
yourself
as a client
until you
decide to
buy
and it's
not really
authentication
that you're
doing
right
you're just
presenting
a method
of payment
right
which may be
stolen
as long as
it's valid
the web server
doesn't care
all they want
to make sure
is that you
will pay
who you are
they don't really
care
so if you're
sending credit
card information
over
of course
that should be
protected
so that's what
really SSL is for
now
it's also there
to protect
to you
against evil
web servers
and that's
where it
transcends
e-commerce
when you go
to CNN.com
assuming you
trust CNN
or whatever
your taste
may be
fox.com
you want
to get news
from them
and not
from some
belorussian
government agency
right
or a north
korean
mouthpiece
of what's
his name
you know
so you
want to get
the real
thing
so in that
case it's
not money
that's a
stake
it's authenticity
right
in that case
nobody cares
that you
actually encrypt
right
in that case
you may not
even care about
encrypting the
data
you care about
authenticating
the server
maybe using
null encryption
make sense
right
of course
SSL
and TLS
they're not
magic
right
they're not
going to do
anything
about like
guaranteeing
that if you
send credit
card data
and shipping
address
or whatever
they're not
going to sell
it to some
mass marketer
or some
annoying
telemarketer
or just
give it to
somebody on
the street
to quickly
buy 500
pair of jeans
you know
you have no
idea what's
happening
with your
credit card
you're just
going to
trust them
that they
will erase
it
or store
securely
most
clients
of course
have no
idea
what it
means
for a
server
certificate
to even
exist
right
most
think about
not
yourselves
because
you're all
super
educated
folks
but
think
about
various
family
members
and
you know
some of
them
are
children
they don't
know
they use
the web
the internet
they have
no idea
what it
all means
so we
rely on
conscious
correct
implementations
to make
sure
that
certificates
are valid
the certificates
correspond to
the websites
that they're
assigned to
etc
more importantly
than
e-commerce
although that's
not as much
of a segment
for
application
domain
for
CLS
is
banking
and other
financial
services
right
it's kind
of
you can
think of
it as
hyper
e-commerce
right
this is
where the
money
the real
is
your
money
right
here the
bank is
not selling
you anything
right
you already
decided to
put your
money in
the bank
and you
have a
relationship
so instead
of entering
your credit
card info
actually here
you do
enter
to begin
a session
with the
bank
you do
enter
your
username
password
and god
knows what
else
MFA
right
so
there's
more
of a
beginning
session
and end
but notice
that people
go to
banks
also to
browse
let's
say
interest
rates
without
having to
log in
so you
do want
to make
sure you're
going to
the bank
it's the
right bank
and it
displays you
truthful
information
so SSL
TLS is
useful there
too
right
even without
you logging
in
and authenticating
yourself
sometimes
in early
2000s
mid 2000s
some banks
that were
kind of
hip
and
cool
thought
they
would
send
customers
I think
I mentioned
before
like various
dongles
and USB
keys
and other
things
that you
could use
to upload
a client
certificate
for SSL
TLS
that way
you could
have
strong
two-way
authentication
this
somehow
fell out
of
fashion
okay
that's
the end
of
SSL
TLS
now we
go on
to
another
beautiful
masterpiece
IPsec
quick show
of hands
how many
people here
have heard
IPsec
two
three
and
well
okay
so
IPsec
is IP
security
extension
strictly
speaking
unlike
Carverus
which is
a system
right
Carverus
remember
e-system
have
many
protocols
right
components
SSL
TLS
is a
protocol
right
our
protocol suite
really
and a set
of formats
right
the protocols
always have
formats
for messages
so
IPsec
strictly speaking
is not
a protocol
it is
actually
a set
of formats
okay
so
this will
become
clear
maybe a
little bit
puzzling
at the
moment
become
clear
in a
bit
I hope
so
let's
consider
IP
is the
lingua franca
the English
of the internet
right
you want
to
communicate
you kind of
better speak
English
in the business
world today
well
if you want
to communicate
today
you need
to speak
IP
you don't
speak
IP
you are
basically
all right
IP
is the
network
layer
it is
what's
called
the
thin
waste
because
the internet
has this
kind of
a
what do you
call it
the hourglass
shape
if you look
at the
protocols
right
there are
many
protocols
why do I
say hourglass
right
so
this
will
be
physical
layer
data
link
and
here
is
network
layer
here
is
where
IP
goes
so
here
things
get
thicker
and above
IP
let's
say
this
is
IP
and
above
IP
you
have
transport
layer
session
so
I have a
presentation
application
whatever
I forget
that
but
they're
all
poorly
demarcated
here
you have
lots of
applications
right
lots and
lots of
applications
below that
also
lots of
applications
like
presentation
platforms
of various
sorts
and here
below
in the
physical
layer
you have
Wi-Fi
Zigbee
Bluetooth
NFC
cellular
right
you have
all these
fiber
optics
twisted
copper
god
knows
what
oh
radar
infrared
right
all these
ways of
communication
so
there are
many choices
here
as the
network
layer
on the
internet
no
choice
IP
or
nothing
that's
what it's
called
the
thin
waste
so
as I
said
before
IP
was
designed
started
around
the
design
was
finalized
around
or
most
of the
work
in
designing
IP
was
done
actually
not
far
from
here
the
place
I
once
worked
it's called
ISI
information
sciences
institute
part of
USC
school
of
engineering
beautifully
situated
far away
from
USC
in
Marina
Del Rey
on
water
inspiring
people
to work
hard
in
course
so
true story
I wasn't
there
I'm not
that old
but
it was
done
a lot
of it
was done
there
at UCLA
also
there were
some
internet
pioneers
who designed
some of
this
and
DARPA
which is a
defense
advanced
research
project
agency
funded
all of
this
and
without
DARPA
there
would
have
been
no
internet
anyway
so
it was
designed
to connect
a bunch
of
routers
switches
computers
and
all
people
well
to
network
and
primary
motivation
back
then
for
the
internet
was
to
access
scarce
resources
remember
back
then
you had
computers
most
of
them
there
were
no
personal
computers
first
of
all
zero
when
FB
was
designed
none
not
such
a
thing
did
not
exist
they
were
mid-range
computers
and they
were
like
mainframes
bigger
computers
and then
the few
here and
there
around
the
world
supercomputers
okay
a
supercomputer
from
back
then
is
an
IoT
device
today
in
terms
of
its
computing
power
but
they
were
supercomputers
and
it
took
like
a
whole
floor
of
building
one
computer
because
these
resources
were
scarce
and
super
duper
expensive
like
gazillions
of
dollars
they
were
precious
right
and people
who wanted
to perform
large scale
computation
of any
kind
have to
like
buy
time
on those
computers
travel
somewhere
to
use
your
computer
right
there
physically
but
that's
not
scalable
so
people
realize
that
if
you
want
to
have
access
remote
to
resources
like
that
you
need
to
connect
them
somehow
and
dial
up
what
existed
modems
remember
maybe
you've
seen
old
movies
go
and
there's
a
modem
connection
yeah
it's
not
somebody
having
a
cold
well
I
still
remember
that
and
but
that
was
totally
terrible
because
you
were
using
unstable
telephone
lines
and
terrible
equipment
so
there was
the idea
to connect
them all
with
dedicated
lines
okay
so
there you
have the birth
of the internet
right
and they
needed a
protocol
that would
basically
break
communication
data
arbitrary
size
into
small
uniform
size
chunks
and
transmit
them
hop
by hop
to their
destination
why
hop
because
you
couldn't
have
fully
connected
network
right
everybody
connected
to
everything
that would
be incredibly
expensive
logistically
nightmare
right
so
they
needed
to
connect
them
via
switches
routers
right
that scales
so
the internet
protocol
was designed
for that
to hop
along
these
routers
and switches
until
these
get to
the
destination
IP
protocol
does
not
actually
perform
the routing
function
it doesn't
distribute
routes
okay
that's done
by what's
called
routing
protocols
which you
should have
learned in
your networking
course
IP just
forwards
things
all it
knows
is how
to
let the
source
generate
the packet
stick it
on the
wire
give it
to the
data link
layer
below
and then
at the
next hop
whatever that
hop might be
it might be
the destination
or it might
be a router
pick that packet
up saying
hmm
let's see
destination
I don't
know this
destination
I am not
that destination
but I think
somebody else
I know
knows where
the destination
is
so you forward
it to somebody
else who knows
better
according to
some routing
data
so back then
the internet
was small
and very friendly
it was populated
by idealistic
and naive
geeks
who just wanted
to compute
stuff
right
and they were
not you know
hostile
I mean they were
they could be
hostile
but they were
not about
to attack
the internet
the cow
that feeds
them all
right
it was all
essentially
research
and almost
no commercial
use was allowed
on the internet
until early 90s
so for good
like 12
14 years
there was no
such thing
as commerce
on the internet
and so
from that
small and
friendly world
we wound up
what we have
today
essentially
internet
in many ways
is a giant
global sewer
where everything
goes
and anything
flies
and back then
all the hosts
were known
in fact
if you were
running a
unix machine
back then
you didn't even
need domain name
service
you could have
what's a file
called
etc password
there was a file
called etc hosts
and it actually
listed one per line
names
and IP addresses
of every host
on the internet
yeah
I remember
when I inherited
my first
machine
in grad school
it was like
from
the machine
was older
but it had
this file
and it had
like I don't know
5,000 entries
and there were
all the hosts
on the internet
that's it
everywhere in the world
the users
were limited too
right
security was
essentially
not an issue
back then
in that world
it was not an issue
think of it
as the internet
was essentially
like a hippie
hippie-dippie
private network
you couldn't
just like
randomly hook up
to the internet
there was no
wireless
access
zero
okay
the easiest way
to work with
the internet
was to actually
like
use a
wired
ethernet
right
you have an
ethernet port
in the wall
you
start with
wire
and
if you have
internet access
you can start
doing
well
as you know
the world has
changed dramatically
since then
so
security has
become an issue
now
people were not
totally naive
already
in the late 80s
they started
thinking about
what will happen
when the internet
becomes available
to the masses
and becomes
commercialized
so
hostility
or
essentially
lack of security
in the original
internet
was already
a problem
so what can
you do with
IP
even if you
don't know
anything
about it
just
trust me
you will
see the
format
in a minute
allows very
easy address
spoofing
so
IP packets
all have
a header
and a header
says
among other things
where is this
packet coming from
and where is it
going to
otherwise it would
make no sense
at least the
destination
but the source
is the spoofed
the source is just
an IP address
IP address
is not in the
form of authentication
it's just
there
right
you can just
like
substitute it
with some
other IP address
and so if you
do some kind
of filtering
based on
source IP
addresses
you're fooling
yourself
because it
doesn't mean
anything
the source address
why do we
use the source
address
well because
the destination
when it wants
to reply
it needs to
know where to
reply
so we still
need the
source
in the
kitchen
most packets
anybody can
take a packet
not touch
the source
address
but modify
the destination
address
or modify
the payload
right
the data
just pick
something up
yeah
sure
packets can
be reordered
right
so if a
malicious router
receives packets
and you can
say oh I
received packet
one before
I received packet
two but I'm
going to send
out packet
two first and
then packet
one just to
confuse and
annoy people
but maybe
actually there's
a security
application
if you send
them the good
example I tell
kids in the
undergrad class
why reordering is
important is think
about this
this is actually
used to be the
case back in
the early 80s
the ATM machines
which used to
have bank
ATM machines
used to have
their own
private network
and if you
and all these
transactions that
you do at the
ATM like
withdraw $100
deposit $500
check my balance
they were like
messages
okay
and so
if you were at
ATM and you
said okay well
here's a $500
deposit
and transaction
click return
and here's a $200
withdrawal
on cash
well that's fine
but what if you
reverse the two
if you reverse the
two
you're going to
get hit with
overdraft charges
right
if you reorder
these two
so that's why
ordering actually
matters a lot
I mean not just
that's a silly
example
of course it
doesn't work
today but
it's an issue
and it actually
happens even
today if you
use ATM for
example in a
foreign country
sometimes they're
poorly connected
and you may
still like for
example you
deposit
something in
one ATM
and the
deposit takes
a day but
in the meantime
you withdrew
something in a
different ATM
that is well
connected and
it happens
immediately
you may have
a problem
anyway reordering
is an issue
deletion is an
issue but
there's nothing
we can do
about deletion
right so
we can delete
packets right
discard them
on the way
eavesdropping
replay
replaying
recording
all packets
or recording
packets
in real time
and then
replaying them
later
and eavesdropping
on not
just data
right
and I want
you to
understand
because it's
important
for IPsec
eavesdropping
on data
that is
carried in
the packet
is one
thing
you can
protect
that
with like
SSL
TLS
right
but
maybe
maybe not
right
depending on
what
you're doing
but
eavesdropping
on metadata
cannot be
protected
with SSL
TLS
or
transport
layer
security
now
what is
metadata
that's
the data
carried
in the
packet
header
and that
be
packet
header
and it
leaks
information
right
it leaks
information
among others
where is
this packet
coming from
and where
is it going
to
that itself
is sensitive
information
in many cases
think about
censorship
now you ever
heard of countries
that do
censorship
right
based on
where packets
come from
going to
a number
of countries
do that
that comes
from metadata
so
IPsec
is a
very very
thin layer
on top
of IP
right
so it
doesn't
interfere
of course
with
physical
and data
link
layers
which
can use
their own
encryption
and their
own
security
and Wi-Fi
for example
uses
there's a number
of standards
right
for Wi-Fi
if you dig
into your
laptop's Wi-Fi
settings
you'll see
there's
all kinds
of options
for Wi-Fi
security
and probably
most of you
have
whole routers
right
or wireless
routers
that you've
set up
and maybe
you've seen
the choices
different choices
for Wi-Fi
security
right
so that just
protects
this first
last hop
right
this
something
immediate
right
from
your device
devices
to the
access point
so that's
not going
to help
you in the
long
run
over
the
long run
and so
you can
do this
hop
by hop
every link
can do
its own
encryption
but it's
not going
to help
n-to-n
and so
IP
is the
first
layer
in the
hierarchy
that is
n-to-n
source
destination
so we
built
here
on top
of network
layer
but it's
not a
transport layer
it's just
like a
sublayer
on top
of network
layer
and its
presence
is
transparent
okay
TCP
UDP
they don't
know
that it
exists
just a
quick recap
of how
IP
works
anybody
seen this
before
if you've
taken a
network
course
you should
have
seen
this
allowing
a few
of you
look
familiar
with
this
okay
is
the
IP
before
heaven
this
is
first
one
two
three
four
five
the
lines
are
the
head
this
is
options
they may
or may
not be
present
okay
but the
first
five
are always
there
okay
and
it's
like
this
it's
bits
per
line
so
the
very
first
thing
you
see
in
the
header
is
a
version
number
now
do you
know
how many
versions
of IP
are there
that's
a
for one
word
answer
you're
both
right
and
wrong
which
rarely
happens
right
answer
because
there
exists
in
IPv6
but
there's
not a
conclusion
there's
ever
been
six
version
nobody's
ever heard
of one
and two
and I
don't think
even three
there's
IPv4
and there's
IPv6
and
IPv5
is like
some
lost
you
know
I
don't
upward
effort
that
never
saw
the
light
of it
so
I
don't
know
what
happened
to
the
IPv5
I
never
heard
of it
there
is
before
and
both
of
them
believe it or not
like
TLS 1.2
and TLS 1.3
exist on the internet
today
and if
you open
your Mac
or your
Windows
machine
you open
your network
setting
you will
see that
you probably
have both
an IPv6
and IPv4
address
depending on
where you
are
which network
you're using
yeah
no
because
and I
thought
you want
to know
why
because
this is
the
within
waste
this is
the only
changing
IP
is like
moving
mountains
okay
it's a
humongous
undertaking
people thought
about it
for decades
because IP
has fundamental
issues
no matter
what version
it is
it's a fundamental
issue
to change
to something
other than
IP
requires
incredible
effort
okay
that's why
with SSL
TLS
it's much
easier
with
Kerber
it's much
easier
this application
things
moving things
in the network
is very high
moving things
evolving things
here
easy
that's
hop by
hop
you can
do it
on your
own
in your
home
install
some
weird
ass
custom
hack
data link
layer
that you
designed
nobody cares
maybe your
neighbors care
but you know
what I mean
you're totally
free to do
that
you want
to put
pigeons
in the
physical layer
that carry
IP packets
you know
no problem
do it
but
yeah
serious
you can do
it
nobody cares
except
people
get pooped
on
but
network
layer
is where
it's
common
and so
it's
impossible
let me put it
this way
you all
got a lot
of years
ahead
I would
be super
duper
surprised
if there's
IPV7
or anything
higher than
in your
lifetime
of course
never say
no
never
but
I would
be really
surprised
because
it's
such a
hard
thing
yeah
but let's
keep our
eye on the
ball
what
IP
before
remember
designed
in like
early
80s
they
thought
jeez
we have
5,000
10,000
hosts
on the
internet
32 bits
is enough
for an
address
32 bits
2 to the
right
big number
wrong
not such a
big number
after all
so
already
by the
decade
later
like
maybe
late
80s
they
started
saying
ah
maybe
mid
80s
even
we're
going to
run
out
sooner
or
later
like
within
years
we're
going
truth
is
actually
they never
did
and
we still
use
before
which
means
we
didn't
quite
there
one
of the
reasons
is
that
and
this
is
totally
obscure
the
U.S.
government
or
the
agency
was
called
IANA
that
allocates
IP
addresses
instead
of
this
weird
agency
that
worldwide
they
allocated
huge
blocks
of
addresses
to
corporations
that
never
used
them
and
they
also
reserved
huge
blocks
for
future
think
they
released
some
of
them
gradually
so
we
wound
up
never
not
yet
running
out
of
IPv4
addresses
but
it's
still
not
a
good
idea
to
stick
IPv4
in
the
longer
so
IPv6
was
designed
to
take
care
of
look
at
IPv4
because
most
of
the
rest
of
the
discussion
today
is
IPv4
version
number
that's
fixed
at
for
IPv4
that's
but
remember
our
SSL
TLS
discussion
if you
have
an
IPv6
packet
that
will
be
and
that
is
the
only
things
they
have
in
common
the
first
thing
in
the
packet
is
the
version
number
it's
kind of
like
an
SSL
TLS
you
look at
the
version
numbers
like
now
I
know
what
to
do
IHL
is
internet
header
length
it's
only
bits
right
so
not a lot
it just
tells you
how many
32 bit
words
there
are
in
the
header
32 bit
words
right
so
for
standard
IPv4
without
options
it's
going
to
be
it's
going
to
just
be
number
type
of
service
type
of
service
is
an
obscure
field
it's
used
for
different
type
of
flows
it was
supposed
to
distinguish
between
let's
say
a
remote
terminal
like
a
login
connection
where
you
type
in
like
one
character
the
time
is
sent
as
a
packet
from
let's
say
file
transfer
connections
where you
have a
fault
more like
HTTP
small
requests
in
big
response
is out
is it
because
it was
like
very
old
that
it
seems
like
odd
that
they
would
waste
so
many
bits
to
say
five
rather
than
oh
no
it's
not
always
five
it's
not
always
it could
be
longer
it could
be
longer
because
of
options
least
five
right
that's
right
I
well
wait
a minute
I
don't
quote
me
I used
to
know
this
I
should
look
back
it
may
be
that
five
is
the
minimum
so
it
counts
over
five
but
it
has
to
have
the
length
and
I'm
pretty
sure
that
let's
see
one
two
four
the
other
question
is
why
would
you need
the
IHL
if you
have
the
total
length
anyway
why
do
you
need
to
ah
total
length
is
including
the
data
that
includes
the
data
that
I'll show
you
okay
below
this
that's
the
header
below
this
is
the
data
so
that's
a
different
bit
and
that's
bits
so
the
maximum
you could
ever
transmit
in one
packet
is
2 to
the
IP
does
not
tell
you
how
big
a
packet
can
be
up to
that
cannot
be
built
above
you
know
to
the
minus
but
it
can
be
less
and
that's
determined
by
that's
again
more
than
you
want
to
know
but
is
determined
by
the
maximum
transmission
unit
of
the
link
of
the
link
not
the
path
link
that you're
transmitting
it
so
for
example
an
internet
it's
1,500
something
bytes
okay
there are
some
other
media
where it's
smaller
and some
where it's
bigger
identification
is essentially
like a
sequence number
of the
packet
it
allows
the
receiver
to say
okay
to order
packets
flags
fragment
offset
that's
called
fragmentation
IPv4
supports
what's
called
fragmentation
which
means
if
you
give
on
the
source
side
to IP
a
large
packet
it
will
chop
it
in
smaller
pieces
okay
subject
to
the
maximum
transmission
unit
of
its
link
am I
making
sense
so
if
the
maximum
transmission
unit
on its
next
top
is
bytes
it
will
chop
everything
into
that
appropriate
size
and
then
it
needs
to
reassemble
them
at
the
receiver
which
is
a
huge
pain
in
ass
because
fragments
of
the
same
packet
can
also
be
fragmented
in
transit
they
can
never
be
reassembled
in
transit
because
in
transit
everything
is
treated
as
one
packet
but
when
they
arrive
at
the
destination
they
need
to
be
reassembled
and
IP
before
implementations
suck
because
of
this
they
are
complex
because
fragmentation
is a
very
painful
thing
also
for
security
IP
has
no
fragmentation
so
offset
means
how far
into
the
original
packet
is
this
particular
packet
make sense
yeah
like
where
in the
original
packet
does
this
one
start
which
piece
of
the
puzzle
is
this
time
to live
is a
hot
count
usually
initialized
to 255
not always
but up
to 255
that's the
only
thing
you can
put there
and the
maximum
value
and it's
decremented
by every
router
that
sees
the
packet
reason
it's
there
is to
avoid
loops
routing
and all kinds
of weird
traffic
things that
used to
happen
on the
internet
right
if you
don't
have it
then
in theory
a packet
can
forever
run
around
like in
a maze
so
once it
reaches
zero
the router
that receives
it
and decrements
it to
zero
discards
the packet
also because
that consumes
resources
right
protocol
protocol means
not IP
what is the
next protocol
which transport
layer
which
which protocol
is going to
handle this
packet after
IP
when it
goes up
remember
packet is
received at
the destination
goes for the
physical layer
right
then
from physical
layer
to the
data link
layer
I hand it
over to
IP
does its
thing
and says
what do I
do with
it next
protocol
tells it
okay
it invokes
the appropriate
function
if it's a
TCP packet
it calls
TCP
received
if it's a
UDPAC packet
it calls
UDP
received
etc
header
checksum
is a very
very silly
value
it's a
once complement
of once
complement
of XOR
of all
the 16
bit
values
like
fold it
here
it's a
terrible
checksum
of the
header
basically
it catches
benign errors
like if
routers used
to be very
unreliable
and once
another
flip a
bit
well if
you flip
a bit
in the
header
you know
you can
like
change
the
destination
of the
source
so
the reason
checksum
is there
is to
catch
such
errors
in
routers
and
throw
away
the
pattern
but it's
not
supposed
to
protect
against
attack
at all
okay
source
address
and
destination
address
yay
okay
that was
a 32
bit
source
IP
destination
options
one second
all kinds
of crap
goes there
time
have you ever
used
ping
trace route
anybody
that uses
options
when you
use
ping
you're
using
what's
called
record
route
options
because
when
you
do
it
will
show
you
for
example
how many
seconds
it
gets
sorry
ping
is
more
timing
ping
is
about
timing
so
you use
what's
called
timing
option
it records
the time
to get
to this
hop
the second
the third
hop
all the way
to the
destination
trace
route
is
used
record
route
option
which
tells
you
exact
route
that
the packet
takes
as it
gets
to
the
destination
so
every
router
okay
most packets
normal packets
don't have
options
everything you
see in red
this should be
red
not blue
everything you
see in red
changes
hop by hop
or at least
can't change
time to live
always changes
for every hop
fragment offset
can change
if a router
refragments
the packet
for example
if you see
the packet
of 1500
bytes
and the
next hop
only takes
800 bytes
maximum
so you
have to
split that
in two
and that
changes
the header
checksum
will change
too
in fact
the header
checksum
changes
anytime
anyway
because
time to live
changes
yeah
absolutely
it should
change
but I think
IHL is not
including the
options
I think
it is
it's back
to his
question
why is it
five
I think
it is
just
waste
but I
double
check
my memory
is just
like
why
yeah
I looked
it up
it has
to be
like the
minimum
value
is
five
and the
max
is 15
but
I think
he's right
because if
you record
the route
it will go
over 15
so I have to
look up the
answer to that
question
what happens
I think
it should
not
but
don't know
anyway
so
one of the
things I
point out
is these
red fields
they can
change
in transit
okay
the other
fields must
be the same
IPv6
in contrast
very different
but notice
the version number
right
that's the
common language
they have
see the version
number
in the very
corner
same
same field
same length
this is how
you know
oh IPv6
IPv4
yeah
when you say
you can't
change the
route
are you
including
like
adding
routers
because that
would change
the source
or destination
shouldn't
right
because IPv
was designed
before NAT
yeah
yes
of course
NATs are
an exception
I mean
you could
always do
things that
you're not
supposed to
right
in a way
but NAT
was originally
a hack
that people
frowned
upon
now
it's a
standard
so it
co-exists
yeah
okay
so now
notice
no options
anymore
notice
no fragments
anymore
much cleaner
design
destination
that is
source
we'll not
run out
of that
there probably
you know
more than
grains of sand
on this
earth
right
2 to the
is a giant
number
payload
length
that's the
of a
payload
you don't
need the
internet
header
length
because it's
fixed
so a
payload
length
is everything
that comes
after
next header
means
particle
which
is going
to end up
in the
header
after
meaning
whatever
starts
here
right
is not
just
playing data
it's another
particle
like
transport
or
another
or something
else
so you
need to
tell
the
IP
header
to which
particle
to pass
this
next
hop limit
that's the
time to live
that's still
there
right
but it's
same
shouldn't
be hopping
too much
but in fact
the number
of hops
on the
internet
has gone
down
over the
years
you know
why
big ASPs
big giant
ASPs
long haul
lines
without
problems
right
so you
can basically
do one
hop
and cross
most of
the US
in one
hop
so
if you
do
just for
fun
pick your
most exotic
location
in
India
you can
think of
like
again
Slabonia
or Kravistan
somewhere
and
try
to do
a
tracer
you
won't
see
that
many
hops
surprisingly
anyway
flow
label
traffic
class
is
again
quality
of
service
that
talks
about
is this
like
a
video
that
you
need
to
see
in
real
time
or
is
this
like
a
file
transfer
so
does
understand
what
quality
of
service
means
or
is
this
like
a
terminal
where
you're
typing
and
again
it's
one
character
per
packet
so
the
delay
different
for
types
of
traffic
and
that's
what
traffic
class
is
supposed
to
capture
flow
label
is
really
for
connection
ID
think
about
connection
ID
between
the
two
IP
interfaces
source
and
this
page
but
there's
no
connection
as
such
right
because
IP
is
connection
okay
so
this
is
just
a
side
by
comparison
with
the
same
things
so
yes
IPv6
Harry
is
longer
because
the
addresses
are
much
longer
but
in
terms
of
like
its
format
it's
cleaner
smaller
right
so
in
the
rest
of
this
we're
going
to
use
IPv4
so
what
is
the
goal
of
IPv4
well
tries
to
address
the
problems
that
I
presented
in
the
beginning
you
want
to
verify
the
source
of
IPv4
okay
that
is
replay
and
reordering
of
patterns
reordering
can happen
accidentally
by the
way
right
replay
not
likely
very
unlikely
replay
happens
reordering
can
happen
reordering
can
happen
for
following
reasons
on
the
internet
there
is
no
guarantee
that
packets
sent
at
time
t
will
arrive
before
the
packet
that
sent
at
time
t
you
see
what I'm
saying
do
you
know
why
that
is
on
the
internet
route
between
two
IP
addresses
is
never
fixed
you
can
send
two
packets
in
rapid
succession
theoretically
they
can
take
completely
different
routes
theoretically
doesn't
happen
most of
the
time
but
they
can
there
is
actually
a
which
is
where
they
made
tiny
in
like
changes
to
the
IP
packets
that
didn't
actually
affect
the
contents
or
whatever
and
change
the
routing
in
such
a
way
that
it
would
either
get
censored
or
not
censored
based
on
the
routed
way
yeah
I
could
see
that
but
just
the
first
part
of
what
you
said
by
subtly
changing
something
in
the
header
okay
remember
that
quality
of
service
that
could
change
the
route
so
for
example
you
might
send
video
packets
via
one
route
and
let's
say
conferencing
video
packets
for
streaming
video
service
on
one
route
zoom
via
different
route
because
zoom
is more
delay
sensitive
than
let's
say
streaming
video
that
you
could
buffer
right
streaming
video
is
pre-recorded
you
can
buffer
right
and
there
is
some
tolerance
to
delay
right
because
of
the
buffering
on
the
receiving
side
but
when
you
are
telecom
fishing
it
is
pre-recorded
right
it is
real
time
so
there is
no
buffering
right
so
you
see
how
different
quality
of
service
when
you
type
on
a
terminal
right
you
log in
remote
login
you
want
to
see
your
echoed
letters
right
away
you
don't
want
to
type
without
seeing
your
letters
you
know
what
means
blind
and
stupid
right
so
there is
a
different
delay
file
transfer
much
more
relaxed
right
when
you're
downloading
your
file
the
delay
requirements
are not
that
stringent
so
there's
all
different
qualities
of
service
my
guess
is
because
of
changing
that
quality
of
service
field
you
get
different
routes
I
don't
think
by
changing
packet
lengths
I
assume
you're
talking
about
same
source
destination
right
yeah
I can
see
that
and
you
could
definitely
change
traverse
different
countries
right
by changing
so
again
if you're
within
one
country
I mean
political
entity
I don't
see that
happening
so
I
suspect
what you're
talking
about
since you
said
censorship
that this
would be
across
borders
but
anyway
maybe not
I mean
if you're
already in
a country
that does
censorship
maybe
that doesn't
work
so
the
security
model
for IP
yeah
sorry
just very
quickly
do
users
or I guess
both the
server and
the client
do they
get to
choose
what type
of traffic
they are
doesn't that
violate
the security
principle
about
resources
in IP
yeah
well
no no
no
that's not
like
SSL
TLS
right
or
HTTP
in IP
layer
you don't
really choose
it's more
like
first of all
there's no
server
client
I mean
like in
the sense
of like
there's
some
resources
right
and there's
some users
yeah
and
so
could you
it's in their
interest
to like
choose the
best
yes
are you
saying
can a
user of
a computer
like a
laptop
hack into
IP
implementation
locally
and fix
that field
right
and change
IP
so that
it will
always put
the highest
priority
kind of
UI
yes
you can
get
yourself
Linux
hack
it
source
available
you can
go into
the IP
implementation
and do
that
I don't
think there's
any way
to prevent
that
but
the other
way
packets
coming back
may not
care about
what you
say
right
so your
packets
might
get a
preferential
treatment
but the
return packets
won't
unless you
agree
hack
both
say I'm
Netflix
why would
I not
want to
make my
QS
the best
and sure
buffering
but I don't
want buffering
for my
users
yeah I
don't know
you could
I suspect
can Netflix
detect anything
that you're
messing with
probably not
no I mean
from Netflix
oh from
Netflix
well they have
to be good
corporate citizens
right because
people can
inspect their
packets
right IP
packet headers
are visible
so this packet
inspection can
say ISP
will say
they even
Netflix
themselves have
a long distance
at least ISP
and like the
borders Netflix
right and they'll
say what the
hell are you
doing
you are choking
all the other
traffic out
I mean they do
they do
but they still
use the rest
of the
even if they
are their own
ISP
I mean their
border other
what's called
autonomous
domains
and those
will come
play
so the
IP security
one is like
this
yeah
I mean I
will use the
word machines
hosts
but what are
we really
talking about
is interfaces
right
because IP
address is not
a host
address
it's an
address of
an interface
you can have
a device that
have multiple
IP addresses
right
you do in
fact have
devices with
multiple IP
addresses
all your
phones and
laptops have
multiple IP
addresses
but just
simplifies things
like this
so it
considers that
you can
essentially
secure these
routers and
secure the
hosts
right
but what you
cannot secure
fundamentally
is these
communication
links
so here
from the
host to
the
right
and I
imagine
that this
picture really
shows you
more like
an organizational
network
right
think about
this is like
UCI
and this is
UCLA
and in
between here
it's only
a short
yellow line
but this
is in fact
a potentially
giant distance
right
many hops
it is the
internet
in between
so we don't
trust anything
that is
between
the boundary
of UCI
and UCLA
but we also
don't trust
anything here
within UCI
because no
we're using
the ether
and you know
maybe we don't
even trust
OIT so much
because they
run all the
wired infrastructure
so that's the
outlook from
my BSEC
point of view
that we don't
trust the
wires
and it
comes in
two
well
it comes in
two
what's called
format flavors
and two
modes
and this is
confusing
I already
can warn you
has two
formats
one is called
ESP
another is called
AH
that one is
simpler
authentication
header
and
encapsulating
security payload
and they
all work
together
with something
we will not
cover
because it
is just
too damn
boring
and too
difficult
to cover
in this
kind of
course
called IP
security policy
and something
called
Ike
internet key
exchange
so unlike
TLS
I will not
be telling
you a lot
about how
keys
are established
because that's
a separate
thing
in SSL
CLS
key
establishment
is like
part and parcel
of all the
actual
part
okay
cover is
true
right
but in
IPSEC
it's not
it's
something
it's like
a separate
component
called
Ike
so what does
IPSEC do
only a couple
more minutes
and we're done
it provides
security in
three cases
but not only
the main
three use cases
host to host
meaning interface
to source
to destination
okay
end to end
security
it also
provides
host to gateway
which means
the typical
scenario I want
you to think
about is that
you work for a
company and
you have a host
your laptop
and you're in a
hotel room
in Slabonia
okay
some godforsaken
place
and you want
to connect
by the
untrusted
internet
right
over to
the home
office
so your
home office
has a
gateway
a router
right
a gateway
is basically
a border
router
and so
that whole
wilderness
between your
laptop
and that
border
router
needs to
be secured
and that's
what IPSEC
will do
for you
too
and then
gateway
to gateway
that's more
like thinking
about
again
the UCI
UCLA
example
on a
previous slide
that's more
like how do
we secure
gateway
to gateway
right
and you
can also
have
all combinations
there are
like you can
secure end
to end
and also
on top of
that
gateway
to gateway
okay
you can
concatenate
them
you can
have
host to
gateway
IPSEC
then separate
gateway to
gateway IPSEC
and another
gateway to
host IPSEC
IPSEC is
very malleable
very flexible
I guess
right
so
typical
and it has
these also
two modes
which we
don't have
time to
discuss
called tunnel
and transport
I guess
that means
not a lot
of IPSEC
questions
on your
big jump
sadly
but you
have time
to read
I will post
this
I just won't
be asking
very detailed
questions
alright
good luck
to y'all
for next
Tuesday
please
prepare
I will
have office
hours on
Monday
typically
people want
for some
reason
come and
visit me
before the
midterm
on the
final
I don't
know why
that is
yeah
and
be on
time