Routing protocols came back to the late 50s, early 60s and they predate the internet because
there were other networks out there in the world besides the internet.
In fact, even today there are other networks, we just don't study them as much, they don't
impact us very much. There were other architectures that were used for private networking and even
internet but different types of internet. Anyway, there are two, okay, how many people have heard
of Dijkstra's algorithm? Oh, that's better. So what does Dijkstra's algorithm do? Shortest
path. So, right, given a network or a graph, and a graph and a network are kind of the same,
right, given a connected, not fully connected, but just a connected graph, Dijkstra's algorithm
will find you a route, i.e. path between A and B. Okay, and it does it depth first.
How many people heard of Bellman Ford? Oh, good, so you heard it in the same context probably in an
algorithms course or some other kind of elementary course. Usually they're covered also, re-covered,
in networks course, as a prelude to route. Bellman Ford is also an algorithm for graphs,
which are networks, connected, right? If you have a disconnected graph, it doesn't work.
And it is breadth first, okay? Not depth first, breadth first. And so for the last 70 years,
there's been a lot of debate about which one is better, right? They're not compatible. They're sort
of mutually exclusive. You either do breadth first or you do depth first. And so today's internet started
out, okay, by using a depth first, right? Something called OSPF, okay? And today it's using,
sorry, it was started out using depth first, now it's using kind of a breadth first. Something called distance vectors.
Okay, I'll explain quickly how distance vector link state works because they don't have slides
on it thinking that you already know. Link state works like this. It basically dice this.
Every node in the network, okay? And imagine we are a graph. So every adjacent person to you is a link, right?
Everybody broadcasts the state of their links. For example, I'm connected to this guy and this guy.
And I'm going to broadcast to anybody who hears that these are my connections. Let's go. Alice, Bob.
Everybody else does the same thing. He broadcasts that he connected just to one person, him. He broadcasts that
he's connected to, I don't know, two people. Everybody broadcasts that the state of their connection,
who they are adjacent to. And that broadcast is flooded. Does everybody know what flooded means?
It means when you receive a packet, you forward it out on all other interfaces, right? Which means on all other
connections. You following me? So this generalizes into following. Everyone receives the state
state of every other node in the network. Yeah? You following me? If everything is flooded and broadcast,
and let's say at roughly the same time, then everyone learns who is connected to whom directly. Yes?
Okay, that allows you to construct a graph. And do the shortest path, for example, the extra set.
Okay? Explicitly knowing what the path is. Right? You actually learn the path.
Right? So for example, to get to you over there, I will learn the path I have to go from him and him.
That's my shortest path. I could also go around, but the shortest path is like this. Okay?
This Daxter's algorithm tells me that.
So that's link state. Why it's called link state? Because everybody broadcasts the state of their links.
Links means immediate connections. Immediate, right? Who am I connected to?
So if my connection to him is down, well, I obviously don't broadcast the fact that I'm connected to him.
I only broadcast the fact that I'm connected to him. And in fact, he's the only one who hears my broadcast.
But then he rebroadcasts my broadcast, and everybody knows that, oh, well, he attends his name, right?
But everybody knows that, oh, let's see, this guy has a path of length one to me.
You learn this. You learn this. Later you rebroadcast. He learns that, he learns that you have a path of length three to me.
And he knows exactly the path. Okay. That's link state. Distance vector is very different. Distance vector says
everybody in the beginning has a table of all other nodes. So we know the population.
Okay. But I tell, I essentially tell my neighbor, my direct neighbor, let's say I'm here.
My direct neighbor is these two. I tell them my routing table.
In the beginning, my routing table is very simple. It lists all of you all with a distance infinity.
Except for them. It says, I can get, I'm connected to him with one half. I'm connected to him with one half.
If I'm telling you that I'm connected to you with one half, it's useless. You already know this.
But what you don't know is I have one half to him. Okay. So all of a sudden, now you, instead of having distance infinity to him, say,
oh, the distance is two and I am the next half. Does everybody understand this example?
And then he broadcasts his own table, which has infinity for everybody except for me, him, and the two people here.
This converges. Everybody does the same thing in the distributed fashion. This converges.
This converges. And at the end, every node has a table with every possible destination, but not the path.
They don't know the graph at all. What you do know is that to get to Isita over there,
I, it costs one, two, three, four hops, and the next hop is him. But I don't know how it goes after that.
Totally ignorant. To get to that guy in the white hat, it will be one, two, three, four. Again, next hop is him.
To get to that guy over there, next hop is him, and the distance is three. One, two, three.
One, two, three. That's what we learned in the end in distance vector. Why? Distance vector.
Because the table shows the distance. And the stuff we exchange out is called distance vectors.
That is a crash course for free.
Well, today's internet, okay, does not use either, truly speaking. It uses a hybrid. It's called path vector.
So, and it does not use actual IP addresses as a destination, or it does not even, in fact,
you can think of it as using autonomous systems. Remember ASs, ADs, as destinations. So, it does it
at a coarser granularity, right? Now, there's some details here, the IP prefixes included, but I'm
going to abstract it all the way. So, think about it that today's internet operates on the granularity
of autonomous domains or autonomous systems, right? Because they're just these blocks, right? What happens
within each autonomous system, which could be small or large, is of no concern to BGP, which is the
protocol that runs it. Inside, you can run whatever routing protocol you want. You could run the same
BGP, border gateway, inside, or you can run OSPF, which is open shortest path first, or you can run RIP,
which is a reliable internet, routing internet protocol. There are a number of other options
you can do. You can do static routing inside also, like manually configured static routing,
and check out, from the andres of the era that I described here, okay? So, what you do inside it,
inside it, AS or AD is up to you, but the main thing is, if you want to connect to the internet,
right, your border routers, right, must run BGP, which is how ASs do routing, okay? So, today,
routing is done, and then it's BGP level done on the basis of ASs or IDs, but they are still using IP
addresses for routing, right? The actual routers use IP addresses, and that's because for each AS or AD,
there is a bunch of IP prefixes associated. So, when you know a route to a particular AS,
you can associate a bunch of IP prefixes with it, okay? And that allows us to route IP back.
Right. So, as I said before, and you know, routing, mechanical actually, routing can be by explicit
IP addresses, but usually it's done by longest prefix match. Remember I discussed that? Longest prefix.
When the router looks in its table, it looks for the longest prefix. The longest prefix may actually
be an explicit address, the full address, or it may be some part of the address, like the preface,
but it looks for the longest prefix, because that's likely to be the best route.
Right. So, this is basically what I told you.
So, we're going to forget link state for now, and we're going to forget the dyke strap. I'm going to
look at Bellman Ford, right? And this is essentially what is at the heart of BGP today.
There are some pitfalls here, and some of the problems with routing aren't necessarily security
problems. They are sometimes reliability and fault tolerance problems, except often we cannot tell
what causes it, right? Is it like accidental malfunction, stupid operators,
just making mistakes, or is it, or implementation errors in the routing protocol implementation,
or an attack? So, one of the problems that occurs in distance vector protocol is what's called a
split horizon update. I don't should just understand how that works. So, I'm going to, this picture shows
you a kind of a very silly network, which is called a line network, where it's not very interesting,
right? But it happens in the real world, where you have essentially, well, these entities. You can
think of them as domains, or you can think of them as just routers or hosts. It doesn't really matter.
But the thick white lines represent direct connections, okay? So, the idea is, like in distance
vectors, I just tried to explain, that you see here, G1, it is directly connected to A.
So, what it does in a normal distance vector protocol, it says, look, it advertises. It tells everybody,
hey, hey, I have a hop one distance to A. Okay? So, it informs G2. It cannot inform anybody else,
right? It just, well, it can inform A, but A already knows. So, it informs G2. And so, they quickly,
and then G2 says, oh, and good news, wonderful. And now I have a two hop route to A. So, it advertises to G3.
And G3 says, yay, I have a three hop route to A. Oh, why? And G2, right? And then, so on. And G4 lands it
with a distance four. Finally, G5 lands it. After a bit, it says, I have a five hop route to A. Okay.
But suppose the link here goes down. Maybe an accident, maybe a hack, we don't care.
Something bad happens. And this G1 and A get disconnected. So, what the protocol does,
naively, G2 says, I have a route of length two to A. Remember that? From the previous slide.
So, G1 says, I have a route with a length infinity. I cannot reach A. The link is down.
Right? That's a fact. So, when the link is down, you're supposed to mark something with infinity.
Because you cannot destination unreachable. But, G2 remembers good news from the previous slide.
And it says, I can get to G1. Sorry, I can get to A in two hops. Remember, distance vector does not
remember routes. It remembers distances and next hop. That's how it's specified.
So, basically, what will happen is, G1 will say, all right, two is better than infinity.
Strictly less. So, now I have a route of length three to eight. That's what G1 thinks.
And then it starts sending packets. Right? To G1. Sorry, if G1 has packets to A,
we'll send it to G2. G2 will send it back to G1. G1 will then send it to two. And there's a loop.
Okay? So, there you have it. And then, what's called is, they're counting to infinity. Because
as they realize, oh, well, you know, there's no path of length two, they're going to increment it. Right?
One by one. And it keeps going. It's called counting to infinity problem. Okay?
Now, once you understand the problem, the solution is easy. Okay? The solution is easy. It says,
you know, do not advertise on the same interface that your receipts are. That is, do not re-advertise.
Do not tell me that I can reach things in. Do you follow?
So, as they exchange routing tables, they both start incrementing, right, by one, the cost to get to A.
A is completely unreachable. There's no way to reach A. But they both think that there is a way to reach.
Just the cost goes up. And this can take for a very long time. Infinity is a large number.
Or whatever the number of bits reserved for the hop count, right, eventually will overrun. So,
if you start, if you stop doing that, right, so you don't, you don't advertise, re-advertise a route
on the interface you received it from. That solves the problem. But it only solves the problem if you
have these kind of very small loops. Does that make sense?
Now, link state does not have this problem. Remember how I described link state? In a link state
protocol, every node in the network receives an entire map of the network. So, loops are impossible.
And so, that's why BGP, one of the reasons, BGP today is what's called path vector. So, it works like a
distance vector, but with a, with a twist, with a, with a, with a, like a, a little bit extra feature.
That, in addition to every table, it's actually every node.
So, normally, a distance vector table would be like this. You will have three columns,
and here will be destination, uh, cost,
next hop. Right, that's a distance vector table. And here it will say something like, I don't know,
uci.edu. I'm just, I'm not putting it, it could be numeric, okay, but I'm just putting, let's say,
some prefix corresponding to uci.edu. And, uh, this could be, I don't know, 12, meaning 12 hops away.
And the next hop is, uh, well, depending, if this is, I don't know, uh, uci.davis,
that, that's the table at uci.davis, and this would be the next hop is, uh, ucla.
Okay, that's how a distance vector table sort of looks like. But, in BGP,
this is not next hop, but that, entire path. So, this will be like uci.edu, uh, I don't know,
SoCal, uh, blah, blah, blah, com, cox.net, et cetera, et cetera. Right? So, it will be a sequence of,
uh, of hops, of actual hops that you have to take, like, a full rep.
One of the reasons this is done is to avoid loops. Right? If you know the actual path, right?
You can see when there are loops, right? You will see that, for example, something is,
you are about to add yourself to the path, and you're already there. That's a loop. Right?
So, this allows you to avoid loops. The other reason BGP is like this,
anybody want to guess why? Remember, this is for the internet, right? Worldwide.
Any idea?
It's not a, it's not a trivial question. If you're not familiar with internet,
individually, it has to do with politics.
The internet covers the world. Right? Pretty much every country has access to the internet.
Every country has at least one AS. At least one.
Countries provide transit services, right?
This explicit remuneration of the path is there so that countries can decide,
oh, I don't want to take this path. I prefer this other path.
Okay? So, for example, if you're sending packets, if you're sending traffic from here to India,
maybe you don't want to transit Iran, even though they offer attractive transit service.
Right? Or maybe if you're in South Korea and you want to go, you know, connect to Mongolia,
you don't want to go through North Korea, even though they'll promise you amazing transit service.
Okay? That's why.
So, if this, if you have just distance vector that shows you the distance and the next path,
you don't know the route, right? But when you, with path vector, which is what the GP is,
you actually not only know the distance, but you also know the cost, but you also know the actual path.
But the path is not at the level of ID routers. The path is at the level of domain.
Does that make sense? Because you don't really care, and it's too much, it's really TMI to know which hops you'll take.
What's important is which domains you will cross. In other words, who is going to look at your traffic?
So, fundamentally, it works just like distance vector, right? The adjacent routers exchange
their routing tables, but the routing tables also contain, you know, in addition to the distance,
these paths, right? So, and you can have multiple paths, and there's another thing. You can, in fact,
should have multiple paths for each destination, because you may prefer one path over another.
Like, for example, if you have only one path to get to, I don't know, Mongolia, and it goes to North Korea,
you don't have a choice. If you don't like North Korea, you don't communicate with Mongolia.
But, you know, there is internet, it's very unlikely there is only one path, right? Maybe you can go
through Russia. Could be a little safe, or not? I mean, you can go through, you know, Leos,
low Earth orbit satellites. I gotta do that. Everybody's favorite, Elon Musk.
That's a domain, by the way, right? The Starlink system is a domain, is an internet domain. It's just
not on, it's not on this Earth, but it's still a domain, right? So, you communicate via the internet,
you go, you go to the satellite, for the satellite, then you, you're transiting a satellite domain.
It's barely.
So, here's a BGP example, just that makes it a little bit, perhaps a little more. So, here we have a very
small toy network, right? These are, these are domain, or ASs, right? Autonomic systems. So,
not individual hosts. So, here we have, these are strangely connected networks, but the main thing
is that, for example, AS2, right? The one in the middle, provides transit service for 7. It's
a kind of a transit domain. So, basically, traffic to and from 7 goes through 2, except for 8, right?
8 can reach 7. So, what does 2 advertise? 2 says, well, sorry, 7 says, hello, to its neighbors, right?
I don't know how to reach anybody, but I'm 7, and I'm one hop away from you.
And 2 says, to its neighbors, hello, I'm 2, and if you want to reach 7, you got to go for me,
and the path is to 7. So, like, 1, the main 1 says, oh, if I want to go to 7, I have to,
the path is first 2, then 7, and that's it, right? That's the path.
The vector, right? And they, let's see, 3 and 6, in turn, also advertise to their neighbors,
that if you want to go to 7, you got to go for them, right? So, 3 says to 4. You want to go to 7?
That's me, right? And the path is 3, 2, 7. And 5 learns that the path to 7 is 6, 2, 7.
You see the fundamental difference here. Sometimes it's not, it's not, it's a little subtle, right?
So, in development 4, or the distance vector, path vector protocols, nobody computes the routes,
like, from a graph. You follow? In link state, everybody actually gets a graph,
information about the complete graph, and computes, cranks the, you know, the Dijkstra's protocol,
and computes the route to every destination. Here, you don't compute the route. You kind of,
like, adjust your tables. So, computationally, that's the claim, it's an argument going on for
50 years among networking people and theory people, so which particle is better?
Nobody knows, but one claim is that, oh, well, this one is computationally less costly, yeah?
And so, finally, like, again, I'm not going to go through the whole example, but, you know,
and then 5 says, oh, I'm 5, and sends to his neighbors, and then 6 re-advertises that,
and then the 2 learns to get to 5, you have to go for 6, and then, et cetera, et cetera, right? Okay?
Enough, right?
So, everybody learns like that. So, this slide is, unfortunately, woefully outdated.
I don't know, it's like 8 years old, at least. Sorry about that. But nothing is lower than what you see.
Numbers are higher. So, BGP routing tables, 125,000 address prefixes, right? Typical BGP routing tables.
That's not ASs. I mean, although routing is done at AS level, it's still prefixes, right?
And these prefixes map to about 70,000 to 80,000. Map the paths. Why such disparity?
Why there are, like, about a magnitude more prefix or IP prefixes than there are paths?
Many prefixes live in the same AS, right? So, right, the IP prefixes, you know, at endpoints,
right? We don't route to transit domains, right? Why would you, you know, normally, right? You don't
communicate. There's no web server in a giant, fast, 500,000 dollar router in the middle of the internet.
Right? You don't go to it. You go to the endpoints, yeah? Or CDNs, right? Sort of endpoints.
Okay? So, that's one. There are way more destination prefixes than there are paths. So,
many of them live in the same place. Like, UCI probably has a bunch of IP prefixes.
But anybody who wants to route packets to UCI still uses the same path to get to them.
I think that figure is about double. So, there are probably, like, 20,000 BGP routers.
But mind you, when I say BGP routers, I mean border routers are all autonomous systems.
And every autonomous system, right here, must have at least one if it's a stub autonomous system,
meaning it's like the endpoint, right? And at least two if it provides transit services.
But usually, if it provides transit services, like NISP is kind of a transit service, like COX
or AT&T, they'll have hundreds of BGP routers.
Okay. Again, there's probably about 3,000 ASs today. Don't know. You can probably look this up
very quickly. Somebody should look up on Google and tell me how many ASs there are today.
Definitely more than 2,000. But this information should be available.
Some 6,000 or so. That probably did not change very much. But 6,000 organizations own prefixes,
meaning they have registered prefixes that are assigned to them. There's parts of the IP address space
that is fixed for them. And this is still the case, I believe. I think I recently saw a paper
where they confirm that this is still the case. So what does that mean? It means on the internet,
things are not as far as you think, in terms of like how many ASs you transit on the way to the
destination. So think about it. This says an average route length for internet traffic is less than four.
And this is length in terms of AS hops, not in terms of like IP router hops.
IP router hops is my favorite number, but in terms of AS hops is less than four. And what it tells you is that
there's the AS where the packet starts and AS where the packet ends. That's two.
And there's at least one transit usually, right? Unless the two ASs are connected, which is usually
not the case. But so there's like three is kind of a given. But then think about the real world,
right? You could be connecting to like, I don't know, Solomon Islands, or Madagascar, or somewhere
in the North Pole to a US Arctic station. And still, there may be AS paths that are longer, like six or
seven, but the average is less than four, which means the average is like source domain, destination
domain, and two transits in the middle. Yeah?
But that happens to average most of my requests. I'm not going to the North Pole. I'm going probably
somewhere within America. Okay, you are within the US. So you're going to
Google, right?
The route length is probably three.
That's my guess. But you can do a tracer route, and from tracer route, not always, but you can often
deduce how many AS hubs. Because tracer route might give you a reverse DNS lookup,
which might actually give you that, not this VIP address of what hubs your packets are taking,
but the actual host name. And so by the host name, you can tell the domain. And the domain often tells
you that that's a different AS. Does that make sense? So it has to be that at least three, maybe four,
you know? I mean, let's say you go to, I don't know, state of Florida government website, maybe it will
be four in that case, you know? Or some small department in the University of Lower East South Dakota
somewhere. Yeah. But that's my guess. But it has to be at least three.
So, I don't know if it's surprising, most people get surprised by this, that it's such a small number
of AS hubs. And 50% of the routes are less than four, and that's, tells you like that's the typical
thing, right? Source domain, source AS, one transit, and the destination. 95 of them are less than five,
five. Which means you really have to try hard to get, to hop through more than five domains.
And mind you, internet includes, I think it also includes like cellular, for example,
you're using your phone, right? And you don't have Wi-Fi access, or you're just not using Wi-Fi.
But you're still using IP, right? And so you do IP over cellular. So you're still kind of,
in fact, a part of the internet.
Alright, so,
a lot of problems in BGP, not just BGP, but other routing protocols, but BGP has been susceptible to it,
is something called black-holing. Black-holing is when a router
advertises routes that are too good. Right? And it's like, I have a distance one route to everyone.
Okay? And so, what happens? Like bees and honey, right? To use a more polite analogy,
everybody starts sending traffic to me. Okay? Which is problematic in two cases, right? First,
if this happens accidentally, I get swamped. Clearly, right? Because everybody says, oh,
forget all the other routes I have. This guy has route one distance to everybody. Must be amazing.
So everybody starts sending traffic to me. There's congestion near me. I get totally, you know,
strangled. Nobody can communicate to anybody, right? Because everybody's sending traffic to me
that I can't handle. Right? So, big problem. Black-holing, right? But it can also be done
maliciously. So it has happened accidentally. It has happened maliciously. When somebody says,
I don't like this company over here. This, I don't know, this whistleblower.com. I don't like them.
So I'm going to advertise a very low dislike. I'm one hop from whistleblower.com.
So essentially, she's like, send me their traffic. Send me their traffic. So I can just discard it.
Okay? This has happened as well. Back in prehistory, before you all were born, 97,
was already after the birth of the web. That was the day the internet died. I remember it.
This Florida ISP de-aggregated its BGP routing tables and basically re-agnetized it. It basically
said what I just described. It said, I'm neighbors with everybody. Bam! The internet just crawled
first like slow down like within seconds. Okay? So it has best route to everywhere on the internet.
And of course, it has to happen in Florida. Right? The most intellectual state in the nation.
Also, today, this is not the case, but the original BGP protocol or sort of the virgin BGP protocol,
the vanilla one, has no security. Again, designed for a friendly internet, right? So no authentication,
no integrity. Right? Today, it still doesn't, but there's something called BGP sec, which is the,
like IP sec for BGP basically, kind of like. And it establishes secure tunnels
between adjacent BGP routers. So it sends that updates over those secure tunnels.
Now, that prevents somebody from injecting packets, right? Or modifying packets between two adjacent
routers. But it does not prevent the malicious router from advertising, uh, from advertising valid,
uh, sort of, uh, malicious routes because, you know, it's, it's, it has a secure connection.
So this, this has happened a number of paths. So this is, uh, just for you to read.
This is back in 2003, I think. So YouTube has been around for a long time, right? YouTube actually
predates Google, even though Google owns it, uh, today. But, uh, so YouTube was popular already in
early 2000. So YouTube advertises, see, this is IP prefix. You know, everyone knows this notation,
you know, 22 bits, okay? Um, so it says here on YouTube, you know, and, uh, it's as an AS, right?
It's called, you see there it says AS three, three, six, five, six, one, three, six, five, six, one,
is the autonomous system ID assigned to YouTube. I think it's still in case today. Yeah.
What do you mean by YouTube for names?
Google. Well, I think YouTube was there. YouTube was a company.
I think it came, like, seven years later. Like 2005, it was YouTube.
Wait. 2008. Okay. Do a quick Wikipedia from here.
I did. And? Google was 98. YouTube was 2005.
Google was 98? Nobody heard of it until, like, 2003 or something.
Sure. But even then, YouTube stole them.
So it's later? Yeah, a little bit later.
But it wasn't part of Google. No, it wasn't right now.
Okay. So at least I got one thing right.
Okay. Uh, so there's your YouTube advertising to the rest of the of the world that here I am.
And here the Pakistani government decided that it doesn't like YouTube.
And so a Pakistani ISP, right, telecom, telecom, that is 7557,
advertising, see that 24?
Right? 2865 and 52.
So it basically says, I subsume.
This is a, this is, this is saying, I subsume YouTube.
So all worldwide YouTube traffic went to Pakistan.
For a little bit.
They had to manually intervene.
And it was a two hour outage.
People were incensed.
Valuable videos were not watched.
There were other incidents that one interesting one was the spammers.
So we have a, if we get to it, because we're moving very slow in this class, but steady.
If we get to it, there's a lecture on spam.
But, you know, spammers hijacked a bunch of, a bunch of, kind of a segment of IP prefixes,
allocated to Northrop Grumman, a company you might have heard of, defense company, very large,
located here in Southern California, among other places.
So it was an unused block of addresses that was allocated to Northrop Grumman since like 20 years
before that, okay?
They were, God knows what they were supposed to use it for, but it was allocated to them.
Now, a bunch of spammers hijacked that.
They just used those addresses to send spam.
But guess what happened?
I don't know if they intended it or not, but one, one important consequence is
that because of their, there were already anti-spam measures, the entire block wound up on the, on the, on the, on the, basically blacklist.
Okay?
So, took two months to actually manually reclaim ownership of those addresses and remove them from the blacklist.
Then there was this Malaysian ISP, also that hijacked the prefix of Yahoo.
Nobody knows if it was accidental or political, not sure what Malaysia has against Yahoo, I don't think, probably it was accidental.
This was more like, more likely to have been political, the Turkish ISP did this in 2004.
But similar thing to what the Pakistan ISP did in a previous slide.
This is a much more recent, this is only four years ago.
Maybe you remember, there was a Facebook outage.
And this was, this was accidental, but could have been malicious, but in this case, actually, no, Facebook, basically, itself, didn't do itself.
It withdrew routes of, of, of its prefixes from the DNS servers.
And basically, nobody could resolve Facebook addresses anymore.
Which means, what, like, it's not that Facebook couldn't be accessed.
Facebook was up and running.
But if you type facebook.com, the DNS would not be able to tell you the IP address.
Okay?
So if you had cached, and some people did this, I remember there was a discussion on the forums.
It's like, if you had actually cached the IP address of Facebook, that you could actually type the IP address in the URL, right?
You do know that you can actually substitute the domain name with the IP address.
In your, like, type it in, in your URL.
Well, if you did that, it would work.
But if you type in facebook.com, it wouldn't.
Because, basically, Facebook shot itself in the book.
But it happened, not because of DNS, it did happen because of BGP.
Right?
Because BGP, right, withdrew address prefixes for Facebook's DNS servers.
And when you resolve facebook.com, you can sell Facebook DNS servers.
Okay.
Switch over.
Domain name service.
Nice transition.
Designed by a guy from here.
Got a PhD around 82, 83.
In ICS.
And I met him a bunch of times.
In fact, I worked in the same organization that he, that he was for a few years.
So a guy's name is Paul Macapetrius.
He's kind of a serial entrepreneur these days.
Not much of a researcher or a scientist.
But back in the early 80s, he worked in a place up in Marina del Rey.
Called Information Sciences Institute.
Which is part of USC School of Engineering.
And basically like a research used to be.
Today it's just a development shop.
But back then it was a research think tank.
They did a lot of AI research.
They did a lot of like defense optics and electronics research.
And they did intern research.
So some of the like IP for example.
TCP IP were partly developed there.
At this USC ISI.
So this guy, Paul Macapetrius, he was a staff researcher there.
And he, people say he invented DNS.
There's no such thing as invented DNS.
DNS is a architecture.
What he did is that he realized that there was, the internet was growing.
Even already then, like in the early 80s.
And there needs to be a way to map the human readable host names.
Like foob.bar.com into IP addresses like 128, 195, 2.3.
Which nobody can remember.
Right?
Even back then it was a pain.
So he's the one that sort of realized it first.
And then came up with the first kind of cut implementation.
Of what we today call DNS.
Now DNS has evolved a lot.
It's not like IP.
IP kind of remained, IPv4 remained static since 1980 till what?
Early 40, 45 years.
But DNS evolved.
But the idea behind it is the same.
It's supposed to resolve, right?
IP domain names or host names.
And give you back IP addresses.
It's a hierarchical system.
Okay?
And without it the internet would grind to a halt.
Right?
In the domain name service today, the domain name system is as important as a routing protocol.
So without routing, the internet dies.
Without DNS, the internet dies.
Not right away necessarily, right?
Because if you cache some DNS addresses, you might not be able to.
You might be able to use the internet for a little bit.
So after a while, I'll be back.
And there are a bunch of these.
What's the root servers?
Anyway, so root servers are like the gods of DNS.
Like they know, they know stuff.
And they are replicated, right?
So they are replicated for fault tolerance and load distribution, load balancing, okay?
Around the world.
And they're not like, there's no like DI there.
They're not trying to be equitable, right?
Or fair.
The reason they are where they are is because of like heavy internet communication.
So they're not trying to say, oh, we should put one in Australia.
Because Australia is a continent.
We should put one in Africa.
We should put one in, I don't know, Siberia.
No.
The idea is, where is the like heaviest communication?
Right?
So it's not driven by so much geopolitical or fairness doctrine, but rather practical stuff.
But where is the traffic?
Most of the traffic, right?
So that's why you see nothing in South America.
South America, as far as the internet goes, is not a powerhouse.
Not a health.
I mean, people obviously use the internet here.
But not as heavily as other places.
Africa, nothing.
Australia, nothing.
This whole chunk of Asia, right?
Or Eurasia, nothing.
But there is something in Japan.
Okay?
And that one must have been more historic, because Japan was one of the first to adopt the internet.
Back in the 70s, or early 80s.
So we have nearby this USCISI, the Marine and Array, that has two root services.
One is actually operated by them, and then is operated by ICANN.
Internet something authority.
It's the organization, non-profit organization that manages essentially the gaming and all kinds of high-level issues for the internet.
And then here, Northern California is a bunch, and then on the East Coast.
Some of these are companies, Verisign and Cogent are companies.
Verisign has been bought, I think.
Then there is another very exciting.
Okay?
Then there is ARL Army Research Lab, US Department of Defense, University of Maryland, Grand One, etc.
So you get to see.
Then London has, and then Stockholm has something.
So these are giant, I mean giant in terms of power, not in size, machines.
They get a lot of traffic.
They are super well connected.
Okay?
They have very high bandwidth wires, essentially, or lines connected to them.
Multiple ones.
Okay?
So they should be able to withstand a lot of traffic.
Simultaneously.
Okay?
And so there is this whole architecture for the root that I won't get into that essentially makes
them fault tolerant.
So there have been a number of attacks trying to take down, because if you take down the root service,
you bring down DNS.
But they're very hard to take down.
So what is the root, right?
So remember I showed you a bunch of them, right?
But every root is essentially the same.
There is a root DNS server that is responsible for what's called the dot domain.
The dot.
And then below the dot, you have the top level domains.
Like .com, .net, .org, .iju, etc., .tw for Taiwan, .jp for Japan, .au for Australia.
There are others, there are others like that, okay?
National level domains.
But these are top.
And then .com will be like here, right?
Google.com, etc., etc.
These are authoritative domains for like organizations.
WordPress, Wikipedia, Harvard, etc., right?
So UCI would be under HTML, of course.
And then, yeah, I'm not showing you all the levels that were the hierarchy, because obviously,
actually, UC.edu would be here.
Maybe UCI would be under UC.
Not sure about that.
Don't quote me.
How does a DNS actually work?
Well, when you type in a human readable post name, okay?
Whether it's facebook.com, google.com, you know, dailymail.com.uk, whatever the heck.
Whatever it is you type it in, you have in your device, not in your browser.
It's not part of your browser.
It's in your device.
You have the network configuration.
How many of you have to look at network configuration?
Oh, nobody's still curious?
They do.
Okay.
Well, you know, when you look in your Mac or your Windows machine, it will tell you like,
okay, here's your ID address, right?
Okay?
Here's your router.
It's all there.
It will also tell you, here's your DNS server.
It's usually configured, like, when you connect to the wireless, it's configured dynamically.
You can also configure it manually.
Like, you can put, I don't know, 8888, I think that's the Google DNS, right?
You can configure it manually or you can do it, you can just get it from the network,
from the local network that you are connected to.
Anyway, so this is your, what's called, local DNS recursive resolver.
This is the DNS agent essentially you go to for all your queries.
You don't go to the root.
Okay?
Because you don't know its address and even if you did, you wouldn't talk to it.
So you come to the DNS resolver and it says, oh, I want to resolve WWICS UCIEDU.
I don't know.
I don't know what that is.
Not always.
Sometimes it does already, if it's cached.
But it says, generally it says, I don't know what this is.
But let me ask the root.
The root is God.
So God should know.
So he goes, WWICS UCIEDU, can you tell me?
And he says, no, but I give you a nameserver record.
This is what NSD is.
So here's a record for UCIEDU, which I've heard of.
Okay?
Then, I'm a bit abstracting it here, because actually at the top there, there might be like
root and root will give you a pointer to EDU server.
Okay?
But then I'm abstracting it away.
Then it says, okay, here is a, and nameserver record to UCIEDU.
So you go here, you get this back, and then you quickly say, okay, now I can contact UCIEDU.
So I tell it, hey, I'm trying to resolve ICS UCIEDU.
And it returns to you the nameserver record.
It says, yeah, I'm UCIEDU.
I know about ICS UCIEDU.
Here is its address.
So you go here, and you say, I want to resolve WWICS UCIEDU.
And he says, oh, well, I do know WWS, the web server for ICS.
And it returns to you the actual IP address.
So this, as you see, is not an easy, like, ask a query, get back a reply.
It's a set of recursive queries.
How many?
Depends.
There are some hierarchies that are quite deep.
So it may go on for more than three handshakes like this.
That's why sometimes when you type, and the internet is not down, but you can see that there's a delay.
Right?
Have you seen that?
You're connected, the internet is working fine, but there's this delay.
And the delay is typically not because of your loading pages.
It's, I mean, it can be, but more often than not, the delays become DNS.
Okay.
Now, to reduce the load on DNS servers, which, as you can imagine, are very busy bees, right?
Because they're popular.
Everybody goes to the DNS servers.
So to reduce the load, the responses are cached.
So your local resolver here, this local DNS recursive resolver, will keep a cache of recent responses.
Okay?
How this cache is maintained depends on something called TTL, time to live.
It could be, it could be your ISP.
Because, like, when you go home, right, and you connect, I don't know if you, there's a wire,
wire also connecting in a dorm or, let's say you go to your parents' home, okay?
You have an, they have an ISP probably, right?
I mean, they're, they're buying internet from somebody, right?
And when you, when you open your laptop, the DNS resolver's name will be, will be in the configuration.
I usually there.
It is possible to run the DNS resolver locally.
You can run, install a DNS resolver on your local machine.
I don't recommend it necessarily, because you need to know what you're doing.
Yeah?
Yeah.
Because we can choose our DNS resolver by ourselves, can we choose the AS for the BGP routing path?
No.
No, you may not.
Because you don't route at the ASL, you don't run BGP.
The, if you are, let's say, customer of Cox.net, of Cox, internet, right?
Or AT&T, they pick it around.
Right?
Which AS, so you don't have, if they decide to send packets through North Korea, you have no control.
They have control.
They can say, I want to, I want to send packets through, I don't know, New Zealand instead of North Korea.
They can prefer one or the other, but you have no control.
Okay, so, as I said, the responses are cached.
And this is like sometimes, you know how you mistype something?
Mistype an address and it goes, name not, host not found or something.
And you keep clicking return and it just like, it doesn't, it very quickly does host not found, host not found.
Because it cached.
It doesn't want to bother the DNS server just to find out that host not found.
So that's one reason.
The other reason is if you are going to, you know, communicate to the same host.
Like if you're going to Facebook multiple times, it doesn't need to resolve it every single time.
Right?
You can just like, cache it in the local resolver and tell you.
It's faster that way.
All right.
So that's called negative queries, right?
They're cached.
Cached records are timed out periodically.
The time to live is subject to what the DNS tells you.
Okay, so DNS server that returns a particular record tells you.
Okay, here's the IP or here's the IP address for this host name.
You can cache this for whatever, 200 seconds.
Okay?
Or here's an IP address for something else and you can cache it for 10 seconds.
So it has a TTL field, every cache.
And so here it will say, it's just another example of a query.
It will tell you that here the TTL might be already there, right?
And ICS.
You might not need to go to the root, right?
And the reason is before, remember the previous example where we're looking at WWICSUCID?
Well, the local resolver, after that, having done that,
already knows that you don't need to go to the root.
You don't need to go to the ICSUCID.
You can just go to ICS-CCID that will resolve everything that ends with ICS-CCID.
So because we already resolved WWW, we can just resolve FTP ICS-CCID by going directly here.
Right?
Because we cached.
So this slide connects to one of the previous slides, right?
Where I showed how to resolve WWW.
All right.
So DNS by itself has no security.
It, how does it know, like, when a local resolver issues a query, right?
It says to the root review server, it says here, here's WWICSUCID.
You give me the idea, guys.
How does it know that the reply is to that query?
Because it might actually, the local resolver might issue many queries.
So, the way it's done, the sort of primitive authentication, there is a 16-bit transaction ID
that every query contains, okay?
So local resolver issues a query includes a 16-bit transaction ID.
When it comes back, it should have the same transaction ID that allows it to associate.
Request with reply.
Make sense?
Kind of a primitive authentication.
Now, it's obviously insecure, because if you have an adversary, it can do the following.
Again, this is like the classical example of DNS proofing.
So, I want you to consider an adversary that has a specific victim in mind.
Now, let's say him.
So, this guy's going to be the victim.
Yeah, you, sorry.
I know his name.
Let's say his name is Joe, right?
Joe is my victim.
I know Joe's email address.
I'm going to send him an, or maybe a phone phone, even better, a cell phone.
Either or, but cell phone is better.
I can send him either a text with a link, or an email with a link, right?
You know, I am the widow of the prince of Nigeria.
You know, I'm about to transfer you $5 million, but just send me your bank account,
and if you want details, I'm going to share my fortune with you.
So, basically, the idea is that he is to get him to click on a link.
Okay?
And the link will have some innocuous looking address, like host1 at foo.com,
where foo.com could be a totally benign domain, okay?
Benign, not necessarily adversarial domain, right?
It could be a bank, for example.
So, he clicks.
The clicking on that link will cause a DNS lookup, right?
Extract the name, the host name, the domain name, and do a DNS lookup.
So, that's him, Joe.
Client.
Whether he clicks on an SMS, a link, an SMS, right?
Or, iMessage, or WhatsApp, doesn't matter, right?
Or, an email.
But the interesting part here is that I know about the time that he does that.
That's why I say SMS is preferred, or text is preferred, because if I know he's a curious
George, he's going to like, I'm going to send him, and very quickly, he's going to click.
And, fishers know how to do this.
So, now what I do, as an adversary, I know that he's going to issue a DNS query to a local resolver,
so resolve host1 foo.com, right?
The local resolver says, oh, let me go to the name server for foo.com, okay?
There's some, I'm skipping the root and the .com, et cetera, right?
I'm just going to the root, to the last bit, et cetera.
Okay.
Now, at this point, or at that time, roughly that time,
the adversary makes a guess of their transaction ID.
Remember, each DNS query has a transaction ID, 16 bits.
2 to the 16, not a small number, right?
How big is this, 32,000?
Something like that.
So, your probability of guessing the correct transaction ID is low, right?
So, what the adversary does, he doesn't know the transaction ID, because we're not assuming
the adversary is actually nearby and listening, right?
In this example, this is why this attack is interesting.
The adversary could be very far away.
Like, Joe would be working for a defense counter or a government agency before.
I'm not anywhere near him.
I cannot snoop on this.
If I snoop, I wouldn't need to guess, right?
But I don't snoop, which makes the attack more interesting.
So, what I do is I guess a transaction ID, and I generate a fake reply.
See that first one?
Guess transaction ID.
HostFood.com is at 6666.
Make another guess.
Okay?
Another transaction ID.
HostFood.com is at 6666.
Okay?
So, I can generate a very large number of these kind of guessed transaction ID replies.
Not infinite, right?
I mean, I cannot generate maybe 32,000.
Maybe I can generate a couple of hundred in close proximity and send them to the victim, to Joe.
Bam.
Now, eventually, this DNS server will reply with a correct IP address for Foo.com, as it's supposed to.
This is not malicious.
This is a good reply, appropriate for that query.
But do you see what the problem happens?
If the adversary, in one of these guesses, guesses correctly, and beats the reply from the actual DNS server,
he wins the game.
Very important that you see that.
Do you?
Not ask.
All the adversary needs to do.
Now, I know, the bar is high, but the adversary needs to do this.
Guess the correct, so the transaction ID guessed by the adversary must match this.
And the, one of the red replies from the adversary, right, must come before this one.
Before the legitimate reply.
It's a probabilistic game.
Okay?
The adversary may lose.
There is.
But if he wins one of a hundred, the rewards are interesting.
He can try to guess as fast as possible.
He can pre-compute the guesses, right?
He doesn't need to, right?
He just, like, can pre-compute random replies, right?
And send them all at the same time.
Or roughly at the same time.
Bam, bam, bam, bam, bam.
As fast as possible.
Now, he doesn't know exactly when the client generates this query.
But he can guess, right?
Like, I send him an SMS, and I know the kind of person he is.
Like, maybe I know something about you.
Like, I know you replied to SMS quickly, right?
I know you're going to click it for the next five seconds, right?
Like this.
So, in those five seconds, I start generating those replies.
You, if you don't expect those replies, you'll just throw them away.
Your laptop, your phone will just ignore them.
You, as a user, will not know.
Right?
Because whenever unsolicited DNS replies arrive at your computer or your phone,
you, as a user, are not notified.
They're just thrown away.
Because nobody's expecting them.
So they're thrown out.
But if one of them comes back and matches the transaction ID, bam,
the real one will be ignored because it will arrive later.
So, if the attacker loses the game, he has to wait until the TTL, the time to live,
and this legitimate reply expires.
But the attacker is a patient.
You can try again.
HostFoo.com, Host3Foo.com, et cetera.
But why do that, right?
Right?
What's the point of hijacking that?
What's the point of getting somebody to click on HostFoo.com?
Or Foo.com at all?
And that is actually pretty easy.
So, the idea is that Foo.com could be a legitimate entity, like a bank or insurance company,
a university, or so on.
So, if you trick and succeed, right?
If you trick the client and actually guess the correct transaction ID, you can put a very long time to live.
Very long, maximum possible.
And now you know that whenever the client goes to anything, Foo.com, he's going to reuse the cash entry.
Aha.
So, now, the reply actually could be, I don't know where Host1Foo.com is, but I know the authoritative nameset report.
So, this is like raising the bar a little bit.
Instead of telling the, no, no, here's the host one, Foo.com, it says the authoritative nameserver lives at NS2Foo.com,
and its address is 6666.
Okay, so this is slightly different from what I showed in the previous slide.
The previous slide, what you saw is the tricking once, right, for one host.
Basically saying, oh, host1Foo.com lives at 6666.
This is a much broader scope.
This attack, which is very similar, but it's broader scope.
It says, if you guess the correct transaction ID, you can make sure that this client, from now on,
when it resolves anything, Foo.com, will go to adversarially controlled nameserver,
which is run by the adversarially.
Which is run by the adversarially there.
So now, if you win the race, this reply, legitimate reply, will be ignored, discarded.
And the attacker essentially will make sure that all subsequent, all future DNS requests for anything,
anything.foo.com, will go to 6666.
A malicious DNS server, fully controlled by the adversary, no need to win any future races.
Okay?
So much better investment of time for the adversary.
All right.
By the way, what can cause a DNS lookup?
Maybe you already know this, but just about anything.
A small ad in a webpage.
Okay?
Tiny.
You don't need JavaScript.
If JavaScript is enabled, it's easy, much easier, but you don't even need JavaScript.
But, like, a DNS hello, mail, oh, mail servers.
Mail servers are a pain in the ass, because, you know, if your mail servers will look up a lot of,
do a lot of DNS queries, right?
Telnet does a lot of DNS queries.
Spam checks do DNS queries.
Files, deliveries, all kinds of stuff.
So, triggering the DNS query is easy, but the best example I can think of is just sending him,
let's say, the victim a text message of some sort, right?
Because, and the nice thing about text messages is they're generally fast, right?
And users pay more attention somehow to them, especially in our more phone-centric culture.
Also, links are easier to hide, right?
Somehow, when you see something on a big screen, you might see something suspicious about the link,
or is it a text message is less like?
Okay, well, we're out of time.
See you next Tuesday.
Oh, because someone asked, if you are a PhD student who wants to include this course in the comprehensive exam,
in order not to have the exam, the actual exam, which is separate, you need to get an A to A plus, right?
So you get an A, at least an A in the course.
A plus is on the other thing.
But if you get an A in the course, you don't need to take the exam.
Let's remember the Karamel amp PP those who is per sorrichten.
Let's see you next time.
Bye.
Bye bye.
We had a great idea.
So these is a followup of the following plan.
Have a good time.
We're always having about a copy.
So we're not making an A a plus.
We're just walking the walk.
We hope we don't know how to add along.